<mediawiki xmlns="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10/ http://www.mediawiki.org/xml/export-0.10.xsd" version="0.10" xml:lang="en">
  <siteinfo>
    <sitename>Wikipedia</sitename>
    <dbname>enwiki</dbname>
    <base>https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Main_Page</base>
    <generator>MediaWiki 1.33.0-wmf.6</generator>
    <case>first-letter</case>
    <namespaces>
      <namespace key="-2" case="first-letter">Media</namespace>
      <namespace key="-1" case="first-letter">Special</namespace>
      <namespace key="0" case="first-letter" />
      <namespace key="1" case="first-letter">Talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2" case="first-letter">User</namespace>
      <namespace key="3" case="first-letter">User talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="4" case="first-letter">Wikipedia</namespace>
      <namespace key="5" case="first-letter">Wikipedia talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="6" case="first-letter">File</namespace>
      <namespace key="7" case="first-letter">File talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="8" case="first-letter">MediaWiki</namespace>
      <namespace key="9" case="first-letter">MediaWiki talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="10" case="first-letter">Template</namespace>
      <namespace key="11" case="first-letter">Template talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="12" case="first-letter">Help</namespace>
      <namespace key="13" case="first-letter">Help talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="14" case="first-letter">Category</namespace>
      <namespace key="15" case="first-letter">Category talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="100" case="first-letter">Portal</namespace>
      <namespace key="101" case="first-letter">Portal talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="108" case="first-letter">Book</namespace>
      <namespace key="109" case="first-letter">Book talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="118" case="first-letter">Draft</namespace>
      <namespace key="119" case="first-letter">Draft talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="710" case="first-letter">TimedText</namespace>
      <namespace key="711" case="first-letter">TimedText talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="828" case="first-letter">Module</namespace>
      <namespace key="829" case="first-letter">Module talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2300" case="first-letter">Gadget</namespace>
      <namespace key="2301" case="first-letter">Gadget talk</namespace>
      <namespace key="2302" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition</namespace>
      <namespace key="2303" case="case-sensitive">Gadget definition talk</namespace>
    </namespaces>
  </siteinfo>
  <page>
    <title>All Nepal Trade Union Federation (Revolutionary)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4365258</id>
    <revision>
      <id>836018879</id>
      <parentid>835876087</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-12T05:22:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>GünniX</username>
        <id>237572</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>/* External links */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3739">{{Infobox Union
|name= ANTUF
|country= [[Nepal]]
|affiliation= [[International Trade Union Confederation|ITUC]]
|members=More than 600 thousand
|full_name= All Nepal Federation of Trade Unions
|native_name=ANTUF
| image= Antufr.png
|founded=Co.Nara Bahadur Karmacharya
|current=
|head=Shalikram Jammakattel
|dissolved_date=2007
|dissolved_state= Nepal
|merged_into=
|office= Perisdanda-35, Kathmandu
|people= Shalikram Jammkattel
|website={{Url|http://www.antuf.org}}
|footnotes=
}}
&lt;!-- Include all unused fields for future use. See [[template talk:Infobox Union]] for usage. --&gt;

The '''All Nepal Federation of Trade Unions''' is claimed to be the largest [[National trade union center|trade union federation]] in Nepal. The president of the ANTUF is Shalikram Jammakattel and Baburam Gautam, Jay Jarki, Ganesh Regmi, Rajan Timilsena, Dhan Bdr Bk. and Jagat Simkhada are its main leaders.

'''All Nepal Federation of Trade Unions (ANTUF)''' is an [[umbrella organization]] for industry-wise [[Trade union federation|national trade union federations]]. It was established in 2007 with the prime motto of promoting and protecting the rights of workers. Decent work, complete social security of workers and democratic labour market is the primary concern of ANTUF.The [[General Federation of Nepalese Trade Unions]] (GEFONT) (Nepali: नेपाल ट्रेड यूनियन महासंघ) is a confederation of 20 national trade union federations. It is politically tied to the [[Communist Party of Nepal]] (Unified Marxist-Leninist). GEFONT declares its goal to be "Socialism for the dignified working class and prosperous life".
Registered in [[Labour Department]], [[Government of Nepal]], ANTUF has been intensifying its campaigns/activities in almost all the sectors from both formal and informal economy over the years. ANTUF has developed a number of trainers in different levels and established strong OSH national, regional/district and enterprises committees. Through regular training/orientation programs, it has not only organized more than 600,000 workers across the nation but also empowered them as well.
For past 7 years of its establishment, ANTUF has been constantly taking initiatives for the formation of [[Labour Law]], Trade Union Law and Social Security Bill. Furthermore, ANTUF has been actively lobbying for [[ratification]] and implementation of all Labour Laws, Social Security Act and ILO Core Conventions. It has been pressurizing concerned authorities/entities to address the fundamental rights of all workers through the promulgation of new constitution. ANTUF has also been raising issues at national level for the genuine representation of workers including women workers in the decision making body.
ANTUF strives for the democratic labor market and industrial development of nation that includes the end of [[feudalistic]] monarchy and the establishment of republic where political, socio-economic and workers rights are guaranteed. With its more than 600,000 levy paying members, ANTUF has now been the leading foundation for the major section of both formal and informal economy workers that always strive for overall [[Socioeconomics|socio-economic]] and political changes in the nation.
'''ANTUF's Assumptions:'''
ANTUF believes that state machinery has to be changed to ensure absolute rights of all the [[Working class|working-class]] people. With its firm conviction, ANTUF takes necessary initiation to bring workers’ friendly state machinery into practice.

==External links==
{{Portal|Organized labour}}
* {{Official website|http://www.antuf.org}}

[[Category:National trade union centers of Nepal]]
[[Category:National federations of trade unions]]


{{Asia-trade-union-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>3s4lbd5bnukwrrrzs7enot4lzkysywr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Apa Vie</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>779206</id>
    <revision>
      <id>532052998</id>
      <parentid>531565234</parentid>
      <timestamp>2013-01-09T00:38:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Addbot</username>
        <id>6569922</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>[[User:Addbot|Bot:]] Removing Orphan Tag (Nolonger an Orphan) ([[User_talk:Addbot|Report Errors]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="944">{{Unreferenced|date=December 2009}}
In [[Romanian mythology]], '''apa vie''' (literally translated as "Living Water" but more accurately as "Water of Life") means the [[water]] from which [[hero]]es drink so that they come back to life after healing their wounds.  
'''Apa moartǎ''' ("Dead Water" or "Water of Death") is the complement of '''apa vie'''. In the vast majority of the tales it has the power to heal wounds of dead bodies (but not to give life). Usually, reviving a dead person is done (in such tales) by putting this Dead Water on their wounds to heal them and then bring them back to life with Living Water, because the Living Water cannot heal the wounds of the dead, and even revived, the people would still bleed to death without being healed first. There is a small percent of tales in which '''apa moartǎ''' is a poisonous drink that kills any person who drinks it.


[[Category:Romanian mythology]]


{{Europe-myth-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>5f6tyklvj6k9hkhgupu4ipi89347k5n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Askia Isma'il</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>46440472</id>
    <revision>
      <id>834119499</id>
      <parentid>757211057</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-04T01:26:17Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>HeathIsling</username>
        <id>28733853</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2153">{{Infobox monarch|name=Askia Ismai'l|title=Emperor of the [[Songhai Empire]]|image=|full name=|birth_date=|death_date=|death_place=|date of burial=|place of burial=|predecessor=[[Askia Mohammad Benkan|Askia Benkan]] (1531-1537)|successor=[[Askia Ishaq I]] (1539-1549)|spouse=|issue=|royal house=|dynasty=Askia Dynasty|father=[[Askia Mohammad I]]|mother=Maryum Daabu|religion=[[Islam]]}}'''Askia Ismail''' was the sixth ruler of the [[Songhai Empire]] from 1537 – 1539, and fourth from the [[Askiya Dynasty|Askia dynasty]]. Ismail came to power through a conspiracy generated by [[Askia Mohammad I]], his father and founder of the Askia dynasty, with the aim of freeing Mohammad from captivity.

Directed to one of Mohammad’s Eunuchs, he was able to obtain gold. With this Ismail was then able to recruit men, allies and Suma Kutubaki, a friend of the ruling [[Askia Mohammad Benkan]]. The conspiracy came to fruition when Benkan was encamped at a village called Mansur. Benkan’s captains turned against him, he was deposed by the Dendi-fari, with the Dendi-fari capturing and chaining up most of Benkan’s inner circle.

Raised to power by the Dendi-fari, Askia Ismail was then able to release his father Askia Muhammad from Kangaba Island, bringing him home to Gao.

Ismail campaigned against the one called Bakabula in Gurma. Ismail gave charge of the cavalry to the Kurmina-fari. Ismail instructed the Kurmina-fari to chase and engage Bakabula and to hold out until Ismail arrived. In the ensuing battle the Kurmina-fari lost over 900 horsemen. However they succeeded in killing Bakabula and were able to take a large amount of booty. Shortly after this battle in December 1539 Ismail died.

==See==
*''[[Tarikh al-fattash]]'' - Chronicle giving the history of the Songhay Empire
*''[[Tarikh al-Sudan]]'' - Chronicle giving the history of the Songhay Empire

==External links==
*[http://www.tombouctoumanuscripts.org/ Tombouctou Manuscripts Project]

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ismail, Askia}}
[[Category:Songhai Empire]]
[[Category:History of Africa]]
[[Category:History of Mali]]
[[Category:16th-century deaths]]


{{Mali-bio-stub}}
{{Africa-royal-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>idagna2tpexq02omkxvowpcpvguoj9s</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bakhtar Institute of Higher Education</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17502939</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864466176</id>
      <parentid>837741416</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-17T11:44:33Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bakhtar.University</username>
        <id>34914371</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Added Some courses names</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1045">{{Unreferenced|date=May 2008}}

'''Bakhtar University''' (پوهنتون باختر) is an established private university in [[Afghanistan]]. It is in the capital city, [[Kabul]]. The university has developed a research and development cell and will issue its first journal, ''Bakhtar Journal of Advance Research'', soon.{{when?|date=April 2015}}

The university, for the first time in the history of Afghanistan, launched Masters programs in Business Administration and Computer Science. The university has well-qualified faculty hired mostly from Pakistan and India. Currently, the university offers MBA, MCS, BBA, BCS, BJR, BCE and LAW, and some diploma programs in the English language. 

== See also ==
*[[List of universities in Afghanistan]]

==External links==
* [http://www.bakhtar.edu.af/ www.bakhtar.edu.af]
{{Afghan universities}}

{{coord missing|Afghanistan}}

[[Category:Universities in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:Schools in Kabul]]
[[Category:Private universities in Afghanistan]]
[[Category:Kabul]]

{{-}}
{{Afghanistan-org-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>mplzk0wfehkivnwgf9cf91zyxlk5z37</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bluebird K7</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>17829496</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868810567</id>
      <parentid>856831054</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T15:59:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>John of Reading</username>
        <id>11308236</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Typo/[[WP:AWB/GF|general]] fixes, replaced: an [[land speed record]] → a [[land speed record]], were she → where she</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="22941">{{Redirect|Coniston Bluebird|the racehorse|Coniston Bluebird (horse)}}
{{italic title}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=February 2014}}
{{Use British English|date=February 2014}}

{|{{Infobox aircraft begin
  |name= ''Bluebird K7''

}}{{Infobox aircraft type
  |type= [[Water Speed Record]]|[[Hydroplane]] high-speed [[Turbojet-powered Hydroplane|Turbojet-powered]] [[water speed record]] Hydroplane
  |manufacturer=[[Samlesbury#Samlesbury Engineering|Samlesbury Engineering]] (hull)&lt;br&gt;[[Metropolitan-Vickers]] (engine)
  |designer=Norris Brothers
  |introduction = January 1955
  |first Record =23 July 1955
  |retired = January 1967
  |primary user=[[Donald Campbell]]
  |produced=
  |number built=1
  |unit cost= £25,000 (1955 value)
}}
|}
[[File:Bluebird K7 in 1960 at Goodwood.jpg|thumb|right|''Bluebird K7'', in its most successful guise, on display at the Goodwood Motor Racing circuit in July 1960.]]
'''''Bluebird K7''''' is a jet engined [[Hydroplane (boat)|hydroplane]] with which Britain's [[Donald Campbell]] set seven world [[water speed record]]s during the later half of the 1950s and the 1960s. ''K7'' was the first successful jet-powered hydroplane, and was considered revolutionary when launched in January 1955. Campbell and ''K7'' were responsible for adding almost {{convert|100|mph}} to the [[water speed record]], taking it from existing mark of {{convert|178|mph}} to just over {{convert|276|mph}}. Donald Campbell was killed in an accident with a much modified ''K7'', on 4 January 1967, whilst making a bid for his eighth [[water speed record]], with his aim to raise the record to over {{convert|300|mph}} on [[Coniston Water]].

==Design==
Donald Campbell began his record-breaking career in 1949 following the death of his father, Sir [[Malcolm Campbell]]. Initially, he had been using his father's 1939-built [[Rolls-Royce R|Rolls-Royce 'R']] type powered propeller-driven [[Hydroplane (boat)|hydroplane]] ''[[Blue Bird K4]]'' for his attempts, but he met with little success and suffered a number of frustrating setbacks. In 1951, ''K4'', which had been modified to a prop-rider configuration to increase its performance potential, was destroyed after suffering a structural failure, when its V-drive gearbox sheared its mountings, and punched through the floor of the hull.

Following rival record breaker [[John Cobb (motorist)|John Cobb]]'s death in his jet boat [[Crusader (speedboat)|''Crusader'']], which broke up at over {{convert|200|mph}} during a record attempt in September 1952, Campbell began development of his own advanced all-metal jet-powered ''Bluebird K7'' hydroplane to challenge the record, by then held by the American prop rider hydroplane ''Slo-Mo-Shun IV''.&lt;ref name="Tremayne, Behind The Mask" &gt;{{cite book
  |title=Donald Campbell: The Man Behind the Mask 
  |last=Tremayne  |first=David
  |isbn=0-553-81511-3
  |publisher=Bantam Books
  |year=2005
}}&lt;/ref&gt; Designed by Ken and Lew Norris, the ''K7'' was a steel-framed, aluminium-bodied, three-point hydroplane, built at Samlesbury by Samlesbury Engineering, powered by a [[Metrovick F.2|Metropolitan-Vickers Beryl]] axial-flow [[turbojet]] engine, producing 3500 [[pound-force]] (16&amp;nbsp;kN) of thrust. Like ''Slo-Mo-Shun'', but unlike Cobb's tricycle ''Crusader'', the three planing points were arranged with two forward and one aft, in a "pickle-fork" layout, prompting ''Bluebird'''s early comparison to a blue [[lobster]]. ''K7'' was of very advanced design and construction, and its load-bearing steel space frame ultra rigid. It had a design speed of {{convert|250|mph}} and remained the only successful jet-boat in the world until the late 1960s.

The designation "K7" was derived from its [[Lloyd's unlimited rating#K7|Lloyd's unlimited rating]] registration. It was carried on a prominent white roundel on its [[sponson]]s, underneath an [[infinity]] symbol. ''Bluebird K7'' was the seventh boat registered at Lloyds in the 'Unlimited' series.

[[File:K7 Registration.jpg|thumb|''K7'''s Lloyds Unlimited Hydroplane registration]]

== ''Bluebird K7'' records ==

Campbell set seven world water speed records in ''K7'' between July 1955 and December 1964. The first of these marks was set at [[Ullswater]] on 23 July 1955, where he achieved a speed of 202.15&amp;nbsp;mph (324&amp;nbsp;km/h) but only after many months of trials and a major redesign of ''Bluebird'''s forward sponson attachments points. Campbell achieved a steady series of subsequent speed-record increases with the boat during the rest of the decade, beginning with a mark of {{convert|216|mph|abbr=on}} in 1955 on [[Lake Mead]] in [[Nevada]]. Subsequently, four new marks were registered on [[Coniston Water]], where Campbell and ''Bluebird'' became an annual fixture in the later half of the fifties, enjoying significant sponsorship from the [[Mobil]] oil company and then [[BP]]. Campbell made an unsuccessful attempt in 1957 at [[Canandaigua]] in New York state in the summer of 1957, which failed due to lack of suitable calm water conditions. ''Bluebird K7'' became a well known attraction, and as well as her annual Coniston appearances, ''K7'' was displayed extensively in the UK, USA, Canada and Europe, and then subsequently in Australia during Campbell's prolonged attempt on the [[land speed record]] in 1963–64.

In order to extract more speed, and endow the boat with greater high speed stability, in both [[pitch axis (kinematics)|pitch]] and [[yaw axis|yaw]], ''K7'' was subtly modified in the second half of the 1950s to incorporate more effective streamlining with a blown Perspex cockpit canopy and fluting to the lower part of the main hull. In 1958, a small wedge shaped tail fin, housing an arrester parachute, modified sponson fairings, that gave a significant reduction in forward aerodynamic lift, and a fixed hydrodynamic stabilising fin, attached to the [[transom (nautical)|transom]] to aid directional stability, and exert a marginal down-force on the nose were incorporated into the design to increase the safe operating envelope of the hydroplane. Thus she reached {{convert|225|mph|abbr=on}} in 1956, where an unprecedented peak speed of {{convert|286.78|mph|abbr=on}} was achieved on the first run, {{convert|239|mph|abbr=on}} in 1957, {{convert|248|mph|abbr=on}} in 1958 and {{convert|260|mph|abbr=on}} in 1959.

Campbell then turned his attention to the [[Land Speed Record]], with the aim of establishing a [[land speed record]] of {{convert|450|mph|abbr=on}} plus. He also planned to set a seventh [[water speed record]] in the same year, and so become the first person to establish the [[land speed record]] and [[water speed record]] in the same year.  He set out for the [[Bonneville Salt Flats]] in August 1960 and was lucky to survive a {{convert|360|mph|abbr=on}} crash in his Norris Brothers designed ''[[Bluebird CN7]]'' turbine powered car later that September. ''Bluebird CN7'' was rebuilt in 1961–62 and Campbell subsequently spent a frustrating two years in the Australian desert, battling adverse track conditions. Finally, after Campbell exceeded the [[land speed record]] on [[Lake Eyre]] on 17 July 1964, at {{convert|403.10|mph|abbr=on}} in ''Bluebird CN7'', he snared his seventh water speed record on 31 December 1964 at [[Dumbleyung Lake]], [[Western Australia]], when he reached {{convert|276.33|mph|abbr=on}}, with two runs at {{convert|283.3|mph|abbr=on}} and {{convert|269.3|mph|abbr=on}} completed with only hours to spare on New Year's Eve 1964.

This latest success made Campbell and ''K7'' the world's most prolific holders of the [[water speed record]], and in addition Campbell realised his 'double' when he became the first, and so far only, person to break both the [[land speed record]] and the [[water speed record]] in the same year.  Following on from this success, Campbell stated that ''K7'' would be most likely retired and become a museum exhibit. Her hull was ten years old, her engine fourteen, and her design speed of {{convert|250|mph|abbr=on}}had been exceeded by over {{convert|30|mph|abbr=on}} on a number of occasions.

===Donald Campbell's speed records===
{| class="wikitable"
|-
! Speed !! Craft !! Location !! Date
|-
|| {{convert|202.32|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  [[Ullswater]] || 23 July 1955
|-
|| {{convert|216.20|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  [[Lake Mead]] || 16 November 1955
|-
|| {{convert|225.63|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  [[Coniston Water]] || 19 September 1956
|-
|| {{convert|239.07|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  Coniston Water|| 7 November 1957
|-
|| {{convert|248.62|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  Coniston Water|| 10 November 1958
|-
|| {{convert|260.35|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  Coniston Water|| 14 May 1959
|-
|| {{convert|276.33|mph|kph|abbr=on}} || ''Bluebird K7'' ||  [[Dumbleyung Lake, Western Australia|Lake Dumbleyung]] || 31 December 1964
|}

==Final record attempt and death of Donald Campbell==
In June 1966, Campbell decided to once more try for a water speed record with K7: his target, 300&amp;nbsp;mph (480&amp;nbsp;km/h).

To add more power, Campbell received a 4,500 pound-force (20&amp;nbsp;kN) [[Bristol Siddeley Orpheus]] engine on loan from the [[Ministry of Defence]]. This was both lighter and more powerful than the original engine. Campbell also purchased a crash-damaged [[Folland Gnat]], which used the Orpheus engine, as a source of spare parts. The [[vertical stabiliser]] from the Gnat was also used on the rebuilt K7, and a new hydraulic water brake designed to slow the boat down on the five-mile Coniston course.

The boat returned to Coniston for trials in November 1966. These did not go well; the weather was appalling and K7 destroyed her engine when the air intakes collapsed under the demands of the more powerful engine, and debris was drawn into the compressor blades. The engine was replaced, using the engine from the Gnat aircraft that he had purchased at the project's start.&lt;ref name="Knowles 2001" &gt;{{cite book
  |title=The Bluebird Years
  |last=Knowles |first=Arthur
  |publisher=Sigma Leisure
  |year=2001
  |isbn=978-1-85058-766-8
}}&lt;/ref&gt; The original Orpheus remained outside the team's lakeside workshop for the rest of the project, shrouded in a tarpaulin.

By the end of November, after further modifications to alter K7's weight distribution, some high-speed runs were made, but these were timed at well below the existing record. Problems with the fuel system meant that the engine could not develop maximum power. By the middle of December, Campbell had made a number of timed attempts, but the highest speed achieved was 264&amp;nbsp;mph, and therefore still shy of the existing record. Eventually, further modifications to K7's fuel system (involving the fitting of a booster pump) fixed the fuel-starvation problem. It was now the end of December and Campbell was all set to proceed, pending only the arrival of suitable weather conditions.

===Final runs===

On 4 January 1967, Campbell mounted his record attempt. Bluebird had completed an initial north-south run at an average of {{convert|297.6|mph|abbr=on}}, and Campbell used the new water brake to slow ''K7'' from a peak speed of {{convert|311|mph|abbr=on}} when he left the measured kilometre. Instead of refuelling and waiting for the wash of this run to subside, as had been pre-arranged, he then decided to make the return run immediately.

The second run was even faster; as ''K7'' passed the start of the measured kilometre, she was travelling at over {{convert|320|mph|-1|abbr=on}}. However her stability had begun to break down as she travelled at a speed she had never achieved before, and the front of the boat started to bounce out of the water on the starboard side. 150&amp;nbsp;yards from the end of the measured mile, ''K7'' lifted from the surface and after about 1.5&amp;nbsp;seconds, gradually lifted from the water at an ever-increasing angle, then took off at a 90-degree angle to the water surface. She somersaulted and plunged back into the lake, nose first, then cartwheeled across the water before coming to rest. The impact broke ''K7'' forward of the air intakes (where Campbell was sitting) and the main hull sank shortly afterwards.

Campbell had been killed instantly.&lt;ref&gt;GRO Register of Deaths: MAR 1967 10F 692 ULVERSTON - Donald M. Campbell, aged 45&lt;/ref&gt; [[Mr Whoppit]], his teddy bear mascot, was found among the floating debris and his helmet was recovered. [[Royal Navy]] divers were able to locate the wreck of ''K7'', but called off the search for Campbell's body after two weeks.&lt;ref name=Hopkins&gt;''Across the Lake'', BBC documentary.&lt;/ref&gt;

Campbell's last words, recorded from the radio intercom, were:
{{quote|Pitching a bit down here&amp;nbsp;... Probably from my own wash&amp;nbsp;... Straightening up now on track&amp;nbsp;... Rather closer to [[Peel Island, Cumbria|Peel Island]]&amp;nbsp;... Tramping like mad&amp;nbsp;... and er&amp;nbsp;... Full power&amp;nbsp;... Tramping like hell here&amp;nbsp;... I can't see much&amp;nbsp;... and the water's very bad indeed&amp;nbsp;... I can't get over the top/I'm galloping over the top&lt;ref&gt;BBC: The latter interpretation of the recording better fits the events at the time; the boat was accelerating rapidly on smooth water&lt;/ref&gt;&amp;nbsp;... I'm getting a lot of bloody row in here&amp;nbsp;... I can't see anything&amp;nbsp;... I've got the bows out&amp;nbsp;... I'm going!&amp;nbsp;....ugh"&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web |work=BBC News |title=Last words from Bluebird |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/1/hi/england/2560957.stm |date=10 December 2002 |access-date=31 December 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}

===Accident analysis===

There are varying theories about the cause of the crash. Not waiting to refuel meant the boat was lighter. The wash from the first run would have been made worse by use of the water brake; however, the wash had not had time to reflect back to the centre of the course, and Campbell had used the water brake well to the south. The still photographs taken of the latter part of the final run clearly show that the water brake was not deployed then, and also that when ''K7'' became airborne, the jet engine was no longer functioning; the exhaust would have very noticeably disturbed the water. The engine had therefore flamed out. It is impossible to be certain why; fuel starvation, damage to a structural element during the bouncing, disturbance of the airstream into the intakes during pitching, or a combination of causes are all possible. The most likely ultimate cause is that ''Bluebird'' exceeded its aerodynamic static stability limit, with loss of engine thrust, damage to the port spar fairing, and the then little understood ground-effect lift enhancement&lt;ref&gt;‘Experimental Evaluations of the Aerodynamics of Unlimited Racing Hydroplanes Operating in and out of Ground Effect’, R.J. Englar, D.M. Shuster and D.A. Ford, SAE Technical Paper Series 901869, 1990.&lt;/ref&gt; all adding to the instability.&lt;ref name=Hopkins/&gt;

==Recovery of ''Bluebird K7''==

The wreckage of ''Bluebird'' was discovered on the lake bed on 5 January 1967. A 10-man Royal Navy diving team led by Lt Cmdr John Futcher, had arrived at Coniston late on the day of the accident. They set off for their first attempt to locate Donald Campbell and ''Bluebird'' at 12.30pm the next day. Futcher believed that Campbell's body would be either at the point of impact, in the main wreckage of the boat, or at a point between the two locations. Ken Norris had made some calculations to guide the dive team to the boat's likely resting point.

The first three dives that afternoon found small pieces of wreckage, indicating the dive team were on the correct track. On the fourth dive, the main hull of ''K7'' was found in 142 feet of water, resting in her correct attitude but facing to the south-east. A subsequent and prolonged search located many pieces of wreckage, and various items were brought to the surface including ''Bluebird'''s broken steering wheel and column.

However, the body of Donald Campbell was not located, and the search was called off on 16 January. The Campbell family and team let it be known that they did not wish to have the hull of ''K7'' recovered in the absence of finding Campbell's body. They also felt they would learn nothing from its recovery. The wreck sat on the lake bed for a further 34 years, its location known by a few people but never disclosed.

A diving team led by Bill Smith was responsible for relocating the wreckage and its subsequent recovery was handled by Smith's Bluebird Project team. The wreckage was recovered between October 2000, when the first small sections were raised, and May 2001, when Campbell's body was finally recovered. The largest section, representing approximately two-thirds of the main hull, was salvaged on 8 March 2001.&lt;ref name="BBC8mar2001"&gt;{{cite web |url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/2/hi/uk_news/1208845.stm |title=Divers salvage the Bluebird |date=8 March 2001 |publisher=BBC News |access-date=12 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Controversy over the recovery ===
The exact date of the retrieval of Campbell's body from the lake was 28 May 2001. He was interred in [[Coniston, Cumbria|Coniston]] cemetery on 12 September that year after a funeral service at St Andrews Church in Coniston.

Campbell's sister Jean Wales had been against the recovery of the boat and her brother's body out of respect for his stated wish that, in the event of something going wrong: "Skipper and boat stay together." This quotation is usually said to have been uttered by Campbell when, in the final week of 1964, he was waiting for good weather to attempt a record run, but a bid seemed so unlikely at that point, his colleagues were pressing him to leave. He refused, and broke the record on the last day of 1964. Jean Wales did not attend his burial or visit his grave although she did remain in daily contact with the salvage crew as the boat's wreckage was being brought ashore.

=== Forensic examination and causes of the accident ===
Because the boat's water brake was found to be extended when the wreck was recovered, it was generally assumed that Campbell had activated it to slow down before the boat had left the water on his final run.  On dismantling the boat, however, a [[hydraulic accumulator]] from the donor Gnat aircraft was discovered to be still connected to the system, meaning that stored hydraulic pressure may well have deployed the brake after the accident.

The boat still contained fuel in the engine fuel lines and a quantity was collected and analysed using [[gas chromatography]] as part of the official investigation of the accident commissioned by Barrow Coroner. However, insufficient evidence was present to completely discount the fuel starvation theory. The engine could have cut-out as a result of intermittent fuel starvation caused by the untried fuel system or failure of the electrical supply to the low-pressure fuel-boost pumps. Full details of the boat's strip-down, and the conclusions drawn from it by the investigators, are lodged within the public domain in the diary pages of the Bluebird Project website.

=== Restoration and future running ===
On Thursday 7 December 2006, Gina Campbell, Donald's daughter, formally gifted ''Bluebird K7'' to the [[Ruskin Museum]] in Coniston on behalf of the Campbell Family Heritage Trust. In agreement with the Campbell Family Heritage Trust and the museum, Bill Smith is to organise the restoration of the boat, which is now under way.&lt;ref name="bbc7nov2016"&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-37890287|title=Donald Campbell's Bluebird roars back to life|date=7 November 2016|publisher=BBC News|language=English|accessdate=12 November 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt; Now the property of the Ruskin Museum, the intention is to rebuild ''K7'' back to running order circa 4 January 1967. Bill Smith has said that this will take an undisclosed number of years to accomplish. Gina Campbell commented: "I've decided to secure the future of ''Bluebird'' for the people of Coniston, the Ruskin Museum and the people of the world". Museum Director Vicky Slowe spoke of Gina's generosity and then said: "Bill Smith has assured us he can get ''Bluebird'' fully conserved and reconfigured at no cost to the museum. {{As of|2008}}, ''K7'' is being fully restored by The Bluebird Project, to a very high standard of working condition in North Shields, Tyne and Wear, using a significant proportion of her original fabric, but with a replacement BS Orpheus engine of the same type albeit incorporating many original components."

As of May 2009 permission has been given for a one-off set of proving trials of ''Bluebird'' on Coniston Water, where she will be tested to a safe speed for demonstration purposes only. There is no fixed date for completion of ''Bluebird K7'' or the trials. ''K7'' will be housed in her own purpose built wing at the Ruskin Museum in Coniston, while remaining in the care of The Bluebird Project.

On 20 March 2018 the restoration was featured on the BBC's ''[[The One Show]]'',&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/b09w7mlw|title=The One Show|work=BBC One|accessdate=26 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; where it was announced that Bluebird K7 would return to the water on [[Loch Fad]], on the [[Isle of Bute]] in Scotland, in August 2018 for handling trials.

==Refloating and initial trials==
In August 2018, initial restoration work on Bluebird was completed. She was transported to Loch Fad where she was refloated on 4 August 2018.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-scotland-glasgow-west-45068703|title=Donald Campbell's Bluebird hydroplane returns to water|work=BBC News|date=4 August 2018|accessdate=26 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; Following initial engine trials on 5 August, Bluebird completed a series of test runs on the loch, reaching speeds of about {{convert|150|mph|km/h|abbr=on}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|url=https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-cumbria-45132210|title=Restored Donald Campbell's Bluebird has 'nothing to prove'|work=BBC News|date=9 August 2018|accessdate=26 August 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; For safety reasons, there are no plans to attempt to reach any higher speeds.

==See also==
* ''[[Across the Lake]]'' a 1988 BBC TV drama about Campbell starring [[Anthony Hopkins]].

==References==
{{reflist|30em}}

==External links==
{{externalimage
|align = right
|width = 300
|image1 = [http://farm1.static.flickr.com/64/214197963_c965b9494e_o_d.jpg The wreckage of the tailfin of ''K7''] &lt;!-- &lt;ref&gt; https://www.flickr.com/photos/kaptainkobold/214197963/in/pool-79693942@N00/ 06-10-2008 &lt;/ref&gt; --&gt;
}}
* [http://www.bluebirdproject.com Bluebirdproject.com - the restoration project for ''K7'']
* [https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=4xemKc2In5Y 1967 Pathe News item about the crash]
{{1955 shipwrecks}}
{{1967 shipwrecks}}

[[Category:Bluebird record-breaking vehicles]]
[[Category:Water speed records]]
[[Category:Jet-powered hydroplanes]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1955]]
[[Category:Maritime incidents in 1967]]</text>
      <sha1>ltfn82pv2b6pgdz5zdq5zxnubfbuovz</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Bondost</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4527907</id>
    <revision>
      <id>857051488</id>
      <parentid>743545615</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-29T07:15:24Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Beland</username>
        <id>57939</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>fix broken HTML entity</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1913">{{no footnotes|date=February 2013}}
{{Infobox cheese
| name          = Bondost
| image         = 
| othernames    = 
| country       = [[Sweden]]
| region        = 
| town          = 
| source        = Cows
| pasteurised   = 
| texture       = Firm
| fat           = 
| protein       = 
| dimensions    = 
| weight        = 
| aging         = 6–8 weeks
| certification = 
}}

'''Bondost''' (sometimes spelled '''bond-ost''', Swedish for "farmer cheese") is a [[Sweden|Swedish]] cheese, also made in the [[United States]], chiefly in [[New York (state)|New York]].

This [[cattle|cow]]'s-milk cheese is cylindrical in shape, about {{convert|13|cm|abbr=on}} across and {{convert|9|cm|abbr=on}} high. After the milk (either raw or [[pasteurization|pasteurized]]) is curdled, heated, cut, salted, stirred, pressed into forms, and immersed into brine for a day or two, the new cheese is ripened for six to eight weeks. Sometimes bondost is spiced with [[cumin]] or [[caraway seed]]s, which are incorporated into the curd just before it is molded.

It has a firm texture providing a mild tasting cheese that can be served as an appetizer or for snacking. When produced, it is brine cured, allowed to dry, and ready to serve in approximately 2 months. Several varieties are cured for 1 to 2 days, while the most flavorful varieties are cured for several weeks.

==See also==
{{portal|Food}}
* [[Brined cheese]]
* [[List of cheeses]]

== References ==
{{cite book|author1=Doane, C.F. |author2=Hargrove, Robert C. |author3=Lawson, H.W. |author4=Matheson, K.J. |author5=Sanders, G.P |author6=Walter, Homer E. |title=Cheese Varieties and Descriptions|year=1969|publisher=U.S. Department of Agriculture}} pp.&amp;nbsp;13&amp;ndash;14

{{Swedish cheeses}}

[[Category:Swedish cheeses]]
[[Category:Cuisine of Wisconsin]]
[[Category:Cow's-milk cheeses]]
[[Category:Brined cheeses]]


{{Sweden-stub}}
{{Wisconsin-stub}}
{{cheese-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>gv9k6svbabyryw76r53jjymexi3h6z1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Carlos Dívar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>55770006</id>
    <revision>
      <id>858740033</id>
      <parentid>858629942</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-09T08:14:28Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Pacostein</username>
        <id>4064630</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 858629942 by [[Special:Contributions/62.57.85.143|62.57.85.143]] ([[User talk:62.57.85.143|talk]]) there were rumors but nothing confirmed</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1497">{{Expand Spanish|Carlos Dívar|date=November 2017}}
[[File:Divarcarlos.jpg|thumb|Carlos Dívar]]
'''José Carlos Dívar Blanco''' ([[Málaga]], December 31, 1941 – [[Madrid]], November 11, 2017) was a [[Spain|Spanish]] [[magistrate]]. He was president of the [[General Council of the Judiciary]] and the [[Supreme Court of Spain|Supreme Court]] from September 2008 to June 2012. Previously, he had been President of the National Court (2001-2008), he being the only judge in Spain to have been President of the [[Audiencia Nacional (Spain)|''Audiencia Nacional'']] and the Supreme Court. He resigned in June 2012 when it was uncovered a scandal of alleged misappropriation of public funds as a result of a series of trips he made to [[Marbella]] for several weekends that were not justified and paid with public money. The Prosecutor's Office of the Supreme Court did not consider his actions criminal, but his reputation was very affected and public opinion forced him to resign.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.rtve.es/noticias/20120613/supremo-rechaza-querella-divar-viajes-marbella-pleno-cgpj/535122.shtml El Supremo rechaza la querella por los viajes de Dívar y cinco vocales piden su dimisión] {{es icon}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.aragon2.com/n-19556-502-fiscalia_indicios_delito_viajes_Divar]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{Reflist}}


{{authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Divar, Carlos}}
[[Category:1941 births]]
[[Category:2017 deaths]]
[[Category:Spanish jurists]]
[[Category:Spanish judges]]


{{Spain-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>07nbmvfjgku6q9hs6cgc1hvo8t49q7u</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Central Irian Jaya</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9858053</id>
    <redirect title="Papua (province)" />
    <revision>
      <id>740088858</id>
      <parentid>740088825</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-19T00:41:45Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Look2See1</username>
        <id>11406674</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="128">#REDIRECT [[Papua (province)]]

[[Category:Papua (province)]]
[[Category:New Guinea]]
[[Category:History of Western New Guinea]]</text>
      <sha1>m4u5o8u4hvze9yv8j1l8t5wrx4blgst</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Cghene</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>224845</id>
    <revision>
      <id>761856279</id>
      <parentid>496500744</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-01-25T05:36:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Premeditated Chaos</username>
        <id>31530</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>no longer an orphan</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="738">'''Cghene''', or '''Oghene''', is the supreme [[God]] of the [[Isoko people]] in southern [[Nigeria]]. He is believed to have created the world and all peoples, including the Isoko. Oghene is beyond human comprehension and is only known by his actions. Because the God is so distant and unknown he has no temples or priests, and no prayers or sacrifices are offered directly to him.

Oghene has a courier named [[Oyise]], which is referred to as uko Oghene or "messenger of Oghene". Through oyise, Oghene can be invoked in case of calamity or need.

== External links ==
*http://www.mircea-eliade.com/from-primitives-to-zen/003.html

[[Category:Creator gods]]
[[Category:African gods]]
[[Category:African mythology]]

{{Africa-myth-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>kc2v2rj7wvrof66m3vz489t8a6glbgu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Civil Service of the Russian Federation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>44039017</id>
    <revision>
      <id>792541458</id>
      <parentid>792539348</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-07-27T04:00:23Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>AnomieBOT</username>
        <id>7611264</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Dating maintenance tags: {{Huh?}} {{Sectstub}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3192">The '''Civil Service of the Russian Federation''' ({{lang-ru | Государственная гражданская служба Российской Федерации}}) involves professional service activities of citizens of the [[Russian Federation]] for the enforcement power of the State. Alongside the [[Russian Armed Forces | military services]], it forms part of the {{ill|State Service of the Russian Federation|ru|Государственная служба Российской Федерации}}.

==Federal Law "On the State Civil Service of the Russian Federation"==
Signed by the President of Russia in 2004.

=== Chapter 1. General Provisions===
=== Chapter 2. Civil Service Positions===
===Chapter 3. Legal Status civil servants===
In connection with the passage of the civil service civil servant shall not allow public statements, judgments and estimates, including in the media, in relation to the activities of government agencies and their leaders, including the decisions of higher state body or public authority, which replaces the position of a civil servant civil service if it is not part of his official duties.{{huh?|date=July 2017}}
=== Chapter 4. Joining the civil service===
Receipt of a citizen in the civil service for a post-civil service or replacement of other civil servants civil service positions is carried out on the results of the competition unless otherwise stipulated by this article. The contest is to assess the professional level candidates for the position of the civil service, their compliance with the qualification requirements for civil service positions.

The competition jury consists of representatives of the employer, the representative of the management body of public service, as well as representatives of the scientific and educational institutions, and other organizations invited by the management body of public service at the request of the employer representative as independent experts - experts on issues related to civil service without specifying personal data experts. The number of independent experts should be not less than one-quarter of the total number of members of the competition committee.

=== Chapter 5. Official contract===
=== Chapter 6. Bases and consequences of termination of the contract of service===

=== Chapter 7 Personal data of a civil servant. Personnel office of the state body ===

===Chapter 8 Working hours and rest periods ===

===Chapter 9 Passing the civil service ===

===Chapter 10 Pay civil servants ===

===Chapter 11 State guarantees in the civil service ===

===Chapter 12 Promotion and rewarding. Service discipline in the civil service ===

===Chapter 13, The formation of civil service cadre ===

===Chapter 14 Funding for the civil service. Development program of civil service ===

===Chapter 15: State supervision and monitoring of compliance with legislation of the Russian Federation on the State Civil Service of the Russian Federation ===
===Chapter 16 Review of individual service dispute ===

===Chapter 17. The entry into force of this Federal Law===

== History ==
{{sectstub|date=July 2017}}

[[Category:Russian law]]
[[Category:Russia stubs]]
{{Russia topics}}</text>
      <sha1>nviqcg293ff7lsqab5v02gugrhmpmfb</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Clermeil</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>90643</id>
    <revision>
      <id>821540224</id>
      <parentid>821540151</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-01-21T03:19:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>2600:1002:B10C:1C54:7514:B7A:6280:EC2E</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Undid revision 821540151 by [[Special:Contributions/2600:1002:B10C:1C54:7514:B7A:6280:EC2E]] oops</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="310">{{Unreferenced|date=December 2009}}

'''Clermeil''' is a [[loa]] who makes [[river]]s flood their banks in [[Haiti]]an [[Haitian Vodou|Vodou]]. He is usually depicted as a white male.

[[Category:Voodoo gods]]
[[Category:Sea and river gods]]
[[Category:African mythology]]


{{Haiti-stub}}
{{Africa-myth-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>mguyay805hk3o6c5wol77dbdxchelse</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Coat of arms of Eswatini</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>10146077</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868866587</id>
      <parentid>868690165</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T23:19:22Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>IamNotU</username>
        <id>5841175</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Reverted 1 edit by [[Special:Contributions/159.8.170.10|159.8.170.10]] ([[User talk:159.8.170.10|talk]]): Reverted block evasion by sock of [[Wikipedia:Sockpuppet investigations/Shingling334/Archive|Shingling334]]. ([[WP:TW|TW]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2169">{{Infobox coat of arms
|name             = Coat of arms of Eswatini
|image            = Coat_of_arms_of_Swaziland.svg
|image_width      = 250
|middle           = 
|middle_width     = 
|middle_caption   = 
|lesser           = 
|lesser_width     = 
|lesser_caption   = 
|armiger          = [[King Mswati III]]
|year_adopted     = 1968
|crest            = A Crown of feathers proper
|torse            = Azure and Or
|shield           = Azure, a Swazi battle shield with decorations, all proper
|supporters       = To the dexter, a Lion and to the sinister an Elephant, both proper
|compartment      = 
|motto            = '''Siyinqaba''' &lt;br&gt; "We Are The Fortress"
|orders           = 
|other_elements   = 
|earlier_versions = 
|use              = 
}}

The '''coat of arms of Swaziland''' is a [[coat of arms]] depicting various symbols for traditional [[Eswatini]] culture. The [[lion]] represents the [[King of Swaziland|King]] and the [[elephant]] represents the Queen-mother. They support a traditional [[Nguni shield]] which represents "protection". Above the shield is the king's ''[[lidlabe]]'', or crown of feathers, normally worn during [[Incwala]] (the festival of the harvest). On a banner below the shield is the Swaziland national motto, ''Siyinqaba'', meaning, "We are the fortress".

== References ==
{{refbegin}}
* {{Cite web
| title = Swaziland - ''Umbuso weSwatini''
| author =
| work = Heraldry of the World
| date =
| accessdate = 2015-08-18
| url = http://www.ngw.nl/heraldrywiki/index.php?title=Swaziland
| quote =
}}
* {{Cite web
| title =  General Swaziland Information: Social
| last = Patricks | first = Richard M.
| work = Swaziland National Trust Commission
| date = 1 July 2000
| accessdate = 2015-08-18
| url = http://www.sntc.org.sz/tourism/social.asp
| language = 
| quote =
}}
{{refend}}
{{Coat of arms of Africa}}

[[Category:National coats of arms|Swaziland]]
[[Category:National symbols of Eswatini]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with crowns|Swaziland]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with lions|Swaziland]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with elephants|Swaziland]]
[[Category:Coats of arms with spears|Swaziland]]

{{Swaziland-stub}}
{{Heraldry-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>qymn7gf73w50ndvxf3m8twia5bl27a3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Confidence-building measures in South America</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>8666291</id>
    <revision>
      <id>508065458</id>
      <parentid>484903886</parentid>
      <timestamp>2012-08-19T01:50:07Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Chris the speller</username>
        <id>525927</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>hyphenation, replaced: over-arching → overarching using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (8267)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="9065">{{nofootnotes|date=December 2009}}
{{Essay-like|date=November 2008}}

The [[South American]] experience with [[confidence-building measures]] has been markedly different from the [[Central American]] one for the obvious reason that South America did not live through the protracted conflict and peacemaking process which dominated Central America in the 1980s and early 1990s. Thus, there was no UN peace-keeping presence in South America, and there was no overarching treaty or [[Contadora]]/ [[Esquipulas]] Treaty framework in which to ground specific CBMs.

Nevertheless, CBMs have been of considerable significance in South America in this period, especially when linked to schemes for economic and political integration. The explicit use of CBMs in this connection may well turn out to have as significant long-term effects as in Central America. Of particular interest is the notion that CBMs and shifts in strategic geopolitical thinking can change the role of the military and assist in strengthening the democratic process. 

The most dramatic shifts have occurred in the Argentine-Brazilian relationship, which has the potential of driving most of the other political, strategic and economic arrangements in southern South America. However, there are other equally significant changes, such as in the Argentine-Chilean and even the Argentine-British relationship which have been positively affected by CBMs in the past decade.

Put in other words, CBMs can assist in shifting the strategic paradigm from one based on hostility and conflict-laden geopolitics to one which stresses "geo-economics" and the geopolitics of cooperation and integration with neighbors. 

==The conflict possibilities==
 
Although often ignored outside of the region, South America has a series of historic strains between pairs of bordering states which have always had the potential of flaring up and reaching the conflict stage. Because the military establishments of many of the South American nations have considerably greater potential than the Central American ones, any inter-state armed conflict would be far more damaging than in Central America (the example of the 1982 Anglo-Argentina war over the [[Falklands/Malvinas]] is illustrative). 

Furthermore, the military establishments of the nations involved have a vested interest in using these possible conflicts as justifications for their budgets, troop levels, and influence. Their use of classical "war hypotheses" based on geopolitical thinking and historic animosities with neighbors is an enduring feature which has shaped military roles and missions. Thus, CBMs can have considerable potential if they serve to reduce these animosities, diminish the credibility of the "war hypotheses", and make the possibilities of conflict less likely.

A short list of potential bilateral conflict situations would include: Guyana-Venezuela; Venezuela-Colombia; Ecuador-Peru; Peru-Chile; Bolivia-Chile; Chile-Argentina; Argentina-Brazil; Argentina-United Kingdom. Conflicts which are multilateral would include Argentine-Brazilian competition for influence in the South American "[[buffer state]]s" (Uruguay, Paraguay, Bolivia); attempts to exercise control over extensive economic or patrimonial maritime zones (such as the Chilean effort to claim a "Mar Presencial"); and issues of sovereignty and resources in the quadrant of Antarctica which is associated with South America, and which is claimed by Argentina, Chile and Great Britain, despite the presence of scientific bases of some 18 nations, including the U. S.

==Impact of CBMs==

It is against this backdrop of potential conflict situations that the significance of CBMs in South America must be examined. Although some of these CBMs have been in place for many years, there was a dramatic increase in their number in the last twenty years, and for the first time the language of CBMs was specifically used in connection with international strains in South America. 

Although it is difficult to document linkages and causality, it appears that the increased use of CBMs in the Central American conflict scenario, and the involvement of several South American nations in the Contadora and Esquipulas effort, produced a "contagion effect" under which CBMs concepts and techniques were transferred from the Central to the South American conflict scenarios. 

CBMs have had the greatest impact on the so-called [[ABC nations|"ABC" countries]] of the [[Southern Cone]] ([[Argentina]], [[Brazil]] and [[Chile]]), and have been linked to attempts at economic integration in the same area (Mercosur); there have also been proposals for a collective security agreement which would unify the [[Mercosur]] countries.

=== Argentina-Brazil===
Within the over-all shift from competition to cooperation between these two major forces in South America, there is a strategic component that is remarkable in light of the fact that the contingency planning of these two nations always included the "war hypothesis" of armed conflict between them. 

One basic CBM has been the periodic meetings of senior representatives of their General Staffs to discuss matters of common interest and plan for specific measures of military-to-military cooperation such as exchanges of information and joint arms manufacturing. These meetings stemmed from the 1985 Iguazú Declaration, and began as bilateral meetings. 

Since then they have included Paraguay, Uruguay and Chile as observers, with plans for including these countries as full members. The meetings are now being called a "strategic Mercosur" to parallel the economic Mercosur. Two of the old areas of dangerous competition, nuclear projects and strains over dams along their riverine borders (sometimes called the "A-Bomb" of atomic rivalry and the "H-Bomb" of incompatible hydroelectric projects) have been basically resolved by means of cooperative approaches in these two potentially conflictive issue-areas between Argentina and Brazil. 

The degree to which CBM terminology has crept into the resolution of these old problems can be seen in the words of Argentine President [[Carlos Menem]] when he signed a decree prohibiting the export of Argentine nuclear and ballistic missile technology to nations which refuse to accept international safeguards: "A lack of transparency (in the past) made us dangerous and untrustworthy". Followers of CBM trends would immediately recognize the significance and origin of the term "transparency" in Menem's words.

=== Argentina-Chile===
The improvement in relations between these two countries is equally remarkable, given their historic rivalry and the fact that they almost went to war in 1978 over the issue of the [[Beagle Channel]] Islands in their far southern frontier. Resolution of that issue by means of Papal mediation paved the way for a series of other measures, many of them clearly CBMs between their military establishments. 

As examples we can cite periodic meetings of the senior naval regional commanders in Puerto Williams, Chile and Ushuaia, Argentina (both sites are on the Beagle Channel). Likewise, southern air force commanders of Chile and Argentine have "hot lines", and meet periodically to minimize the danger that border incidents might lead to something more serious. High-level discussions between Presidents Menem and Aylwin over remaining border issues were accompanied by lower-level military contacts and exchange of visits aimed at enhancing CBMs.

=== Argentina-United Kingdom===
CBMs in this area are of special interest because of the legacy of [[Falklands War|the 1982 war]], which might have been averted had confidence-building measures existed then. Some of the CBMs established by the two countries are clearly inspired by CBMs which had been set up between [[NATO]] and the [[Warsaw Pact]]. 

Other CBMs may have stemmed from the Central American peace process, in which Argentina played a significant role as part of the Contadora Support Group as well as participation in the United Nations Observer Group [[ONUCA]] (with both observers and a group of naval patrol vessels in the [[Gulf of Fonseca]]). The Anglo-Argentine CBMs are contained in a series of joint declarations signed in 1989, 1990 and 1991, and include classic CBMs such as the establishment of direct communication links, exchanges of information, search and rescue procedures, notification of military movements and maneuvers above certain specified levels, and the establishment of certain "rules of behavior".

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==Further reading==
*Beltrán, Virgilio. "Buscando Nuevos Roles para los Ejércitos de América Latina", ''International Congress of Military Sociology'', Valparaiso, Chile, 29-31 August 1992, pp. 37-38.
*Goodman, Louis. ''The Military and Democracy''. Lexington: Lexington Books, 1990.
*OAS, Permanent Council, Grupo de Trabajo sobre Cooperación para la Seguridad Hemisférica. ''Nuevo Concepto de Seguridad'', OAS Document CP/GT/CSH-13/92, 12 February 1992.

[[Category:South America]]
[[Category:International relations]]</text>
      <sha1>tq6ru13wb6havr1a13ay5dsqy7tu3d2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Dan najlepših sanj</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>18586395</id>
    <revision>
      <id>830983703</id>
      <parentid>699187121</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-03-18T02:00:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Entranced98</username>
        <id>27199084</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>+navbox</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2330">{{Infobox song contest entry
| song         = {{flagicon|Slovenia}} "Dan najlepših sanj"
| image        = 
| caption      = 
| year         = 1996
| country      = Slovenia
| artist       = Regina
| as           = 
| with         = 
| language     = Slovene
| languages    =
| composer     = [[Aleksander Kogoj]]
| lyricist     = [[Aleksander Kogoj]]
| conductor    = [[Jože Privšek]]
| place        = 21st
| points       = 19
| lyrics       = [http://www.diggiloo.net/?1996si from Diggiloo Thrush]
| prev         = Prisluhni mi
| prev_link    = Prisluhni mi
| next         = Zbudi se
| next_link    = Zbudi se
}}
'''"Dan najlepših sanj"''' ("The day of the most beautiful dream") was the [[Slovenia in the Eurovision Song Contest 1996|Slovene]] entry in the [[Eurovision Song Contest 1996]], sung by [[Regina (singer)|Regina]] in [[Slovene language|Slovenian]].

The song was performed fourteenth on the night, following [[France]]'s [[Dan Ar Braz|Dan Ar Braz &amp; L'Héritage des Celtes]] with "[[Diwanit Bugale]]" and preceding [[Netherlands]]'s [[Maxine (singer)|Maxine]] &amp; [[Franklin Brown]] with "[[De eerste keer]]". At the close of voting, it had received 19 points, placing twenty-first in a field of twenty three.

It was succeeded as Slovene representative at the [[Eurovision Song Contest 1997|1997 contest]] by [[Tanja Ribič]] with "[[Zbudi se]]".

{| class="wikitable sortable" style="font-size: 95%"
|-
! Points !! Country
|-
| style="text-align:center"|12 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|10 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|8 || {{Esc|Bosnia and Herzegovina}}
|-
| style="text-align:center"|7 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|6 || {{Esc|Croatia}}
|-
| style="text-align:center"|5 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|4 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|3 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|2 || style="text-align:center"|—
|-
| style="text-align:center"|1 || {{Esc|Spain}}, {{Esc|Iceland}}
|}

{{Slovenia in the Eurovision Song Contest}}
{{Eurovision Song Contest 1996}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Dan najlepsih sanj}}
[[Category:Eurovision songs of 1996]]
[[Category:Eurovision songs of Slovenia]]
[[Category:1996 songs]]


{{Slovenia-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>bxnzauv9ekndlod1pqc8yx3fvpgoh37</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Davtashen Bridge</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39206500</id>
    <revision>
      <id>783300212</id>
      <parentid>783300036</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-06-01T11:32:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Preacher lad</username>
        <id>13992507</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1915">{{Infobox bridge
|bridge_name= Davtashen Bridge
|image=Դավթաշենի կամուրջը.JPG
|caption=Davtashen Bridge
|official_name=
|carries=
|crosses=[[Hrazdan River]]
|locale=[[Yerevan]]
|maint= 
|id=
|design= 
|mainspan=
|length= {{convert|496|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
|width= {{convert|32|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
|height= {{convert|92|m|ft|1|abbr=on}}
|clearance=
|below=
|traffic= Dual carriageway
|open= 2000
|life=
|closed=
|map_cue=
|map_image=
|map_text=
|map_width=
|coordinates= {{Coord|40|12|36|N|44|29|34|E|}}
|lat=
|long=
}}

'''Davtashen Bridge''' or '''Davitashen Bridge''' ({{lang-hy|Դավթաշենի կամուրջ}}) is a bridge for traffic linking across the [[Hrazdan River]] in [[Yerevan]], [[Armenia]]. It connects the Vaghrshyan street of [[Arabkir district]] with the Sasna Tzrer street of [[Davtashen district]] within the capital city. The construction process was launched during the 1970s by the Soviet government but abandoned shortly after. Only in 2000, the construction of the bridge was completed.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.encyclopedia.am/pages.php?bId=1&amp;hId=333 Bridges in Armenia]&lt;/ref&gt; Height above the water level of the river Hrazdan -92m.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.kamurjshin.am/en/showprogram/10/|title=KamurjShin.am|website=www.kamurjshin.am|language=en|access-date=2017-01-26}}&lt;/ref&gt; The bridge was constructed by [[Kamurjshin]] company.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=http://www.hhpress.am/index.php?sub=hodv&amp;hodv=20110618_18&amp;flag=am|title=HHpress.am|website=www.hhpress.am|access-date=2016-11-11}}&lt;/ref&gt;

The bridge was designed by architect [[Rafael Israelyan]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.yerevan.am/edfiles/files/ANDZNAGIR/kamurjner+.pdf Bridges in Yerevan]&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Yerevan landmarks}}

[[Category:Bridges in Yerevan]]
[[Category:Bridges completed in 1996]]
[[Category:Road bridges in Armenia]]

{{asia-bridge-struct-stub}}
{{Armenia-struct-stub}}
{{Armenia-transport-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>d87qwbtf52swbc5o6kqysczuac678mg</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Der Kampf</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>27847329</id>
    <revision>
      <id>827799935</id>
      <parentid>780059723</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-26T20:22:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Bearcat</username>
        <id>24902</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added [[Category:Weekly newspapers published in Luxembourg]] using [[WP:HC|HotCat]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2391">{{notability|date=February 2017}}
{{unreferenced|date=February 2017}}
{{Infobox newspaper
| name                 =Der Kampf
| logo                 = 
| image                = 
| caption              = 
| type                 = 
| format               = 
| owners               = 
| founder              = 
| publisher            = 
| editor               = 
| chiefeditor          = 
| assoceditor          = 
| maneditor            = 
| newseditor           = 
| managingeditordesign = 
| campuseditor         = 
| campuschief          = 
| opeditor             = 
| sportseditor         = 
| photoeditor          = 
| staff                = 
| foundation           = 1920
| political            = [[Communist Party of Luxembourg]]
| language             = [[German language|German]]
| ceased publication   = 1922
| headquarters         = 
| circulation          = 
| sister newspapers    = 
| ISSN                 = 
| oclc                 = 
| website              = 
}}
'''''Der Kampf''''' (English: ''The Struggle'') was a weekly newspaper published in [[Luxembourg]] by the [[Communist Party of Luxembourg]] between 1920 and 1922.

The newspapers had various subheadings over time, from ''Wochenschrift der Kommunisten Luxemburgs'' ("Weekly journal of the Communists of Luxembourg") in the first edition, to later ''Organ der Kommunistischen Partei Luxemburgs (Sektion der 3. Internationale) ''("Organ of the Communist Party of Luxembourg [Part of the 3rd International]") in the 8th edition.

The first edition appeared on 18 November 1920. From 3 April 1921, the paper had a supplement, ''Der kommunistische Gewerkschaftler'' ("The communist trade unionist").

Due to the Communist Party's poor finances, the newspaper was shut down in 1922.

== See also ==
* [[List of newspapers in Luxembourg]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Kampf}}
[[Category:1920 establishments in Luxembourg]]
[[Category:1922 disestablishments in Luxembourg]]
[[Category:Communist newspapers published in Luxembourg]]
[[Category:Defunct newspapers of Luxembourg]]
[[Category:Defunct weekly newspapers]]
[[Category:German-language communist newspapers]]
[[Category:German-language newspapers published in Luxembourg]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1920]]
[[Category:Publications disestablished in 1922]]
[[Category:Weekly newspapers published in Luxembourg]]


{{Luxembourg-newspaper-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>hevalz9zyph7s6bjdbiplaiwm3we2a3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>EL &amp; IT Forbundet</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5277641</id>
    <revision>
      <id>821494294</id>
      <parentid>651024705</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-01-20T20:56:02Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Helper201</username>
        <id>24323093</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1768">{{Infobox Union
|name= EL &amp; IT
|country= [[Norway]]
|affiliation= [[Norwegian Confederation of Trade Unions|LO]]
|members= 37,000
|full_name= EL &amp; IT Forbundet
|native_name=
|image= [[Image:EL&amp;IT logo.png|200px]]
|founded= 1999
|current=
|head=
|dissolved_date=
|dissolved_state=
|merged_into=
|office= [[Oslo]], Norway
|people= [[Jan Olav Andersen]], president
|website= [http://www.elogit.no www.elogit.no]
|footnotes=
}}
&lt;!-- Include all unused fields for future use. See [[template talk:Infobox Union]] for usage. --&gt;

'''EL &amp; IT Forbundet''' is a [[trade union]] in [[Norway]]. It was formed by the 1999 merger of the [[Electricians and Power Station Workers]], and the [[Data and Telecommunications Workers]].

EL &amp; IT Forbundet has a membership of over 37,000 and is affiliated with the [[Norwegian Confederation of Trade Unions]] (LO).

[[Hans O. Felix]] was president of the union from 2001 to 2015. [[Jan Olav Andersen]] was elected in March 2015.&lt;!-- Norwegian language source: http://frifagbevegelse.no/nettverk/felix_tar_ikke_gjenvalg_305686.html 
http://frifagbevegelse.no/arbeidsliv/el__it_forbundet_valgte_jan_olav_andersen_som_ny_forbundsleder_328262.html --&gt; 

==References==
*{{cite book
 | year = 2005
 | title = Trade Unions of the World
 | editor = [[International Centre for Trade Union Rights|ICTUR]] et al.,
 | edition = 6th
 | publisher = John Harper Publishing
 | location = London, UK
 | isbn = 0-9543811-5-7
}}

==External links==
* [http://www.elogit.no EL &amp; IT Forbundet] official site.

{{Portal|Organised labour}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:EL and IT Forbundet}}
[[Category:Norwegian Confederation of Trade Unions]]
[[Category:Trade unions established in 1999]]
[[Category:Trade unions in Norway]]


{{Norway-org-stub}}
{{Europe-trade-union-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>j1mddr8qqy6qg8cykq5p82ywlbog2f1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Estonian Rescue Board</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15708858</id>
    <revision>
      <id>843908942</id>
      <parentid>839476629</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-06-01T09:04:46Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Estonian1885</username>
        <id>32360614</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>New Director General.</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2465">{{Infobox government agency
|agency_name     = Estonian Rescue Board
|type            = 
|native_name      = Päästeamet
|logo            = 
|logo_width      = 
|logo_caption    = 
|seal            = Paasteameti vapp.jpeg
|seal_width      = 
|seal_caption    = 
|picture         = 
|picture_width   = 
|picture_caption = 
|formed          = 
|preceding1      = 
|dissolved       = 
|superseding     = 
|jurisdiction    = [[Government of Estonia]]
|headquarters    = Raua 2, [[Tallinn]]
|coordinates     = {{coord|59|26|6.82|N|24|45|50.15|E|region:EE|display=inline,title}}
|motto           = 
|employees       = 
|budget          = 
|chief1_name     = Kuno Tammearu
|chief1_position = Director General
|agency_type     = 
|parent_agency   = [[Ministry of the Interior (Estonia)|Ministry of the Interior]]
|child1_agency   = 
|child2_agency   = 
|keydocument1    = 
|website         = {{URL|http://www.rescue.ee}}
|footnotes       = 
}}

[[File:2009 04 24 Nublu Vabaõhumuuseumi Pritsukuuris.jpg|right|thumb|'''Nublu''', the [[mascot]] of the Estonian Rescue Board, at the [[Estonian Open Air Museum]]]]
[[File:Lõuna-Eesti Päästekeskuse auto.jpg|thumb|Car from South-Estonian division of Estonian Rescue Board in [[Tartu]].]]
The '''Estonian Rescue Board''' ({{lang-et|Päästeamet}}) is an autonomous governmental institution within the Ministry of Internal Affairs. The Rescue Board is responsible for inland fire and rescue services in Estonia. In general, operational services are organized at county level and the Rescue Board has administrative duties, but there are also some operational units directly under The Rescue Board's control.

Among other duties, the Board carries out [[explosive ordnance disposal]] in Estonia through the Estonian EOD Center, which has received [[U.S. State Department]] funding. Estonian de-mining personnel have deployed to Afghanistan, and to [[Georgia (country)|Georgia]], after the [[2008 South Ossetia war|South Ossetia War]] of 2008.

==See also==
* [[IT and Development Centre. Ministry of the Interior, Estonia|SMIT]] - [[IT and Development Centre. Ministry of the Interior, Estonia]]

==References==
{{reflist}}
*{{official website|http://www.rescue.ee}}
*[http://www.environmental-expert.com/resultEachPressRelease.aspx?cid=819&amp;codi=8733&amp;idproducttype=6&amp;level=0 Estonia is getting prepared; Source: Lamor Corporation AB; Published Dec. 4, 2006 ]

[[Category:Law enforcement agencies of Estonia]]


{{Estonia-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>ttjm352frj7wagr24ryl45p2dej5dag</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Flynderupgård</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>51702739</id>
    <revision>
      <id>744843970</id>
      <parentid>740668588</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-10-17T19:45:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>The Anomebot2</username>
        <id>1979668</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Adding geodata: {{coord|56.0045|N|12.5551|E|source:wikidata|display=title}}</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2411">[[File:Flynderupgaardmuseet 1.jpg|thumb|300px|Flynderupgård in winter]] 
'''Flynderupgård''' is a former country house in the [[Espergærde]] district of [[Helsingør]], [[Denmark]]. It is now part of [[Helsingør City Museum|Helsingør Museums]] dedicated to the non-urban parts of the municipality with its farming communities, farmland, forestry and fishing villages. The outdoor premises comprises traditional breeds of farm animals, cultivation of a five hectares piece of land and a garden, all as it would appear in the 1920s.

==History==
Flynderupgård was originally a farm but converted into a country house in the beginning of the 19th century. The main building was adapted in its current style in 1915&amp;ndash;20.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.helsingorleksikon.dk/index.php/Flynderupg%C3%A5rd_Museet|title=Flynderup¨ård|language=Danish|publisher=Helsingør Museum|accessdate=18 September 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exhibition==
The museum comprises two large local collections. One of them is a collections of artifacts compiled by teacher at Rspergærde School Arne Meyling in the period between 1954 and the 1970s. The other is a collection of artefacts aelated to fishing which was donated to the museum by architect Per Christiansen.

The main building contains a recreation of a historic grocery store as well as a living room. The museum also arranges special exhibitions several times a year.

==Garden==
The garden is a recreation of the garden as it would appear in the 1920s. In association with the garden is a sculpture walk as well as several -free-standing sculptures by the sculptor Karl Otto Johansen.

==Frilandskulturcentret Flynderupgård==
Om association to the museum is Frilandskulturcentret Flynderupgård which keeps of farm animals cultivate a five hectares piece of land in the same way as it was done in the 120s. The farm animals are all traditional Danish breeds such as such as Rød Dansk Malkerace cattle Dansk Landrace pigeand .

==Restaurant==
Folkestuen serves traditional Danish as it would be prefared in the 1920s.

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
{{Commons}}
* [http://www.helsingormuseer.dk/index.php?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=25&amp;Itemid=116 Official website]

{{Copenhagen museums}}
{{Helsingør}}

{{coord|56.0045|N|12.5551|E|source:wikidata|display=title}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Helsingør Municipality]]

{{Denmark-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>m27mawnhfzzd3gzj7gdwcgnjfjsbdqh</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Frjáls þjóð</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2375328</id>
    <revision>
      <id>739962245</id>
      <parentid>739962209</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-09-18T06:06:01Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Egeymi</username>
        <id>16490385</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2040">{{Unreferenced|date=August 2008}}
The '''''Frjáls þjóð''''' (''{{Lang-is|Free Nation}}'') was a weekly [[newspaper]] published in [[Reykjavík]], [[Iceland]] from 1952 to 1967. Its policy was to protest against increasing American influence in Icelandic daily life. It was opposed to Icelandic membership of [[NATO]] and to [[Naval Air Station Keflavik|American bases on Icelandic soil]] in peacetime. It protested that American soldiers could wander around Iceland without being monitored, and also protested that American base television programs were visible to the Icelandic general public. It also criticised the [[United People's Socialist Party (Iceland)|United People's Socialist Party]] (''Sameiningarflokkur alþýðu, sósíalistaflokkurinn'') for being to loyal to the [[Soviet Union]]. The newspaper also fought against what it saw as corruption in Icelandic society and possible Icelandic membership of the [[European Union]]. In 1967 the newspaper supported [[Hannibal Valdimarsson]], the chairman of the electoral alliance [[People's Alliance (Iceland)|People's Alliance]], in his campaign for a seat in Parliament as an independent.

The editors and owners of ''Frjáls þjóð'' supported the [[National Preservation Party]] which was founded in 1953. Amongst the editors of this newspaper was one, [[Bergur Sigurbjörnsson]], who was Member of Parliament for the National Preservation Party 1953-1956, editor from the beginning in 1952 to 1954 and also in 1967. Two later editors/owners who became members of parliament were [[Ragnar Arnalds]] in 1960 and [[Jón Baldvin Hannibalsson]] 1964-1967.

{{DEFAULTSORT:Frjals Thjod}}
[[Category:Newspapers published in Iceland]]
[[Category:Defunct weekly newspapers]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1952]]
[[Category:Publications disestablished in 1967]]
[[Category:1952 establishments in Iceland]]
[[Category:1967 disestablishments in Iceland]]
[[Category:Media in Reykjavík]]
[[Category:Icelandic-language newspapers]]

{{Iceland-newspaper-stub}}
{{italic title}}</text>
      <sha1>8meoogrn9dq65t2rymk8ad93occv1iv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Greek Basket League Finals MVP</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>49264548</id>
    <revision>
      <id>833687676</id>
      <parentid>833687604</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-01T23:29:37Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wdurbin0010</username>
        <id>19037985</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Greek Basket League Finals MVP award winners */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8645">{{Greek Basket League awards}}
[[File:Νίκος Γκάλης.jpg|thumb|upright|240px|[[Nikos Galis]] was the [[Greek Basket League]] Finals MVP 5 times (1987, 1988, 1989, 1990, 1991).]]
The '''Greek Basket League Finals MVP''', or '''Greek Basket League Playoffs MVP''' [[Greek Basket League awards|award]] ([[Greek language|Greek]]: Ελληνικού Α1 Μπάσκετ Πρωταθλήματος Tελικός MVP) is the yearly Finals MVP award for the playoff finals of the [[Greek basketball league system|1st-tier]] professional [[basketball]] league in [[Greece]], the [[Greek Basket League]].

==Greek Basket League Finals MVP award winners==
[[File:Dejan Bodiroga green.jpg|thumb|upright|240px|[[Dejan Bodiroga]] was the [[Greek Basket League]] Finals MVP 2 times (1999, 2000).]]
[[File:Diamantidis 11052013.JPG|thumb|upright|240px|[[Dimitris Diamantidis]] was the [[Greek Basket League]] Finals MVP 6 times (2006, 2007, 2008, 2009, 2011, 2014).]]
[[File:Vasileios Spanoulis.jpg|thumb|upright|240px|[[Vassilis Spanoulis]] was the [[Greek Basket League]] Finals MVP 3 times (2012, 2015, 2016).]]
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
| style="background-color:#FFFF99; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; width:6em"| *
| [[List of members of the Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame|Member]] of the [[Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame]]
|-
| style="background-color:#FF9999; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; width:6em"| **
| [[List of members of the FIBA Hall of Fame|Member]] of the [[FIBA Hall of Fame]]
|-
| style="background-color:#FFCC99; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; width:6em"| ***
| Member of both the [[Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame|Naismith]] and [[FIBA Hall of Fame|FIBA]] Halls of Fame
|}

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
! Season !! '''Finals MVP''' !! Club !! Ref.
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1986–87&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFCC99"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Galis]]** || [[Aris B.C.|Aris]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1987–88&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFCC99"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Galis]]** (2×) || [[Aris B.C.|Aris]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1988–89&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFCC99"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Galis]]** (3×) || [[Aris B.C.|Aris]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1989–90&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFCC99"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Galis]]** (4×) || [[Aris B.C.|Aris]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1990–91&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFCC99"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Galis]]** (5×) || [[Aris B.C.|Aris]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1991–92&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FF9999"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Panagiotis Fasoulas]]** || [[PAOK B.C.|PAOK]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1992–93&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Georgios Sigalas]] || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1993–94&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Georgios Sigalas]] (2×) || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1994–95&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Georgios Sigalas]] (3×) || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1995–96&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Georgios Sigalas]] (4×) || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1996–97&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Georgios Sigalas]] (5×) || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1997–98&lt;/center&gt; || !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFFF99"| {{flagicon|Croatia}} [[Dino Rađja]]* || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;1998–99&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|FR Yugoslavia}} [[Dejan Bodiroga]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 1999-00|1999–00]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|FR Yugoslavia}} [[Dejan Bodiroga]] (2×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2000-01|2000–01]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|FR Yugoslavia}} [[Željko Rebrača]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2001-02|2001–02]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimos Dikoudis]] || [[AEK B.C.|AEK]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2002-03|2002–03]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|SLO}} [[Jaka Lakovič]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2003-04|2003–04]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Chatzivrettas]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2004-05|2004–05]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|SLO}} [[Jaka Lakovič]] (2×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2005-06|2005–06]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2006-07|2006–07]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] (2×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2007-08|2007–08]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] (3×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2008-09|2008–09]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] (4×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2009-10|2009–10]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|USA}} [[Mike Batiste]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2010-11|2010–11]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] (5×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2011-12|2011–12]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Vassilis Spanoulis]] || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] || &lt;center&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurohoops.net/featured/262345/vassilis-spanoulis-named-mvp-of-the-greek-finals Vassilis Spanoulis named MVP of the Greek Finals,]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2012-13|2012–13]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GAB}} [[Stéphane Lasme]] || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2013-14|2013–14]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] (6×) || [[Panathinaikos B.C.|Panathinaikos]] ||
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2014-15|2014–15]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Vassilis Spanoulis]] (2×) || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] || &lt;center&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurohoops.net/featured/262345/vassilis-spanoulis-named-mvp-of-the-greek-finals Vassilis Spanoulis named MVP of the Greek Finals,]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| &lt;center&gt;[[A1 Ethniki 2015-16|2015–16]]&lt;/center&gt; || {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Vassilis Spanoulis]] (3×) || [[Olympiacos B.C.|Olympiacos]] || &lt;center&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.eurohoops.net/featured/262345/vassilis-spanoulis-named-mvp-of-the-greek-finals Vassilis Spanoulis named MVP of the Greek Finals,]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.esake.gr/el/DFDA3270 TAGHeuer MVP των τελικών ο Σπανούλης {{el icon}}.]&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
|}

==Multiple Greek Basket League Finals MVP award winners==
{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
| style="background-color:#FFFF99; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; width:6em"| *
| [[List of members of the Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame|Member]] of the [[Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame]]
|-
| style="background-color:#FF9999; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; width:6em"| **
| [[List of members of the FIBA Hall of Fame|Member]] of the [[FIBA Hall of Fame]]
|-
| style="background-color:#FFCC99; border:1px solid #aaaaaa; width:6em"| ***
| Member of both the [[Naismith Memorial Basketball Hall of Fame|Naismith]] and [[FIBA Hall of Fame|FIBA]] Halls of Fame
|}

{| class="wikitable sortable"
|-
! '''Greek Basket League Finals MVP''' !! Number Of Greek Basket League Finals MVPs Won
|-
| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Dimitris Diamantidis]] || &lt;center&gt;(6×)&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Georgios Sigalas]] || &lt;center&gt;(5×)&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| !scope="row" style="background-color:#FFCC99"| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Nikos Galis]]** || &lt;center&gt;(5×)&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| {{flagicon|GRE}} [[Vassilis Spanoulis]] || &lt;center&gt;(3×)&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| {{flagicon|SLO}} [[Jaka Lakovič]] || &lt;center&gt;(2×)&lt;/center&gt;
|-
| {{flagicon|FR Yugoslavia}} [[Dejan Bodiroga]] || &lt;center&gt;(2×)&lt;/center&gt;
|}

==See also==
*[[Greek Basket League awards]]
*[[Greek Basket League MVP]]

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* [http://www.esake.gr Official Greek Basket League Site] {{el icon}}
* [https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC0RK8N84HBgZo6cTih0zTCw Official Greek Basket League YouTube Channel] {{el icon}}
* [http://www.basket.gr/ Official Hellenic Basketball Federation Site] {{el icon}}
* [http://www.basketblog.gr/ Basketblog.gr] {{el icon}}
* [http://www.greekbasketball.gr/ GreekBasketball.gr] {{el icon}}

{{European Basketball MVP Awards}}
{{Greek Basket League Finals MVPs}}
{{Basketball in Greece}}
{{Greek Basketball Championship}}

[[Category:Greek Basket League]]
[[Category:Greek Basket League awards|Finals MVP]]
[[Category:European basketball awards]]

{{Greece-stub}}
{{basketball-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>7zba7hgo8xoeegf6bwfhacx9ethpubo</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Greek–Yugoslav confederation</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>32726246</id>
    <revision>
      <id>807361833</id>
      <parentid>807361781</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-10-27T13:39:55Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>184.63.80.190</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="10213">[[File:Balkan Union.png|thumb|right|Map of the British backed Balkan Union, with prewar borders on the left, and postwar borders on the right.
{{legend|#2D5F2C|Initial "Greek-Yugoslav confederation" (step 1)}}
{{legend|#447C43|Expansion of confederation into "Balkan Union" (step 2)}}
{{legend|#5F935D|Final stage of expansion, a union of the "Balkan Union" and an expanded "[[Polish–Czechoslovak confederation]]" that would include Hungary. (step 3)}}]]
The '''Greek-Yugoslav confederation''' or '''federation'''{{Ref_label|a|a|none}}, or '''Balkan Union''', was a political concept during [[World War II]], sponsored by the [[United Kingdom]] and involving the [[Yugoslav government-in-exile]] and the [[Greek government-in-exile]]. The two governments signed an agreement pushing the proposal ahead, but it never got beyond the planning stage because of opposition from within the Yugoslav and the Greek governments, real world events, and the opposition of the [[Soviet Union]]. The proposal envisioned the creation of a [[confederation]] of [[Kingdom of Greece|Greece]] and [[Kingdom of Yugoslavia|Yugoslavia]].

==Background==
Greece and Yugoslavia were occupied by [[Nazi Germany]] and formed governments-in-exile in [[London]].&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;

Establishment of the union was the first step of the British "Eden plan": its final aim was to create a central-eastern union that was friendly to the west. The next step was to include [[Albania]], [[Bulgaria]] and [[Romania]] into a Balkan Union. The last step was to be folding of the Balkan Union with a Central European federation formed by [[Hungary]], [[Czechoslovakia]] and [[Poland]].{{sfn|Levy|2007|p=203}} The first step was restricted to only Yugoslavia and Greece because they were the only countries that supported the [[Allies of World War II|Allies]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Cahiers de Bruges, n.s|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=uXsOAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=12 January 2014|year=1971|publisher=College d'Europe|page=69|quote=Only two countries, Yugoslavia and Greece, were in the Allied camp, which explains why practical plans of a regional Balkan confederation had to be restricted to them.}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Agreement ==
The two governments-in-exile negotiated the conditions of the agreement until the end of 1941. The agreement was signed by [[Slobodan Jovanović]] and [[Emmanouil Tsouderos]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|title=Hidryma Meletōn Chersonēsou tou Haimou|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=AWgNAQAAIAAJ|accessdate=12 January 2014|year=1964|publisher=Institute for Balkan Studies|page=111|quote=Negotiations lasting until the end of 1941 led to the conclusion of an agreement, signed on January 15, 1942, by Prime Ministers Tsouderos and Slobodan Jovanovid, concerning the establishment of a Balkan Union whose primary}}&lt;/ref&gt; on the ceremony held in [[British Foreign Office]], presided by the British Foreign Minister [[Anthony Eden]]. The agreement explicitly stated that both governments looked forward to accede other countries of the Balkans to the Union.{{sfn|Kelly|2004|p=132}} quoted in {{harvtxt|Wheeler|1980|pp=157–8}} Although caution was advised with revealing the hope that Bulgaria and Romania would join the union, on 4 February 1942, Eden stated in the [[House of Commons of the United Kingdom|House of Commons]] that the treaty signed between Yugoslavia and Greece was going to be a basis for the establishment of the Balkan confederation.{{sfn|Kelly|2004|p=132}}

Encouraged by the British [[Foreign Office]], together with the [[Polish-Czechoslovak confederation]], they were to form a pro-Western organisation of states between Germany and the Soviet Union.&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Larres2002-2"/&gt;&lt;ref name="CapetSyWonyu2003"/&gt; Both governments-in-exile agreed to form a political, economic and military union, with the motto "The Balkans for the Balkan People".&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;

Their governments would not be unified but there would be much coordination between their respective parliaments and executives. Their respective monarchies were to be unified with the marriage of King [[Peter II of Yugoslavia|Peter of Yugoslavia]] to Princess [[Alexandra of Yugoslavia|Alexandra of Greece]].&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt; The union was to be finalised after the war.&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;

The marriage of Peter and Alexandra proved to be a problematic move and reduced support for the union from both governments-in-exile.&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt; On the international scene, the confederation was received favorably by [[Turkey]] but opposed by the Soviet Union, as [[Joseph Stalin]] saw no need for a strong and independent federation in Europe that could threaten his designs in Eastern Europe.&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Levy2007-201"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Lipgens1985"/&gt;&lt;ref name="Larres2002"/&gt;

==Demise==
In 1942, the British government decided to support [[Josip Tito]]'s forces instead of the [[Chetniks]] in Yugoslavia and rejected the plan as unworkable.{{sfn|Kola|2003|p=84}} In 1944, the British withdrew their recognition for the Yugoslav government and recognised the communist [[Yugoslav National Committee of Liberation]] of [[Ivan Subasic]], who was subordinate to Tito.&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;

As the war ended, Yugoslavia shifted towards the communist camp, and the [[Greek Civil War]] started.&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"/&gt;

With little support for the confederation from any existing powers, it was never realised, but it was briefly entertained in the form of a communist federation by some regional communist leaders, shortly after the war.&lt;ref name="Roberts2006"/&gt;

== Alternative plans ==
By the end of 1944, the [[Yugoslav Communist Party]] began the development of alternative plans for establishment of a [[Balkan Federation]]. Because Churchill and Stalin agreed that Greece would be in the Western sphere of influence, the plans had to exclude Greece.{{sfn|Kola|2003|p=85}}

==See also==
*[[Międzymorze]]

==Notes==
'''a''' {{Note_label|a|a|none}} As the details of the planned union were never finalized, it is not clear whether it would be a federation or a [[confederation]]. Sources use both the term "Greek-Yugoslav federation" and the term "Greek-Yugoslav confederation".

==References==
{{reflist|2|refs=
*&lt;ref name="CapetSyWonyu2003"&gt;{{cite book|author1=Antoine Capet|author2=Aïssatou Sy-Wonyu|title=The "Special Relationship"|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=QpHzjq-KqnkC&amp;pg=PA30|accessdate=12 August 2011|year=2003|publisher=Publication Univ Rouen Havre|isbn=978-2-87775-341-8|page=30}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name="Larres2002-2"&gt;{{cite book|author=Klaus Larres|title=Churchill's Cold War: the politics of personal diplomacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bo1POHRb3H8C&amp;pg=PA58|accessdate=12 August 2011|year=2002|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-09438-1|page=58}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name="Larres2002"&gt;{{cite book|author=Klaus Larres|title=Churchill's Cold War: the politics of personal diplomacy|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=bo1POHRb3H8C&amp;pg=PA64|accessdate=10 August 2011|year=2002|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-09438-1|pages=64–65}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name="Levy2007-201"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jonathan Levy|title=The Intermarium: Wilson, Madison, &amp; East Central European Federalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wNb4RXDxEt4C&amp;pg=PA201|accessdate=10 August 2011|date=6 June 2007|publisher=Universal-Publishers|isbn=978-1-58112-369-2|page=201}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name="Levy2007-203-205"&gt;{{cite book|author=Jonathan Levy|title=The Intermarium: Wilson, Madison, &amp; East Central European Federalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wNb4RXDxEt4C&amp;pg=PA203|accessdate=12 August 2011|date=6 June 2007|publisher=Universal-Publishers|isbn=978-1-58112-369-2|pages=203–205}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name="Lipgens1985"&gt;{{cite book|author=Walter Lipgens|title=Documents on the history of European integration: Plans for European union in Great Britain and in exile, 1939–1945 (including 107 documents in their original languages on 3 microfiches)|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=X3TsVCAt9F4C&amp;pg=PA648|accessdate=10 August 2011|year=1985|publisher=Walter de Gruyter|isbn=978-3-11-009724-5|page=648}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*&lt;ref name="Roberts2006"&gt;{{cite book|author=Geoffrey Roberts|title=Stalin's wars: from World War to Cold War, 1939–1953|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5GCFUqBRZ-QC&amp;pg=PA348|accessdate=12 August 2011|year=2006|publisher=Yale University Press|isbn=978-0-300-11204-7|page=348}}&lt;/ref&gt;
}}

== Sources ==
* {{cite book|last1=Briggs|first1=A.|last2=Meyer|first2=E.|last3=Thomson|first3=David|title=Patterns of Peacemaking|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=8fFEAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA190|accessdate=12 January 2014|year= 2013|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-136-23257-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last= Kelly|first=George |authorlink=George Kelly (psychologist)|title=The Psychology of Personal Constructs: Volume One: Theory and Personality|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=LuTKHujU37sC&amp;pg=PA132|accessdate=12 January 2014|year= 2004|publisher=Routledge|isbn=978-1-134-48878-0|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Kola|first=Paulin|title=The Search for Greater Albania|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=W_LV5RJe_EkC&amp;pg=PA83|accessdate=12 January 2014|year= 2003|publisher=C. Hurst &amp; Co. Publishers|isbn=978-1-85065-596-1|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last= Levy|first=Jonathan |title=The Intermarium: Wilson, Madison, and East Central European Federalism|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=wNb4RXDxEt4C&amp;pg=PA203|accessdate=12 January 2014|year= 2007|publisher=Universal-Publishers|isbn=978-1-58112-369-2|ref=harv}}
* {{cite book|last=Wheeler|first=Mark C.|title=Britain and the war for Yugoslavia, 1940-1943|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=3aB4AAAAIAAJ|year=1980|publisher=East European Monographs|isbn=978-0-914710-57-8|ref=harv}}
{{Greece during World War II|state=collapsed}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Greek-Yugoslav confederation}}
[[Category:Greece–Yugoslavia relations]]
[[Category:Federalism]]
[[Category:Greece in World War II]]
[[Category:Yugoslavia in World War II]]
[[Category:Political history of Greece]]
[[Category:Political history of Yugoslavia]]
[[Category:Proposed countries]]</text>
      <sha1>88cc6hmb7dibbrf22q5myxw5wx4r28j</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Heidi Hollinger</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>13511683</id>
    <revision>
      <id>852799534</id>
      <parentid>852798670</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-07-31T12:57:30Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Lopifalko</username>
        <id>11116033</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Move prosaic info from lead into body + [[MOS:BIRTHPLACE]] + copyedit + add wikilink + [[WP:SURNAME]] + exhibitions are always "selected" + change ref warning</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="5571">{{BLP refimprove|date=March 2018}}
{{Infobox artist
| honorific_prefix = 
| name             = Heidi Hollinger
| honorific_suffix = 
| image            = HeidiHollingerimg587ts-signed.jpg
| image_size       = 
| alt              = 
| caption          = Hollinger, Montreal, 1994
| native_name      = 
| native_name_lang = 
| birth_name       = &lt;!-- only use if different than name --&gt;
| birth_date       = {{birth year and age|1968}}
| birth_place      = [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]]
| nationality      = 
| education        = 
| alma_mater       = [[McGill University]]&lt;ref name="McGill"&gt;{{cite web|title=The bilingual globetrotter|url=http://mcgillnews.mcgill.ca/s/1762/news/interior.aspx?sid=1762&amp;gid=2&amp;pgid=850|publisher=McGill University|accessdate=27 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
| known_for        = [[photography]]
| notable_works    = 
| style            = 
| movement         = 
| spouse           = 
| awards           = &lt;!-- {{awd|award|year|title|role|name}} (optional) --&gt;
| elected          =
| patrons          = 
| memorials        = 
| website          = {{URL|heidihollinger.com}}
}}

'''Heidi Hollinger''' (born 1968) is a political photographer and documentary presenter. 

==Life and work==
Hollinger was born in [[Montreal]], [[Quebec]].

After opening a photo studio in Moscow, she photographed over 100 political conventions in Russia, and traveled extensively to photograph other world leaders, including [[Vladimir Putin]], [[Mikhail Gorbachev]], [[Jean Chrétien]], [[Fidel Castro]], and the [[Dalai Lama]].

After living for ten years in Moscow she returned to Montreal. For four years starting January, 2011, she was a presenter of documentary series ''Waterfront Cities of The World'' for [[Discovery Channel]]. Each of 39 episodes of this series described one of the port cities in different parts of the world.&lt;ref name="McGill" /&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Waterfront Cities of The World|url=http://thetvdb.com/?tab=seasonall&amp;id=250675|publisher=The TVDB.com|accessdate=27 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Waterfront Cities of the World - Examining port cities with photographer Heidi Hollinger|url=http://www.tvguide.com/tvshows/waterfront-cities-of-the-world-2015/episode-8-season-4/seoul/348742/|website=TV Guide|publisher=CBS Interactive Inc.|accessdate=27 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Exhibitions==
*''Faces of the Opposition,'' Moscow Photo Center (1994); Kazan, Tartarstan (1994); Omsk, Russia (1994); Bergamot Station Galleries, Los Angeles (1995);&lt;ref name="molva"&gt;{{cite web|title=Фотоальбом Хайди Холлинджер|url=http://www.molva.ru/gallary/article984.html?fst=106|website=Молва.ru|publisher=Lavtech.com Corp.|accessdate=27 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Building Moscow,'' Moscow City Hall (1995)&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Politicians from A to Z,'' The State Duma, Moscow (1996)&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''New Genre: The Russian Political Portrait,'' Manezh Gallery, Moscow (1996)&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Contemporary Artists,'' Metropole, Moscow (1996)
*''Politicians,'' Almaty (1998); Saratov (1999)&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Peculiarities of National Politicians,'' Manezh Central Exhibition Hall, Moscow (1999); The State Duma, Moscow (2000)&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Russians,'' Tretyakov Gallery, Moscow (2000); Canadian Embassy, Moscow (2000); Mike Bossy, Montreal (2000).
*''100 years of Moscow'' (as part of group show), Montreal City Hall (2000)
*''10 years in Moscow,'' Canadian Parliament, Ottawa (2001); Russian Embassy, Ottawa (2001)
*''The Russians Emerge,'' Russian Consulate, New York (2002); Philadelphia (2003); Cirque du Soleil, Montreal (2003); The Arts Factory, Las Vegas (2004); Carlu, Toronto (2004).
*''The Himalayas,'' Biosphere, Montreal (2004)
*''Selected Histories,'' Groupe Cossette, Montreal (2004)
*''Distinct Society,'' HollingerCollins Gallery, Montreal (2006)
*''300 Reasons to Love Havana/300 raisons d'aimer La Havane,'' [[Montreal Museum of Fine Arts]] (foyer Boutique-Librairie M) (March-November 2018)

==Books==
*''Heidi Chez Les Soviets, Les Intouchables.'' Montreal, 1999.&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Peculiarities of Russian Politicians.'' Moscow: Vagrius, 1999.&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Les Russes, Les Éditions Stanké.'' Montreal, 2000.&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''Russians.'' Moscow: Vagrius, 2000.&lt;ref name="molva" /&gt;
*''The Russians Emerge.'' New York: Abbeville, 2002. {{ISBN|0789207575}}.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Heidi Hollinger|url=https://www.abbeville.com/authors/heidi-hollinger-451|publisher=Abbeville Press|accessdate=27 July 2017}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*''Monsieur Poutine, Vous Permettez?.'' Montreal: Semaine, 2008.
*''300 Reasons to Love Havana.'' Montreal: Homme, 2018.
*''300 raisons d'aimer La Havane.'' Montreal: Homme, 2018.

==Collections==
Hollinger’s photos can be found in the permanent collections of the [[Moscow History Museum]], the [[Moscow House of Photography]], the [[Cirque du Soleil]] and the [[Montreal Museum of Contemporary Art]].{{citation needed|date=March 2017}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

==External links==
*{{Official website|www.heidihollinger.com}}
*[https://www.mcgill.ca/news/2001/spring/heidi/ "The Heidi Chronicles"] ''McGill News'', alumni quarterly, spring 2001

{{Authority control}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Hollinger, Heidi}}
[[Category:1968 births]]
[[Category:Living people]]
[[Category:Canadian photographers]]
[[Category:Photography in Russia]]
[[Category:Canadian people of Finnish descent]]
[[Category:Artists from Montreal]]
[[Category:McGill University alumni]]
[[Category:Moscow State University faculty]]
[[Category:Canadian women photographers]]

{{Russia-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>84ud3xwjim6lxazf1hxlmt4n8bx7kk2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Joint Control Commission</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4845874</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862630957</id>
      <parentid>804861360</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-05T16:49:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Donutcity</username>
        <id>12848559</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>grammar</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3487">{{Distinguish|Joint Control Commission for Georgian–Ossetian Conflict Resolution}}The '''Joint Control Commission''' (JCC, {{lang-ru|Объединенная контрольная комиссия - ОКК}}) is a tri-lateral [[peacekeeping]] force and joint military command structure from [[Moldova]], [[Transnistria]], and [[Russia]] that operates in a [[buffer zone]] on the border between the [[Republic of Moldova]] and [[Ukraine]]. The disputed territory between the two is controlled by the Pridnestrovian Moldavian Republic (Transnistria, PMR). 

==History==
Following the [[War of Transnistria]], the Joint Control Commission was established on the initiative of Russian president [[Boris Yeltsin]] by the signing of a [[cease-fire]] agreement on July 21, 1992. It consists of soldiers from the [[Military of Moldova|armed forces of Moldova]], the [[Pridnestrovian Moldavian Republic|PMR]] and [[Armed Forces of the Russian Federation]], originally with a numerical underrepresentation{{Clarify|date=August 2009}} of the PMR. In 1998, the commission was enlarged by the addition of 10 Ukrainian [[military observer]]s. Moreover, the [[Organization for Security and Co-operation in Europe]] also has a Transnistria-based observation mission and participates in all JCC meetings. The current peacekeeping mechanism is a [[multi-state mission]] equipped with an [[international mandate]] that began deployment on 29 July 1992.&lt;ref&gt;[https://www.state.gov/documents/organization/13611.pdf]&lt;/ref&gt;

Of the three original sides supplying troops, [[Russia]] has traditionally provided the most with [[Moldova]] second and the smallest contingent provided by Transnistria.{{Clarify|date=August 2009}} As of 2006, however, both Moldova and the PMR participate with slightly more soldiers than Russia: Moldova currently supplies 403 men to the force, the PMR 411 men and Russia up to 385 men.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olvia.idknet.com/ol143-07-06.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

==Mission==
The Joint Control Commission is charged with ensuring observance of the ceasefire and security arrangements and has generally been successful, as the armed conflict has not at any time re-erupted since 1992. The [[demilitarized]] buffer zone, known locally as the ''Dniester Valley security zone'', roughly follows the outline of the [[Dniester]] river. It is 225 kilometres long and from 1 to 15 kilometres wide.{{cn|date=November 2012}}

As per the 1992 agreement with Moldova, Russia has a right to keep 2,400 troops in Transnistria. However, as of 2006 the number of Russian troops was just 1,500, with between 349 and 385 of those assigned to JCC at any given time.&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.olvia.idknet.com/ol49-05-06.htm]&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Colbasna]]
* [[14th Army involvement in Transnistria]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}
# {{cite book
 | editor = John Mackinlay, Peter Cross (editors)
 | title = Regional Peacekeepers
 | publisher = United Nations University Press
 | isbn = 92-808-1079-0
 }}
# {{cite news
 | url = http://www.nato.int/acad/fellow/99-01.htm
 | author = Ion Mardarovici
 | title = NATO and the security in the Eastern countries during transition times
 | publisher = NATO Fellowship Program
 | date = 2002
 }}

==External links ==
* http://www.okk-pridnestrovie.org/p0088.htm

[[Category:History of Transnistria since 1991]]
[[Category:Politics of Transnistria]]
[[Category:Politics of Moldova]]
[[Category:Military of Moldova]]
[[Category:Military of Russia]]

{{Moldova-stub}}
{{Transnistria-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>jr0mtnjgbq5dejuv4x3ka0g0tf052l2</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Khon Kaen Sugar</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21420092</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853674608</id>
      <parentid>849492373</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-06T08:10:26Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>58.10.213.131</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3824">{{Infobox company
| name             = Khon Kaen Sugar
| logo             = Khon Kaen Sugar (logo).jpg
| caption          = 
| type             = [[Public company|Public]]
| traded_as        = {{SET|KSL}}
| fate             = 
| predecessor      = 
| successor        = 
| foundation       = {{Start date and age|1945}}
| founder          = 
| defunct          = 
| location_city    = [[Bangkok]]
| location_country = [[Thailand]]
| locations        = 
| area_served      = 
| key_people       = 
| industry         = [[Food]]
| products         = [[Sugar]]
| services         = 
| revenue          = {{decrease}} [[United States dollar|US$]] 552.6 million (2014)&lt;ref name="Financial Data"&gt;[http://www.set.or.th/set/companyhighlight.do?symbol=KSL&amp;ssoPageId=5 KSL Financial Data], then using the December 31, 2014 exchange rate of 1 baht = 0.02812 US dollar &lt;/ref&gt;
| operating_income = 
| net_income       = {{decrease}} [[United States dollar|US$]] 45.7 million (2014)&lt;ref name="Financial Data" /&gt;
| aum              = 
| assets           = {{increase}} [[United States dollar|US$]] 1.1 billion (2014)&lt;ref name="Financial Data" /&gt;
| equity           = 
| owner            = 
| num_employees    = 
| parent           = 
| divisions        = 
| subsid           = 
| homepage         = {{URL|www.kslsugar.com/en/home}}
| footnotes        = 
| intl             = 
}}
'''Khon Kaen Sugar''' (KSL) is a [[sugar|sugar-manufacturing company]] based in [[Thailand]]. Its corporate headquarters are in [[Bangkok]].  Principal manufacturing facilities are in [[Khon Kaen]], northeastern Thailand.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=About KSL |url=http://www.kslsugar.com/en/profile |website=KSL Group |accessdate=5 August 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150903173248/http://www.kslsugar.com/en/profile |archivedate=3 September 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==History==
Khon Kaen Sugar was founded as Kwang Soon Lee in 1945 in Bangkok and in 1952 moved to a plant in [[Thonburi]], producing 250 bags of sugar a day. The company spent the next decades merging with and acquiring companies and in 1974 organized itself and its companies as KSL Group. It one of six sugar companies listed on the [[Stock Exchange of Thailand]] (SET) and is on the [[SET50 Index and SET100 Index#SET50 Index constituent companies|SET50 Index]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=List of Companies / Securities|url=http://www.set.or.th/en/company/companylist.html|website=The Stock Exchange of Thailand (SET)|accessdate=5 August 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Subsidiaries==
Other KSL subsidiary companies include Thai Fermentation Industry, which produces Red Spoon brand [[condiment]]s and is the largest exporter of seasoning products in Thailand; and Chengteh Chinaware Thailand, which produces and trades [[ceramic]] [[gift|giftware]].  As of 2003 KSL is working to use waste [[molasses]] and [[bagasse]] for the production of [[ethanol]] and [[gasahol]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Business and Products |url=http://www.kslsugar.com/en/product |website=KSL Group |accessdate=5 August 2015 |deadurl=yes |archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20150903173248/http://www.kslsugar.com/en/product |archivedate=3 September 2015 |df= }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://finance.google.com/finance?q=BAK%3AKSL Google finance, Khon Kaen Sugar]{{DL|date=August 2015}}
*[https://www.bloomberg.com/apps/quote?ticker=KSL%3ATB Bloomberg, Khon Kaen Sugar]


{{Asia-company-stub}}
{{Thailand-stub}}
[[Category:Food and drink companies of Thailand]]
[[Category:Manufacturing companies based in Bangkok]]
[[Category:Khon Kaen]]
[[Category:Sugar companies]]
[[Category:Companies listed on the Stock Exchange of Thailand]]
[[Category:1945 establishments in Thailand]]
[[Category:Food and drink companies established in 1945]]
[[Category:Agriculture companies of Thailand]]</text>
      <sha1>04253j5z7pxqim18c70g3cvjsrx0wm0</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Komba gewerkschaft</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>11044256</id>
    <revision>
      <id>676631429</id>
      <parentid>676631292</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-08-18T06:12:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Oneforfortytwo</username>
        <id>9351822</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="894">{{lowercase title}}
{{Infobox Union
|name= komba
|country= [[Germany]]
|affiliation=
|members= 80,000
|full_name= komba gewerkschaft
|native_name=
|image= &lt;!-- Image with inadequate rationale removed: [[File:DBB logo.png|200px]] --&gt;
|founded=
|current=
|head=
|dissolved_date=
|dissolved_state=
|merged_into=
|office= [[Berlin]], Germany
|people= Heinz Ossenkamp, president
|website= [http://www.komba.de www.komba.de]
|footnotes=
}}
&lt;!-- Include all unused fields for future use. See [[template talk:Infobox Union]] for usage. --&gt;

The '''komba gewerkschaft''' is a [[Germany|German]] [[trade union]] in [[Berlin]]. It organises over 80.000 local administration workers.

==External links==
*[http://www.komba.de komba gewerkschaft]

{{Portal|Organized labour}}

[[Category:Trade unions in Germany]]
[[Category:Organisations based in Berlin]]


{{Europe-trade-union-stub}}
{{Germany-org-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>726whzvbbf0g36265kuxu0gqi7ij9lr</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Krajowe Eliminacje do Konkursu Piosenki Eurowizji</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30321046</id>
    <revision>
      <id>867099070</id>
      <parentid>867034165</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-03T17:13:15Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Kornelisahovit</username>
        <id>25240411</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Winners */ ..</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1393">'''''Krajowe Eliminacje do Konkursu Piosenki Eurowizji''''' ("National Qualification for the Eurovision Song Contest") is the first Polish national selection for the country's entry to the [[Eurovision Song Contest]]. The first contest was held in 2003 and the last in 2004. In 2006 it was renamed ''[[Piosenka dla Europy]]''.

==Winners==
{| class="wikitable sortable"
!Year
!Song
!Artist
!Songwriter(s)
! Final
! Points
! Semi-final
! Points
|-
|-
| [[Poland in the Eurovision Song Contest 2003|2003]]
| [[Keine Grenzen-Żadnych granic]]
| [[Ich Troje]]
| [[André Franke]], [[Jacek Łągwa]],&lt;br&gt;[[Michał Wiśniewski]], [[Joachim Horn-Bernges]]
| 7th
|90
|data-sort-value="99999" colspan="2" {{N/A|No semi-finals}}
|-
| [[Poland in the Eurovision Song Contest 2004|2004]]
| [[Love Song (Blue Café song)|Love Song]]
| [[Blue Café]]
| [[Paweł Rurak-Sokal]], [[Tatiana Okupnik]]
| 17th
|27
|colspan="2" data-sort-value="-9999" {{N/A|Top 11 previous year}}
|}

==See also==
*[[Piosenka dla Europy]]
*[[Krajowe Eliminacje]]
*[[Poland in the Eurovision Song Contest]]

==External links==
* [http://www.eurowizja.org/ Polish OGAE site]
* [http://www.eurowizja.com.pl/ Polish official site]

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Poland in Eurovision}}
{{Eurovision Song Contest}}
{{poland-stub}}

[[Category:Poland in the Eurovision Song Contest]]
[[Category:Eurovision Song Contest selection events]]</text>
      <sha1>nhzwobg618f1pwk6shkfv4jru1szhx1</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lebonya languages</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>33599143</id>
    <revision>
      <id>860129679</id>
      <parentid>674587616</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-09-18T14:53:25Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JHunterJ</username>
        <id>842922</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>unneeded italics</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="851">{{Infobox language family
|name=Lebonya
|region=[[Democratic Republic of the Congo]]
|familycolor=Niger-Congo
|fam2=[[Atlantic–Congo]]
|fam3=[[Benue–Congo]]
|fam4=[[Southern Bantoid]]
|fam5=[[Bantu languages|Bantu]] ([[Guthrie classification of Bantu languages#Zone D|Zone D]])
|child1=[[Lengola language|Lengola]]
|child2=[[Bodo language (Bantu)|Bodo]]
|child3=[[Nyali languages|Nyali]]
|glotto=lebo1246
|glottorefname=Lebonya
}}

'''Lebonya''' is a proposed intermediate group of [[Bantu languages]] coded Zone D in Guthrie's classification. There are three branches:
*[[Lengola language|Lengola]]
*[[Bodo language (Bantu)|Bodo]]
*the [[Nyali languages]]

''Glottolog'' 2.3 classifies Bodo instead as one of the [[Ngendan languages]].

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{Narrow Bantu languages}}
[[Category:Lebonya languages| ]]


{{Bantu-lang-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>mxoxjuvjslxmy2jiesd3z2q0x6cla0n</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Lisbon Zoo</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>19244915</id>
    <revision>
      <id>814542555</id>
      <parentid>753951020</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-12-09T12:28:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>CommonsDelinker</username>
        <id>2304267</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Replacing Pigs_July_2008-1.jpg with [[File:Pot-bellied_pigs_in_Lisbon_Zoo_2008.jpg]] (by [[commons:User:CommonsDelinker|CommonsDelinker]] because: [[:c:COM:FR|File renamed]]: [[:c:COM:FR#FR2|Criterion 2]] (meaningless or ambiguous name) · optional tex...</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1956">{{expand language|topic=|langcode=pt|otherarticle=Jardim Zoológico de Lisboa|date=October 2012}}
{{Infobox zoo
|zoo_name         = Lisbon Zoo
|logo             =
|logo_caption     =
|image            = Jardim Zoologico Lisboa 1.JPG
|image_caption    = Main entrance
|location         = [[Lisbon]], [[Portugal]]
|date_opened      = 1884
|date_closed      =
|coordinates      = {{coord|38|44.69476|N|9|10.28887|W|type:landmark_scale:2500_region:PT_source:dewiki|display=it}}
|area             =
|num_species      = 300
|num_animals      = 2,000
|largest_tank_vol = 
|total_tank_vol   =
|annual_visitors  = 800,000
|members          =
|exhibits         =
|website          = {{URL|http://www.zoo.pt/}}
}}
'''Lisbon Zoo''' (Jardim Zoologico de Lisboa) is a zoological garden in [[Lisbon]], [[Portugal]]. It was founded in 1884. It was the product of the efforts of Dr. Van Der Laan, owner of the largest aviary in Portugal, with the support of Bento de Sousa, Sousa Martins, and May Figueira. 
In 1905 it was transferred to its present location in Sete Rios, Lisbon.

About 2,000 animals of more than 300 species are represented:
*Approximately 
*114 [[mammals]]
*157 [[birds]]
*56 [[reptiles]]
*5 [[amphibian]]s and [[arthropods]]

[[File:Pot-bellied pigs in Lisbon Zoo 2008.jpg|thumb|left|Two [[pot-bellied pig]]s sleeping at Lisbon Zoo.]]
The mission of the Lisbon Zoo includes the conservation and breeding of endangered species, as well as scientific research, and educational and recreational activities. About 800,000 people visit the zoo annually.
{{Clear}}

==External links==
*{{Commons category-inline|Jardim Zoológico de Lisboa|Lisbon Zoo}}
*{{Official website|http://www.zoo.pt/}} (Portuguese)


{{Zoos of Portugal}}

[[Category:Buildings and structures in Lisbon|Zoo]]
[[Category:Zoos in Portugal]]
[[Category:1884 establishments in Portugal]]
[[Category:Tourist attractions in Lisbon]]
[[Category:Zoos established in 1884]]


{{Portugal-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>rwjg37y6x50xbijtkbsh36jbffl5j6z</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>List of supermarket chains in Asia</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15412125</id>
    <revision>
      <id>871676513</id>
      <parentid>870925027</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-12-02T18:52:40Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Aspects</username>
        <id>4441371</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Removed flagicons per [[WP:MOSICON]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="8519">{{refimprove|date=February 2013}}
This is a '''[[list of supermarket chains]] in [[Asia]]'''.

==[[Afghanistan]]==
* A-One
* Chelsea Supermarket&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.smninvest.com/finest-superstore SMN Investments | Partnerships for peace and prosperity » Finest Superstore]&lt;/ref&gt;
* Finest Superstore
* Global
* [[Spinneys]]

==[[Armenia]]==
* [[Carrefour]]
* Galaxy
* SAS supermarket
* Star
* SuperStar
* Yerevan City

==[[Azerbaijan]]==
* Ameli
* City Market
* Continental
* [[Migros]] Türk

==[[Bangladesh]]==
* Agora Supermarkets
* Almas
* Best Buy
* Canteen Stores Department
* Family Needs
* Family World
* Komart
* Lavender
* Meena Bazar
* Nandan
* Prince Bazar
* Priyo
* Sad Musa City Center
* Shwapno
* Unimart

==[[Bahrain]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Bahrain}}

==[[China]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in the People's Republic of China}}

==[[Cyprus]]==
* AlphaMega
* [[Carrefour]]
* E&amp;S
* [[Lidl]]
* [[METRO (supermarket)]]
* Olympic

==[[Egypt]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Egypt}}

==[[Georgia (country)|Georgia]]==
* [[Carrefour]]
* [[SPAR]] - 100 stores&lt;ref&gt;https://www.esmmagazine.com/spar-opens-100th-store-in-georgia/66989&lt;/ref&gt;

==[[Hong Kong]]==
* 759 Stores
* [[ÆON]] ([[JUSCO]]) 
* [[c!ty'super]]
* [[China Resources Vanguard Shop]]
** Volè
** USelect
* [[DCH Food Mart]]
* KaiBo
* [[Marks &amp; Spencer]]
* [[PARKnSHOP]]
** Fusion
** Grand
** Gourmet
**International
**Taste
* [[Seibu Department Stores]]
* [[Seiyu Group]]
* [[Sogo]] (also considered a [[department store]])
* [[Uny]] APiTA
* [[Wellcome]]
** [[Market Place by Jasons]]

==[[India]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in India}}

==[[Indonesia]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Indonesia}}

==[[Iran]]==
* Almas Shahr, Diamond City
* [[Carrefour]]
* Hyperstar Market (Carrefour)
* [[Proma Hypermarket]]
* [[Refah Chain Stores Co.]] 
* [[Shahrvand Chain Stores Inc.]]
* Hyperme Pazh Mashhad City

==[[Israel]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Israel}}
* Alef
* [[ampm]]
* Blue Square
* Clubmarket
* Eden Teva Market
* Hazi Hinam
* Hyper-Kol
* Mega
* Mister Zol
* [[Rami Levy Hashikma Marketing|Rami Levy]]
* Shefa Shuk
* [[Shufersal]]
* Stop market
* [[Super-Sol]]
* [[Tiv Taam]]
* [[Victory]]
* Yaanot bitan
* [[Yesh]]
* Zol Po

==[[Japan]]==
* [[Albis (store)|Albis]]
* Arks and Universe - [[Hokkaido]], [[Aomori Prefecture]], [[Iwate Prefecture]] and [[Akita Prefecture]] {{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}
* Beisia - [[Kantō region]] and [[Kōshin'etsu region]], mainly [[Gunma Prefecture]]
* Direx - discount store in [[Kyushu]], [[San'yō region]] and [[Ryukyu Island]] area, mainly [[Saga Prefecture]]
* [[Don Quijote (store)|Don Quixote]] - discount store
* Fuji - [[Shikoku]] and [[San'yō region]], mainly [[Ehime Prefecture]]
* Heiwado - [[Shiga Prefecture|Shiga]], [[Kyoto]] and [[Hokuriku region]]
* [[Ito-Yokado]]
* Izumi - [[Chūgoku region]] and [[Northern Kyūshū]], mainly [[Hiroshima Prefecture]]
* [[Izumiya]]
* [[Kanesue]]
* [[Kansai Super]]
* Lamu - discount store
* Life
* Mandai - [[Osaka Prefecture]] and [[Hyogo Prefecture]] {{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}
* [[Maxvalu Tokai]]
* Oasis - Kansai area, owned by [[Hankyu]].
* Oisix
* OK Store, [[Greater Tokyo Area|Tokyo Metropolitan Area]] and [[Sendai]]&lt;ref&gt;[[:ja:オーケー]] '''(Japanese language)''' Retrieved date on July 14, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;
* Okuwa - Southern [[Kansai region]] and [[Tōkai region]], mainly [[Wakayama Prefecture]]
* Ryubo - [[Okinawa Prefecture]] {{Citation needed|date=December 2011}}
* [[Seiyu (retailer)|Seiyu]]
* [[Seiyu Group]]
* Summit
* Sunny Mart - [[Shikoku]], mainly [[Kōchi Prefecture]]
* Trial - discount store, mainly Kyushu
* [[Uny]] Apita, Biago
* Uoroku - regional chain in [[Niigata Prefecture]]
* Valor - [[Chūbu region]], mainly [[Gifu Prefecture]]
* Yamazawa - regional chain in [[Yamagata Prefecture]] and [[Sendai]] area
* Yaokō, [[Kanto region]], mainly [[Saitama Prefecture]] and [[Chiba Prefecture]].&lt;ref&gt;[[:ja:ヤオコー]] '''(Japanese language)''' Retrieved date on July 14, 2017.&lt;/ref&gt;

==[[Kazakhstan]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Kazakhstan}}

==[[Kuwait]]==
* [[Carrefour]]
* [[City Center]]
* [[Geant]]
* Grand Hypermarket
* Gulfmart
* [[Lulu Hypermarket]]
* [[Lulu Hypermarket|Lulu Supermarket]]
* [[The Sultan Center]]

==[[Laos]]==
* [[Big C]]
* Rimping (located at the ViewMall)

==[[Lebanon]]==
* [[Carrefour]]&lt;ref&gt;[[Carrefour]]&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Monoprix]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.monoprix.com.lb&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[Spinneys]]&lt;ref&gt;http://www.spinneys-lebanon.com&lt;/ref&gt;
* [[The Sultan Center]]&lt;ref&gt;[[The Sultan Center]]&lt;/ref&gt;

==[[Malaysia]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Malaysia}}

==[[Mongolia]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Mongolia}}

==[[Nepal]]==
*[[BhatBhateni Supermarket and Departmental Store]]

==[[Northern Cyprus]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Northern Cyprus}}

==[[Pakistan]]==
* [[Agha's Supermarket]]
* [[Alpha Supermarket]] ''([[Tesco]])''
* [[ARY Cash and Carry]]
* [[Canteen Stores Department (Pakistan)|CSD Pakistan]]
* [[Chase Up]]
* [[Chase Value Centre]]
* [[Diamond Super Market]]
* [[MDS SUPER MARKET ]]
* [[EBCO Supermarket]]
* [[Green Valley Pakistan]]
* [[Carrefour|Hyperstar Pakistan]]
* [[Imtiaz Super Market]]
* [[Metro_Cash_and_Carry#Pakistan|Metro Cash and Carry Pakistan]]
* [[Naheed Supermarket]]
* [[PSO Shop Stop|Shop Stop]] ([[Pakistan State Oil|PSO]])
* [[Spar (retailer)|Spar Pakistan]]
* [[Utility Stores Corporation]]

==[[Philippines]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in the Philippines}}

==[[Russia]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Russia}}

==[[Singapore]]==
* [[Cold Storage (supermarket)|Cold Storage]] ([[Dairy Farm International Holdings|DFI Group]])
* [[Giant Hypermarket|Giant]] ([[Dairy Farm International Holdings|DFI Group]])
* [[Market Place by Jasons|Jasons Market Place]] ([[Dairy Farm International Holdings|DFI Group]])
* [[NTUC Fairprice]]
* [[Prime Supermarket]]
* [[Sheng Siong]]
* U Star Supermarket
* YES Supermarket
* Taste Supermarket
* Honestbee Habitat 
* RedMart Supermarket
* BigBox Supermarket
* Mahota Supermarket
* YES Supermarket
* Mustafa Supermarket

==[[South Korea]]==
* [[Costco]]
* [[E-mart]]
* [[Hanaro Mart]]
* [[Lotte Mart]]
* [[Mega Mart]]
* [[Homeplus]]

==[[Sri Lanka]]==
* Arpico Super Centres
* Cargills (Ceylon) PLC (Food City)
* Keells Super (Jaykay Marketing Services)
* Lanka Sathosa
* Laugfs Sunup Supermarkets (pvt) Ltd
* Star United&lt;ref&gt;http://www.sundaytimes.lk/130113/business-times/new-supermarket-chain-emerges-27815.html&lt;/ref&gt;

==[[Taiwan]]==
* [[A.mart]]
* [[c!ty'super]]
* [[Carrefour]]
* [[Costco]]
* [[PXmart]]
* [[RT-Mart]]
* [[Wellcome]]

==[[Thailand]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Thailand}}

==[[Turkey]]==
{{main|List of supermarket chains in Turkey}}

==[[United Arab Emirates]]==
* AAl Maya Lal's Supermarket
* Abela Supermarket
* Abu Dhabi Cooperative Society&lt;!-- (http://www.adcoops.com/)--&gt;
* Al Ain Cooperative Society
* Al Madina
* Al Mushrif Cooperative Society
* Al Safeer Group - supermarkets and hypermarkets
* Alam HyperMarket
* Alam SuperMarket
* [[Auchan]]
* Bani Yas Cooperative Society
* Bismi Hypermarket
* [[Carrefour]]
* Choithram Supermarket
* Emirates MarketI'm 
* Fathima Hypermarket
* Fathima Supermarket
* Fresh &amp; More Hypermarkets
* Fresh &amp; More Supermarkets
* [[Géant]]
* Grand Express Supermarkets 
* Grand Hypermarkets - Regency Group
* [[Panda Retail Company|HyperPanda]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.panda.com.sa Hyperpanda]&lt;/ref&gt;
* KM Trading Co
* Le Marché
* LIFCO Supermarket&lt;!-- (http://www.lifco.com)--&gt;
* [[Lulu Hypermarket]]
* [[Lulu Supermarket]]
* Safestway
* Shaheen Supermarket
* [[Spinneys]]
* Union Co-op
*[[Almanama Supermamarket]]

==[[Vietnam]]==
* [[Big C]], a part of [[Casino Guichard|Groupe-Casino]]
* Citimart (29 stores in 2016)
* Co.op Mart, the leading retailer in HCMC and in South Vietnam
* Fivimart (24 stores in 2016) 
* Intimex, based in the North
* Maximark, based in the South (Acquired by VinMart)
* VinMart 
* Parkson
* Auchan
* Lotte Mart
* minor chains: Savimart, Hapro Mart, Hanoi Starmart, Marko

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

{{Asia topic|List of supermarket chains in}}
{{Continent topic
|name   = Lists of supermarket chains by continent
|title  = [[List of supermarket chains|Lists of supermarket chains by continent]]
|prefix = List of supermarket chains in_
}}

[[Category:Lists of supermarkets|Asia]]
[[Category:Companies of Asia| ]]
[[Category:Retail companies of Asia| ]]
[[Category:Asia-related lists|Supermarket chains]]</text>
      <sha1>i7yi8aexabw6vcax8v7ac0i9bjc77tv</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Martin's Battery</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39012939</id>
    <revision>
      <id>759611774</id>
      <parentid>744560106</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-01-12T05:17:51Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>JJMC89 bot</username>
        <id>27446209</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Migrate {{Infobox military installation}} coordinates parameters to {{Coord}}, see [[Wikipedia:Coordinates in infoboxes]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1680">{{Infobox military structure
|name = Martin's Battery
|native_name =  
|partof = [[Fortifications of Gibraltar]] 
|location =[[Gibraltar]] 
|image = 
|caption = 
|map_type = Gibraltar 
|map_size = 300 
|map_alt = 
|map_caption = Location in [[Gibraltar]] 
|type = [[Artillery Battery]] 
|coordinates = {{coord|36.12505|-5.34188|type:landmark_region:GI|display=inline}}
|code = 
|built =
|builder = 
|materials = 
|height = 
|used = 
|demolished = 
|condition = 
|ownership = [[Ministry of Defence (United Kingdom)|Ministry of Defence]] 
|open_to_public =  
|controlledby = 
|garrison = 
|current_commander = 
|commanders = 
|occupants = 
|battles = 
|events = 
}}
'''Martin's Battery''' was an [[artillery battery]] in the [[British Overseas Territories|British Overseas Territory]] of [[Gibraltar]].&lt;ref name="Fa2006"&gt;{{cite book|author=Fa &amp; Finlayson|title=The Fortifications of Gibraltar 1068-1945|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=BC5QBR0oB04C&amp;pg=PA31|accessdate=4 April 2013|year=2006|page=51|publisher=Osprey Publishing|isbn=978-1-84603-016-1}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Description==
During World War Two there were two 4 inch and two 4 inch Quick Firing guns at Martin's Battery on the west side of the [[Rock of Gibraltar]].&lt;ref name="Fa2006"/&gt; Presumably named for the drunken soldier who reportedly discovered [[Martin's Cave]] in 1821.&lt;ref name="Critic"&gt;{{cite work|title=The Critic: A Weekly Review of Literature, Fine Arts, and the Drama, Volume 1|page=272|date=21 February 1829|chapter=Sketch: St Martin's Cave|publisher=Critic Press|location=New York}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}


{{Fortifications of Gibraltar}}

[[Category:Batteries in Gibraltar]]

{{Gibraltar-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>0vieud9lemimmfg6z9e8v9jlkv83lwj</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Meatball</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>30876149</id>
    <revision>
      <id>871684503</id>
      <parentid>871684248</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-12-02T19:57:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>208.123.6.157</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* Europe */</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="23082">{{other uses}}
[[File:Soup with meatballs-01.jpg|thumb|''[[Hochzeitssuppe]]'', German traditional wedding soup with meatballs]]
[[File:I'm 51 and have never made my own meatballs. Till tonight. Had some good ground beef from the TRU Meat Store. (15795383467).jpg|thumb|Raw meatballs]]
[[File:Gehaktballetjes.jpg|thumb|Meatballs being cooked]]
A '''meatball''' is [[ground meat]] rolled into a small [[ball]], sometimes along with other ingredients, such as [[bread crumbs]], minced [[onion]], [[egg (food)|eggs]], [[butter]], and seasoning.&lt;ref name="Smithsonian"&gt;{{cite web | title = Is Spaghetti and Meatballs Italian? | first =Shaylyn | last = Esposito | publisher = Sithsonian.com | date =  6 June 2013 | url = http://www.smithsonianmag.com/arts-culture/is-spaghetti-and-meatballs-italian-94819690/?no-ist | accessdate = 14 April 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Meatballs are cooked by [[frying]], [[baking]], [[steaming]], or [[braising]] in sauce.

There are many types of meatballs using different types of [[meats]] and [[spices]]. The term is sometimes extended to meatless versions based on vegetables or fish; the latter are commonly known as [[fishball]]s.

== History ==

The [[Chinese cuisine|Chinese recipe]] "Four Joy Meatballs" (四喜丸子—''Sì xǐ wánzi'') is derived from [[Shandong cuisine]], which originated in the native cooking styles of [[Shandong]]. Its history dates back to the [[Qin dynasty]] (221 BC to 207 BC).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web| title = Lu Cuisine | publisher = A bite of China | url = https://sites.google.com/site/chinasbite/home/lu-cusine | accessdate = 14 April 2015 }}&lt;/ref&gt;{{Self-published source|date=September 2017}}

The [[Ancient Rome|ancient Roman]] cookbook ''[[Apicius]]'' included many meatball-type recipes.&lt;ref&gt;Sally Grainger, ''Cooking Apicius: Roman Recipes for Today'', Prospect Books, 2006, {{ISBN|1-903018-44-7}}, p. 17-18&lt;/ref&gt;

Early recipes included in some of the earliest known [[Arab cuisine|Arabic cookbooks]] generally feature seasoned lamb rolled into orange-sized balls and glazed with egg yolk and sometimes [[saffron]]. This method was taken to the West and is referred to as gilding. Many regional variations exist, notable among them the unusually large [[Tabriz#Cuisine|''kufteh Tabrizi'']], having an average diameter of {{convert|20|cm}}.&lt;ref&gt;[[The Oxford Companion to Food]], ''s.v.'' kofta&lt;/ref&gt; 

''[[Poume d'oranges]]'' is a gilded meatball dish from the [[Middle Ages]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book | last=Adamson | first=M.W. | title=Regional Cuisines of Medieval Europe: A Book of Essays | publisher=Taylor &amp; Francis | series=Garland Medieval Casebooks | year=2013 | isbn=978-1-135-30868-1 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=VelSAQAAQBAJ&amp;pg=PA27 | access-date=June 15, 2017 | page=27}}&lt;/ref&gt;

== Various cultures ==
Various recipes of meatballs can be found across Europe and Asia. From [[Iberia]] and [[Sweden]] to [[India]], there is a large variety of meatballs in the [[kofta]] family.&lt;ref&gt;[[Alan Davidson (food writer)|Alan Davidson]], ed., ''[[The Oxford Companion to Food]]'', ''s.v.'' kofta&lt;/ref&gt;

=== Europe ===
[[File:Tatarsko kufte.JPG|thumb|[[Bulgaria]]n big meatball, ''tatarsko kufte'']]
[[File:Frikadeller.jpg|thumb|A freshly made batch of Danish meatballs (''[[frikadeller]]'')]]
[[File:koettbullar stockholm2006.jpg|thumb|Meatballs served in Swedish and Finnish style with [[mashed potato]]es, [[Brown sauce (meat stock based)|brown sauce]], [[lingonberry jam]] and pickled cucumber]]
[[File:04848 Meatballs Klopsy, PL 2011.JPG|thumb|''Klopsy'' with potato purée from Poland]]
[[File:Inegöl köfte.jpg|thumb|[[İnegöl meatballs]] from Turkey.]]
*[[Albanian cuisine|Albanian]] fried meatballs (''qofte të fërguara'') include [[feta cheese]].
*[[Armenian cuisine|Armenian]] stewed meatballs/meatball and vegetable stew (''kufte rize'') is a classic dish often poured over rice for consumption.
*In [[Austria]], fried meatballs are called ''Fleischlaibchen'' or ''Fleischlaberl''.
*In [[Belgium]], meatballs are called ''ballekes'' or ''bouletten'' in [[Flanders]] and are usually made of a mixture of beef and pork with bread crumbs and sliced onions. Many other variations exist, including different kinds of meat and chopped vegetables.
*In [[Bosnian cuisine|Bosnian]], meatballs are called ''ćufte'' and are typically made from ground beef and served with mashed potatoes.
*In [[Bulgaria]], meatballs are called ''kyufte'' and are typically made from ground beef or pork, or a mix of the two. They can be shallow fried or grilled and often contain diced onions and soaked bread. They are a very popular dish.
*In [[Croatia]], meatballs are called polpete in the Dalmatian region or ćufte in the continental part. They are typically made with ground beef or a mixture of pork and beef and served with mashed potatoes or rice, often with tomato based sauce.
*[[Danish cuisine|Danish]] meatballs are known as ''[[frikadeller]]'' and are typically fried. They are usually made out of ground [[pork]], veal, onions, eggs, salt, and pepper; these are formed into balls and flattened somewhat, so they are [[Frying pan|pan]] ready. However, the Danish cuisine also includes other versions, such as "Boller i Karry" (meatballs in curry sauce, typically served with rice), and the smaller meatballs used in soup with "Melboller" (Danish dumplings).
*In [[Estonia]], meatballs are called ''lihapallid'' (literally "meatballs") and are similar to those of Finnish or Swedish cuisine.
*In [[Finnish cuisine]], meatballs are called ''lihapullat'' (literally "meatbuns"). They are made with ground beef or a mix of ground beef and pork, or even with ground reindeer meat, mixed with breadcrumbs soaked in milk or [[viili]], beef stock and finely chopped onions or alternatively, [[French onion soup]] readymix. They are seasoned with [[white pepper]] and [[salt]]. Meatballs are traditionally served with gravy, boiled potatoes (or mashed potatoes), [[lingonberry jam]], and sometimes [[pickled cucumber]].
*In [[Alsace]], [[France]], meatballs are known as ''Fleischkiechele''. They are made of beef, pork, onions, bacon, eggs, and bread. They are served plain or with cream sauce.&lt;ref&gt;Wikipedia in French&lt;/ref&gt;
*In [[Germany]], meatballs are mostly known as ''Frikadelle'', ''Fleischküchle'', ''Fleischpflanzerl'', ''Bulette'' or ''Klopse''. A very famous variant of meatballs are ''[[Königsberger Klopse]]'', which contain [[anchovy]] or salted [[herring]], and are eaten with [[Caper#Culinary uses|caper sauce]].
*In [[Greece]], fried meatballs are called ''keftédes'' (κεφτέδες) and usually include within the mix of bread, onions, parsley and mint leaf.&lt;ref name=CFVM&gt;{{cite web|title=Κεφτέδες|url=http://foodmuseum.cs.ucy.ac.cy/web/guest/parsintages/civitem/1682|website=foodmuseum.cs.ucy.ac.cy|publisher=Cyprus Food Virtual Museum|accessdate=30 November 2015|language=Greek}}&lt;/ref&gt; Stewed meatballs are called ''yuvarlákia'' (γιουβαρλάκια: from the [[Turkish language|Turkish]] word ''yuvarlak'', which means "round") and usually include small quantities of rice.
*In [[Hungary]], as well as territories from neighbouring countries where Hungarian is spoken, a meatball is called ''fasírt'' {{IPA-hu|ˈfɒʃiːrt|}} or ''fasírozott'' {{IPA-hu|ˈfɒʃiːrozott|}} probably coming from Austrian German ''faschierte Laibchen''. It is a mixture of minced pork meat, minced onions, garlic, paprika, salt and breadcrumbs, deep fried in oil or pork fat and eaten with potatoes or [[főzelék]]. Also, the ''májgombóc'' {{IPA-hu|ˈmaːjɡomboːt͡s|}} (liver dumpling) is popular in soups.
*In [[Italy]], meatballs (named ''polpette'' {{IPA-it|polˈpette|}}, sing. ''polpetta'') are generally eaten as a main course or in a soup. The main ingredients of an Italian meatball are beef and/or pork and sometimes poultry or sausage, salt, black pepper, chopped garlic, olive oil, Romano cheese, eggs, [[bread crumbs]], and parsley, mixed and rolled by hand to a golf ball size. In the [[Abruzzo]] region of Italy, especially in the [[Province of Teramo]], the meatballs are typically the size of marbles and are called ''polpettine'' {{IPA-it|polpetˈtiːne|}}.
*In the [[Netherlands]], meatballs are called ''gehaktbal'', and are often served with boiled potatoes and vegetables. They are usually made out of mixed beef and pork minced meat, eggs, onion and [[bread crumbs]].
*In [[Norway]], meatballs are called [[:nb:Kjøttboller]] (lit. "meat bowls"). ''Kjøttboller'' are often served with brown sauce, [[:nb:Kålstuing|kålstuing]], [[:nb:Tyttebær|tyttebær]] and potatoes. Kjøttkaker are similar to Kjøttboller, except by form. Kjøttboller are round, like the typical meatball, whereas Kjøttkaker or meat cakes are in a patty form, flattened out and a bit oval in shape.
*In [[Poland]], they are called ''pulpety'' (from the Italian name) or ''klopsy'' (singular ''pulpet''; ''klops'', from German ''Klopse''), and ''pulpeciki'' ("little ''pulpety''"), and are usually served cooked with a variety of sauces (such as tomato or a kind of gravy thickened with flour, as well as forest mushroom sauce) with potatoes, rice or all sorts of ''[[kasza]]''. ''Pulpety'' or ''klopsy'' are usually made from seasoned ground meat with onion and mixed with eggs and either breadcrumbs or wheat rolls soaked in milk or water. Fried ''pulpety'' are larger than typical cooked ones. They can be round or flat in shape. The latter, in many countries, would be considered a cross between a meatball and a hamburger. The fried variety is called ''mielony'' (short for ''kotlet mielony'', literally "minced cutlet"), and its mass-produced version (as well as the one served in bars, etc.) is the subject of many jokes and urban legends about what is used to produce it.
*In [[Portugal]], meatballs are called ''almôndegas'' {{IPA-pt|aɫˈmõdɨɣɐʃ|}}. These are usually served with tomato sauce and pasta.
*In [[Romania]] and [[Moldova]], meatballs are called ''[[chiftele]]'' or ''[[pârjoale]]'' and are usually deep fried and made with pork or poultry, moistened [[mashed potato]]es and spices. ''[[Chiftele]]'' are flat and round and contain more meat. A variant mixing rice inside the meatball is used for sour soup, making ''[[ciorbă de perişoare]]''.
*In [[Russia]], they are called kotlety ({{lang-rus|котлеты}}) in flat forms or tefteli ({{lang-rus|тефтели}}) in ball forms.  They can be made with chicken, pork, beef or fish.  Tefteli have rice, potatoes and other vegetables mixed in as well.  (Kotlety is only meat... with spice.) They can be served with a side of mashed potatoes or noodles, or in a sauce.
*In [[Slovenia]], they are called polpeti. They are typically made with ground beef or a mixture of pork and beef and served with mashed potatoes, with tomato based sauce.
*In [[Spain]] and [[Hispanic America]], meatballs are called ''albóndigas'', derived from the [[Arabic]] ''al-bunduq'' (meaning hazelnut, or, by extension, a small round object). ''Albóndigas'' are thought to have originated as a Berber or Arab dish imported to Spain during the period of [[Al-Andalus|Muslim rule]]. Spanish ''albóndigas'' can be served as an appetizer or main course, often in a tomato sauce. Mexican ''albóndigas'' are commonly served in a soup with a light broth and vegetables.
*In {{anchor|Swedish meatball}} [[Swedish cuisine|Sweden]], ''köttbullar'' {{IPA-sv|ˈɕœtːbɵlar|}} are even often referred to as "köttbullar"  Meatballs come in a few different types, all typically small, and the international influence is great, perhaps the greatest from Sweden and Spain. They are usually eaten with [[potato]]es or [[pasta]]. Some common additions are various vegetables, ketchup, various spices, etc. are made with ground beef or a mix of ground beef, pork and sometimes [[veal]] or [[venison]], sometimes including breadcrumbs soaked in milk, finely chopped (fried) onions, some broth and often including cream. They are seasoned with [[white pepper]] or [[allspice]] and [[salt]].&lt;ref name="SE"&gt;Widenfelt, Sam ''Swedish Food'', Gothenburg, Sweden Esselte 1956.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=meatball&gt;{{cite news |title=Köttbullar |url=https://sweden.se/culture-traditions/classic-swedish-food-meatballs/ |work=Sweden.se |date=January 1, 2018 }}&lt;/ref&gt; Swedish meatballs are traditionally served with gravy, boiled potatoes, [[lingonberry jam]], and sometimes [[pickled cucumber]].&lt;ref name="SE" /&gt; Traditionally, they are small, around {{convert|2-3|cm|in}} in diameter although larger meatballs are often served at restaurants.&lt;ref&gt;Herbst, Sharon Tyler ''Food Lover's Companion'' Hauppauge, New York: Barron's Educational Series, Inc. 1990.&lt;/ref&gt; In 2018 a Swedish twitter account claimed that what we know as Swedish meatballs are based on a Turkish recipe.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/may/03/my-whole-life-has-been-a-lie-sweden-admits-meatballs-are-turkish |title='My whole life has been a lie': Sweden admits meatballs are Turkish |first= Jon |last= Henley | publisher=[[TheGuardian.com]]|date= 3 May 2018 |accessdate=4 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt; This statement has later been debunked by Swedish ethnologists.&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url=https://www.svd.se/forskare-sagar-varldsnyhet-om-kottbullar-fabricerat |title='Forskare sågar världsnyhet om köttbullar: ”Fabricerat”'| publisher=[[svd.se]]|date= 3 May 2018 |accessdate=4 May 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*In the [[United Kingdom]], [[faggot (food)|faggots]] are a type of spicy [[pork]] meatball. A faggot is traditionally made from pig's heart, liver and fatty belly meat or bacon minced together, with herbs added for flavoring, and sometimes bread crumbs.

=== Americas ===
[[File:Meatball pizza.jpg|thumb|upright|A [[meatball pizza]]]]
[[File:Albondigas en Chipotle.jpg|thumbnail|[[Mexican cuisine|Mexican]] albóndigas al chipotle]]
Most meatball recipes found in Americas are derived from European cuisine influences, notably Italian, Iberian (Portuguese-Spanish), and Nordic (Swedish-Finnish) cuisines.
*In [[Brazil]], meatballs are called ''almôndegas'', derived from  [[Italy|Italian]] influences. These are usually served with tomato sauce and pasta.
*In the [[Canada|Canadian]] province of [[Quebec]], meatballs are the main component of a traditional dish called ''ragoût de boulettes'' (meatballs stew). The meatballs are made with ground pork, onions, spices like cinnamon, cloves and nutmeg and are simmered in a gravy that's thickened with toasted flour. The dish is normally served with boiled or mashed potatoes and pickled beets. It is so popular that a factory-processed version of the dish is available canned in most supermarkets throughout the province.
*In [[Mexico]], ''albóndigas'' are commonly served with a light broth and vegetables, or with a mild chipotle sauce.
*In the [[United States]], meatballs are commonly derived from European cuisine influence. Usually, they are served with [[spaghetti]], on [[pizza]], or on a [[submarine sandwich|sub]], as in [[spaghetti and meatballs]], [[meatball pizza]], and [[meatball sandwich]]. In the southern United States, venison or beef is also often mixed with spices and baked into large meatballs that can be served as an entree. Another variation, called "porcupine meatballs" are basic meatballs often with rice in them.

=== Middle East and South Asia ===
{{Main article|Kofta}}
[[File:Koofteh tabrizi.jpg|thumb|''Kofta'' (''Kufteh'' [[Tabriz]]i)]]
''Kofta'' is a type of meatball or [[dumpling]] that is widely distributed in [[Middle East]]ern, [[South Asian]], [[Mediterranean]] and Balkan (Central and Eastern Europe) cuisines. The word ''kofta'' is derived from [[Persian language|Persian]] ''kūfta'': In Persian, کوفتن (kuftan) means "to beat" or "to grind" or ''meatball''.&lt;ref&gt;Alan S. Kaye, "Persian loanwords in English", ''English Today'' '''20''':20-24 (2004), {{DOI|10.1017/S0266078404004043}}.&lt;/ref&gt; In the simplest form, koftas consist of balls or fingers of minced or [[ground meat]] – usually [[beef]] or [[Lamb and mutton|lamb]] – mixed with spices and/or onions and other ingredients. The vegetarian variety is popular in India. They can be grilled, fried, steamed, poached, baked or marinated, and may be served with a rich spicy sauce.

*In [[Afghanistan]], meatballs are used as a traditional dish with homemade soups or are made with a tomato-based sauce that may include some plum seeds to increase tartness and is served with bread or rice which is called ''Kofta-Chelou''. Nowadays meatballs are also grilled on top of [[pizza]].
*In [[Iran]], several types of meatballs are consumed. If they are cooked in a stew, they are called ''kufteh.'' If they are fried (typically small meatballs), they are called ''kal-e gonjeshki'' (literally "[[sparrow]]'s head"). Both types are consumed with either bread or rice. Typically, herbs are added, and for ''kufteh'', usually the meatball is filled with hard boiled eggs or dried fruits. There are several (at least 10) types; the most famous is "kufteh tabrizi", traditionally from [[Tabriz]] in northwestern Iran.
*In [[Israel]], meatballs are called ktzitzot basar ({{lang-he|קציצות בשר}}), or sometimes simply ktzitzot ({{lang-he|קציצות}}). Their exact ingredients and preparation vary widely, due to the influence of Jewish immigration from different regions. They are typically made of spiced ground beef, though turkey and chicken versions are also available, and in their common form, they are shaped as slightly flattened balls, pan fried and then cooked in tomato sauce or broth. Other variations also exist, including the [[Gondi (dumpling)|gondi]], which were brought by the [[Persian Jews]], the albondigas of the [[Sephardic cuisine]], and the kufta that is customary with some [[Mizrahi Jews]].
*In [[Pakistan]] and [[India]], meatballs are called ''koftas''. Pakistani &amp; Indian meatballs are normally cooked in a spicy curry and sometimes with whole pre-boiled eggs. In Pakistan they are cooked in a gravy called ''chorba.'' Sometimes the eggs are encased in a layer of the spicy kofta meat so that the final product resembles an Indian [[Scotch egg]]. These kofta dishes are very popular with Indian diaspora and are widely available from many Indian restaurants.
*In [[Syria]], meatballs are prepared in numerous ways. They are grilled on charcoal with or without eggplants or cooked in a stew with potato, onion and tomato sauce with a side of rice which is called Dawood Pasha. 
*In [[Turkish cuisine|Turkey]], meatballs are called [[köfte]] and are extremely popular, there are many different versions with a variety of shapes – not necessarily round. Meatballs in Turkey are usually made with ground lamb or a mix of ground beef and lamb. Some of the most popular ones are [[İnegöl köfte]], [[İzmir köfte]], [[Tire meatballs|Tire köfte]], [[şiş köfte]], [[kadınbudu köfte]], [[sulu köfte]], and [[Akçaabat meatballs|Akçaabat köftesi]].
*In [[West Bengal]] state of India and [[Bangladesh]], koftas are made with prawns, fish, green bananas, and cabbage, as well as minced goat meat.

=== East and Southeast Asia ===
[[File:Chinese meatballs 2.jpg|thumb|A variety of Chinese meatballs and [[fishball]]s]]
*[[Chinese cuisine|Chinese]] meatballs (''wanzi'') are typically made of pork and can be steamed, boiled or deep fried, sometimes with the addition of [[soy sauce]]. Large meatballs, called [[lion's head (food)|lion's heads]], can range in size from about {{convert|5-10|cm|in|abbr=on}} in diameter. Smaller varieties, called [[pork ball]]s, are used in soups. A [[Cantonese cuisine|Cantonese]] variant, the [[steamed meatball]], is made of beef and served as a [[dim sum]] dish. Fish and seafood can also used to create different flavors and textures, and vegetarian alternatives to meatballs are served during festivals. In northern China, meatballs made from minced meat and flour, sometimes with the addition of [[lotus root]] or [[water chestnut]] for texture, are deep-fried and served in a [[vinegar]]-based sweet and sour sauce, or in a light broth with chopped [[coriander]].
[[File:Bakso.jpg|thumb|Indonesian ''[[bakso]]'' noodle soup]]
*[[Indonesia]]n meatballs are called ''[[bakso]]'' which are usually served in a bowl, served in broth soup, with noodles, rice vermicelli, bean curd (tofu), hard-boiled egg, ''siomay''/ steamed meat dumpling, and fried wonton. They have a consistent homogeneous texture. ''Bakso'' can be found in major Indonesian cities and towns, however, the most popular are ''bakso Solo'' and ''bakso Malang'' (named after the city of origin). In Malang, ''bakso bakar'' (roasted ''bakso'') is also popular. As most Indonesians are Muslim, generally it is made from beef or sometimes chicken.
*In [[Japanese cuisine]], a popular variant of meatballs is ''[[tsukune]]'', minced chicken meatballs on a skewer. The [[Japan]]ese [[hamburger]] steak, ''hanbāgu'', is typically made of ground beef, milk-soaked [[panko]] (bread crumbs) and minced, sauteed onions. They are typically eaten with a sauce made from ketchup and [[Worcestershire sauce]]. Chinese style meatballs are also popular.
*In the [[Philippines]], meatballs are called ''almondigas'' or ''bola-bola'' and are usually served in a ''[[misua]]'' noodle soup with toasted garlic, squash and pork [[Pork rind|cracklings]]. ''Almondigas'' are derived from Hispanic influence on Filipino cuisine and ultimately derived from Moorish influence. Bola-bolas are also stewed or pan-fried until golden brown. Bola-bola is also used as a filling for [[siopao]], the local variant of [[baozi]].
*In [[Vietnam]], meatballs (''thịt viên'' hay ''mọc'', ''bò viên'', ''cá viên'') can be used as an ingredient in ''[[phở]]'' and ''[[hủ tiếu]]''. It is also common to cook meatballs in tomato sauce, and finely chopped spring onion and peppers are added before serving. In ''[[bún chả]]'' (a specialty Vietnamese rice noodle), meatballs are grilled to be ''chả'' and served with ''bún'' (rice noodles) and dipping sauce (based on fish sauce seasoned with rice vinegar, sugar, garlic, and chili). ''Xíu Mại'' is a pork meatball in a tomato sauce often served with a baguette.

&lt;gallery class="center" caption="" widths="220px" heights="160px"&gt;
File:Seseri and Tsukune.jpg|Japanese ''Seseri'' (left) and {{Nihongo|[[Tsukune]]|つくね}} (right)
File:Miswajf7582.JPG|Bola-bola with [[misua]] from the [[Philippines]]
File:Bun Moc Ha Noi.jpg|A bowl of ''[[Bún mọc]]'' in [[Vietnam]], ''bún'' is rice vermicelli, while ''mọc'' means pork-ball
&lt;/gallery&gt;

== See also ==
{{portal|Food}}
* [[Frikandel]], a Belgian and Dutch snack, similar in texture to meatballs, but shaped more like a hot dog or sausage than a ball 
* [[List of meatball dishes]]
* [[Rissole]]

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

== External links ==
*{{Commons category inline|Meatballs}}
*{{Wikibooks-inline|Cookbook:Meatballs}}
{{Meat|state=expanded}}
{{Lists of prepared foods}}

[[Category:Meatballs| ]]
[[Category:World cuisine]]
[[Category:Meat dishes]]
[[Category:Types of food]]
[[Category:National dishes]]</text>
      <sha1>dnooiqdnxixnhi5p2hu16r6mutu1rqy</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Military occupations of Luxembourg</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5986548</id>
    <revision>
      <id>692953218</id>
      <parentid>687226064</parentid>
      <timestamp>2015-11-29T13:08:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BattyBot</username>
        <id>15996738</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>removed [[Template:Multiple issues]] &amp; [[WP:AWB/GF|general fixes]] using [[Project:AWB|AWB]] (11749)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1177">{{unreferenced|date=October 2008}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2012}}

There have been several '''military occupations of Luxembourg''' through the ages.  Amongst them have been:

* The French occupation of Luxembourg during the [[Franco-Spanish War (1635)|Franco-Spanish War]].  This led to the [[first Partition of Luxembourg]], with the loss of [[Thionville]], under the [[Treaty of the Pyrenees]].
* The French occupation of Luxembourg before and during the [[War of the Grand Alliance]] (1684–1697).
* The [[Kingdom of Prussia|Prussian]] occupation of Luxembourg from 1815 until 1867.  Under the 1815 [[Treaty of Paris (1815)|Treaty of Paris]], which ended the [[Napoleonic Wars]], the fortress of [[Luxembourg City]] came under the control of the [[German Confederation]].  Thus, Luxembourg was occupied by Prussian soldiers until the 1867 [[Treaty of London, 1867|Treaty of London]] ordered an end to the occupation and the demolition of the fortifications.
* The [[German occupation of Luxembourg in World War I]] (1914–1918).
* The [[German occupation of Luxembourg in World War II]] (1940–1944).

[[Category:Military history of Luxembourg]]


{{Luxembourg-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>7qnjdkixrfqng64bicuyqizq58tcxc5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Movement for Development and Solidarity</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>2718084</id>
    <revision>
      <id>750054695</id>
      <parentid>459368387</parentid>
      <timestamp>2016-11-17T16:13:50Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Everyking</username>
        <id>44020</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="781">{{Unreferenced stub|auto=yes|date=December 2009}}
{{Politics of Benin}}
The '''Movement for Development and Solidarity''' ({{Lang-fr|Mouvement pour le Développement et la Solidarité}}) is a [[political party]] in [[Benin]]. In the [[legislative]] [[elections in Benin|elections]] held on 30 March 2003, the party was a member of the Presidential Movement, the alliance of supporters of [[Mathieu Kérékou]], who had won the 2001 presidential elections, and won one out of 83 seats. It helped form the coalition [[Union Makes the Nation]], the main opposition to President [[Yayi Boni]]'s government following the 2011 elections.

{{Political parties in Benin}}
{{DEFAULTSORT:Movement For Development And Solidarity}}
[[Category:Political parties in Benin]]

{{Benin-party-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>5xk5lrsfdwhunk8chkyr95rz971wuur</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Munkácsi</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>22972299</id>
    <revision>
      <id>864568800</id>
      <parentid>850238266</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-18T02:23:04Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>74.64.51.168</ip>
      </contributor>
      <comment>added Erno Munkacsi</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="415">'''Munkácsi, Munkácsy:''' means "from [[Mukachevo|Munkács]]" (Mukachevo):

{{surname|Munkácsi, [[Munkacsi]], [[Munkácsy]], [[Munkacsy]]}}
* [[Mihály Munkácsy]] (1844–1900), Hungarian painter
* [[Martin Munkácsi]] (1896–1963), Hungarian-American photographer
* [[Erno Munkacsi]] (1896-1950), Hungarian jurist and writer

{{DEFAULTSORT:Munkacsi}}
[[Category:Hungarian-language surnames]]

{{Hungary-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>4eerausk5kvzbdc5kju2z6no2cip28c</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>NBA League Pass</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>9512162</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869678080</id>
      <parentid>869677384</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-20T00:24:47Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Msw1002</username>
        <id>3759712</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>duplicate</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="12825">[[File:NBA League Pass (2010 Logo).jpg|right|thumb|NBA League Pass logo]]

The '''NBA League Pass''' is a [[sports television]] service that features all [[National Basketball Association]] games. The service is operated by [[Turner Broadcasting System]] on behalf of the NBA. It was made available prior to the start of the 1995-1996 NBA season. It is available to viewers in the [[United States]] and as an international package for all other countries. The pricing structure and services on offer are different, depending on where the viewer is located. The 2013-14 season was the 20th year of League Pass.&lt;ref name="auto"&gt;Whitaker, Lang. blogs.nba.com "[http://allball.blogs.nba.com/2013/10/02/new-nba-league-pass-features-announced/ New NBA League Pass Features Announced]". Accessed 5th October 2013&lt;/ref&gt; Full League Pass access for the 2014-15 season was priced at $199 for US customers, for comparison the premium service was £169.99 for UK viewers (these prices are for access to the full season prior to the first game and before any discounts, in previous seasons prices have dropped as the season moves closer towards the play-offs).&lt;ref&gt;{{Cite web|url = http://watch.nba.com/nba/subscribe|title = Subscription - NBA Game Time|date = 8 August 2014|accessdate = 8 August 2014|website = nba,com|publisher = |last = |first = }}&lt;/ref&gt;

==United States League Pass==

'''NBA League Pass''' is an [[out-of-market sports package]] that allows its subscribers to watch up to 40 out-of-market [[National Basketball Association]] games a week. Videos of the games come from local stations and [[regional sports networks]].

League Pass comes in three varieties in the United States: '''NBA League Pass TV''', which plays the games through a cable or satellite TV provider; '''NBA League Pass Broadband''', which uses [[broadband|highspeed]] [[Internet]] connection to stream videos to a computer; and '''NBA League Pass Mobile''', which is for mobile devices.

Customers outside the United States can sign up for '''NBA International League Pass'''.

===Blackout restrictions===
{{see also|Blackout_(broadcasting)#NBA_blackout_policy|l1=NBA blackout policy}}

If a local team is playing and the game is televised in the home market, the associated feed on League Pass is blacked out and unavailable for viewing.

Per the NBA.com website: 
“Games will also be blacked out when they are appearing on national television. This applies to games being televised on ABC, ESPN, TNT and NBA TV. You may view these games simply by switching to the designated channel.” 

In Canada, Bulls games on [[WGN-TV]] are not blacked out.

===NBA League Pass availability in the US===
NBA League Pass TV is available with these cable, satellite and streaming providers in the United States:

* ''United States'':
** [[AT&amp;T U-verse]]
** [[DIRECTV]]
** [[Dish Network]]
** [[fuboTV]]
** [[In Demand|iN DEMAND Team]]
*** [[Adams Cable]]
*** [[Blue Ridge Communications]]
*** [[Cablevision]] ([[Optimum TV]])
*** [[Comcast]] ([[Xfinity]])
*** [[Cox Communications]]
*** [[Frontier Communications]]
*** [[RCN Corporation|RCN]]
*** [[Time Warner Cable]]
*** [[Verizon FiOS]]
** [[Sling TV]]


Most providers who offer subscriptions to League Pass TV also include [[NBA TV]] and a companion League Pass Broadband subscription. It is also included in some cable subscriptions.

==NBA International League Pass==

NBA International League Pass is available to users living outside the United States, and differs from the US version of the product in its content, packaging, and pricing. While both the US and international products feature games available for live or on-demand viewing, the major distinction between the two products is that International League Pass provides access to all NBA games played during the regular season, All Star Weekend, Playoffs, and Finals, free from blackout restrictions. The single exception to this offering is in Canada, where games televised nationally are blacked out live and are available for on-demand viewing only after the game is completed.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.watch.nba.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=704416&amp;SPID=118008&amp;DB_OEM_ID=29500&amp;ATCLID=205736022|title=NBAILP Support|accessdate=23 March 2015|deadurl=yes|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20141101203056/http://support.watch.nba.com/ViewArticle.dbml?SPSID=704416&amp;SPID=118008&amp;DB_OEM_ID=29500&amp;ATCLID=205736022|archivedate=1 November 2014|df=}}&lt;/ref&gt; International League Pass also provides access to games from previous seasons through archives.&lt;ref&gt;watch.NBA.com - [http://watch.nba.com/nba/subscribe Subscription: NBA GAME TIME]. Accessed March 23, 2015 (note: accessed from an Australian IP. The page will differ by region).&lt;/ref&gt;

International users have the option of subscribing to one of two packages: NBA League Pass and NBA League Pass Premium. Subscribers to both packages are able to watch all NBA games from the regular season, All Star Weekend, Playoffs, and Finals live or on-demand from a variety of devices, including desktop computers, iPhones, iPads, Android phones and tablets, and TV-connected devices like Apple TV, Google Chromecast, Xbox and PlayStation consoles (the platforms supported differ by country).&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://support.watch.nba.com/SportSelect.dbml?&amp;DB_OEM_ID=29500&amp;SPID=118008&amp;SPSID=704415|title=NBAILP Support|accessdate=23 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; Subscribers to both packages are also able to use in-game features including multi-game viewing, stats windows, and a condensed game feature that only includes scoring and highlight plays. Subscribers to the Premium package gain additional features, including access to a live stream of NBA TV International, additional NBA VOD content in the "Video Vault" including TNT's Overtime studio show, Spanish language feeds for certain games, and the option to choose between the broadcasts of the home or away team.

Beginning in the 2014-15 season, NBA International League Pass introduced continuous game feeds for selected games and all home feeds, which replaced the game break videos (highlights, commercials, etc.) shown during play breaks with highlight clips, live footage of in-arena activities including dance team performances, half-time entertainment, fans in the crowd, and interviews or features produced by the local broadcaster. Included with this footage is a statistics feed providing stats updates from around the league.

===International Packages and Promotions===

In addition to the standard and Premium packages, users also have the option to purchase a stand-alone streaming subscription to NBA TV International, which broadcasts games, studio shows, press conferences, and other basketball content.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url= http://watch.nba.com/nba/live|title=NBA TV Live|accessdate=23 March 2015}}&lt;/ref&gt; In past seasons, International League Pass has also offered sampling packages that provide stand-alone access to Christmas Day games and All Star Weekend events. The last several weeks of the regular season have also been made available in a separate "Race to the Playoffs" package.

During the off-season, both International League Pass and International League Pass Premium subscribers have live and on-demand access to Summer League games and certain games or scrimmages played by the USA Basketball team in preparation for or during the [[Olympics]] and the [[FIBA World Cup]] tournament, in addition to continued access to past NBA regular seasons in archives. This summer content has also been sold as a stand-alone package.

During the 2014-15 season, International League Pass offered a free trial of the product during the first week of the regular season and at the halfway point of the regular season, and other promotional free previews have been made available at various points in the season.

===NBA League Pass availability outside the US===

Note: Subscriptions can be bought in most regions via the Internet to be streamed to applications on various devices or to a browser (see above for list). Some of the following services include League Pass, either fully or partially, but they are not required to view League Pass.
 
*''Brazil''
**[[SKY Brasil]]
* ''Canada'':
** [[Bell TV]]
** [[Shaw Direct]]
** [[Cogeco|Cogeco Cable]]
** [[EastLink (company)|EastLink Cable]]
** [[Rogers Cable]]
*''Mexico and Central America'':
** [[SKY México]]
*''Philippines'':
** [[Cablelink]], [[Globe Telecom|Globe]], [[Sky Cable]], and [[PLDT]]/[[Smart Communications|Smart]]
*''South America and Caribbean (except Brazil)'':
** [[DirecTV]]
*''United Kingdom'':
** [[BT Sport]]

==Applications, Features and Platforms supported==

Apps are currently available for:

* Smart TVs (depends on manufacturer/model)
* [[Apple TV]]
* [[Xbox 360]]
* Android devices
* [[iOS]] devices
* [[Windows Phone]]
* [[Roku]]
* [[Amazon Kindle Fire]]
* [[PlayStation 4]]&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.playstation.com/en-us/explore/playstationnetwork/entertainment/nba-gametime/ NBA Game Time], blog.playstation.com&lt;/ref&gt;

For the 2013-14 season, League Pass's apps were updated with the ability to select home and away feeds on all games, and video-on-demand access for games broadcast nationally.&lt;ref name="auto"/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Pollakoff, Brett. "[http://probasketballtalk.nbcsports.com/2013/10/02/nba-makes-new-league-pass-features-official-all-nationally-televised-games-now-archived/ NBA makes new League Pass features official, all nationally televised games now archived]". ''Pro Basketball Talk'' (NBC Sports). Accessed October 5, 2013&lt;/ref&gt;

For the 2016-17 season, a new feature known as "Mobile View" was introduced, which allows viewers to access a special feed of the home telecast with optimizations for viewing on smartphones. The Mobile View feed will utilize a new dedicated camera angle with a tighter, zoomed-in shot of gameplay. The league will provide a camera and a producer for the feature at each regular-season game, who will have access to the special camera and all others in use for the production.&lt;ref name="svg-mobileview"&gt;{{cite web|title=NBA Installs Extra Camera, Adds Dedicated Producer to Each Game for New ‘NBA Mobile View’ Feature|url=http://www.sportsvideo.org/2016/10/24/nba-installs-extra-camera-adds-dedicated-producer-to-every-game-for-new-nba-mobile-view-streaming-feature/|website=Sports Video Group|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name="techcrunch-mobilefriendly"&gt;{{cite web|title=NBA League Pass is launching Mobile View to make it more enjoyable to watch games on your phone|url=https://techcrunch.com/2016/10/24/nba-league-pass-is-launching-mobile-view-to-make-it-more-enjoyable-to-watch-games-on-your-phone/|website=TechCrunch|publisher=AOL|accessdate=25 October 2016}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==WNBA Season Pass==
[[File:WNBA Season Pass.jpg|right|thumb|200px|Former WNBA Season Pass logo]]
From 1999 to 2001, NBA League Pass had a companion service called '''WNBA Season Pass''' which showed out-of-market games of the [[Women's National Basketball Association]]. The WNBA has discontinued this service; today, all national broadcasts are on [[ESPN on ABC|ABC]], [[ESPN2]], or [[NBA TV]]. However, they now offer the '''WNBA Broadband Season Pass''', a web program that allows subscribers to watch every game live for each season.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|url=http://www.wnba.com/broadband/bsp_info.html|title=WNBA.com: WNBA Broadband Season Pass Info|author=|date=|website=www.wnba.com|accessdate=8 April 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Summer League Pass==

The [[2013 NBA Summer League]] was available as a streaming subscription service with an app' for [[IOS]] and [[Android (operating system)|Android]] devices in the 2013 off-season. Priced at $14.99, all 61 games&lt;ref&gt;nba.com "[http://www.nba.com/bucks/news/john-henson-named-2013-all-nba-summer-league-team John Henson Named to 2013 All-NBA Summer League Team]". Accessed: October 2nd 2013.&lt;/ref&gt; in both the [[Orlando Pro Summer League]] and the [[2013 NBA Summer League|Las Vegas League]] were included in the price.&lt;ref&gt;NBA.com. "[http://www.nba.com/2013/news/07/01/nba-tv-summer-league-schedule-release-2013/index.html NBA TV to televise 62 Summer League games, title game]". Accessed; October 2nd, 2013.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[NFL Sunday Ticket]]
* [[MLS Direct Kick]]
* [[MLB Extra Innings]]
* [[NHL Center Ice]]
* [[NASCAR Hot Pass]]
*[[National Basketball Association criticisms and controversies]]

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*[http://www.nba.com/leaguepass/index.html Official site]

{{Sports television in the United States}}
{{U.S. premium television services}}
{{Canadian premium television services (PPV)}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Nba League Pass}}
[[Category:Satellite television]]
[[Category:National Basketball Association on television]]
[[Category:Out-of-market sports packages]]
[[Category:Television channels and stations established in 1995]]</text>
      <sha1>t880spkr3g211gki5623fstqn1xehv3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Nanjing Television Broadcast Group</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>6703566</id>
    <revision>
      <id>800040693</id>
      <parentid>674391870</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-09-11T07:04:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>WereSpielChequers</username>
        <id>4071608</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>/* top */[[WP:AWB/T|Typo fixing]], replaced: the  is  →  is the using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="701">'''Nanjing Broadcast Television Station''', is a [[television network]] in the [[Nanjing, China]] area.  It is the owner of the [[Nanjing Broadcasting Network]] and [[Nanjing Radio]].

==External links==
*[http://www.njbg.com.cn/ Official Website]
*[http://babelfish.altavista.com/babelfish/trurl_load?lp=zh_en&amp;url=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.njbg.com.cn%2F Official Website (translated to English with Babelfish)]
*[http://babelfish.altavista.com/babelfish/trurl_pagecontent?lp=zh_en&amp;trurl=http%3a%2f%2fwww.njbg.com.cn%2ftopic%2f06sjjdh%2findex.htm Nanjing Broadcasting Network (translated to English with Babelfish)]

[[Category:Chinese television networks]]
[[Category:Media in Nanjing]]


{{PRChina-tv-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>81nd4aq3n9m6k87geuwub3b0w4zuluu</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>OSN Movies</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48549909</id>
    <revision>
      <id>855701234</id>
      <parentid>850588741</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-20T06:50:14Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Roses23</username>
        <id>31118927</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2553">{{Infobox TV channel
| name              = OSN Movies
| logosize          = 250px
| logofile          = OSN Movies 2013.jpg
| logoalt           = 
| launch            = 1996
| replaced names    = 
| share             = 
| share as of       = 
| share source      = 
| owner             = [[OSN|OSN Network]]
| country          =  {{flag|UAE}}, [[Dubai]]
| sister names      = [[OSN News]]&lt;br/&gt;[[OSN Sports]]
| web               = [http://www.osn.com osn.com]
| sat serv 1        = [[OSN]] {{small|(MENA)}}
| sat chan 1        = {{ubl|Channel 1 (OSN Movies First, HD)|Channel 2 (OSN Movies First +2, HD)|Channel 4 (OSN Movies Action, HD)|Channel 5 (OSN Movies Action +2, HD)|Channel 6 (OSN Movies, HD)|Channel 7 (OSN Movies +2, SD)|Channel 9 (OSN Movies Thriller, HD)|Channel 10 (OSN Movies Thriller +2, SD)|Channel 13 (OSN Movies Festival, HD)|Channel 15 (OSN Movies Kids, HD)|Channel 16 (OSN Movies Disney, HD)|Channel 17 (OSN Movies Comedy, HD)|Channel 31 (OSN Movies Box Office 1, HD)|Channel 32 (OSN Movies Box Office 2, HD)|Channel 33 (OSN Movies Box Office 3, HD)}}
| cable serv 1      = 
| cable chan 1      = 
| cable serv 2      = 
| cable chan 2      = 
| adsl serv 1       = 
| adsl chan 1       = 
| adsl serv 2       = 
| adsl chan 2       = 
| online serv 1     = 
| online chan 1     = 
| online serv 2     = 
| online chan 2     = 
| online serv 3     = 
| online chan 3     = 
|}}

'''OSN Movies''' is a series of [[Pay television|premium]] movie channels provided by [[OSN]] for the [[MENA]] market. The channels include content such as the latest Hollywood films of various genres from major companies such as [[Walt Disney Pictures|Disney]], [[20th Century Fox]], [[Warner Bros.]], [[Sony Pictures|Sony Pictures Entertainment]], [[Universal Pictures]], [[Metro-Goldwyn-Mayer|MGM]], and [[DreamWorks Animation]].

==List of OSN Movie channels==
*OSN Movies HD 
*OSN Movies +2
*OSN Movies Action HD
*OSN Movies Action+2 HD
*OSN Movies Thriller HD
*OSN Movies Thriller+2
*OSN Movies First HD
*OSN Movies Pop Up HD Marvel
*OSN Movies Festival HD
*OSN Movies Kids HD
*OSN Movies Comedy HD
*OSN Movies Disney HD
*OSN Movies Box Office 1 HD ([[Pay-per-view|PPV]])
*OSN Movies Box Office 2 HD ([[Pay-per-view|PPV]])
*OSN Movies Box Office 3 HD ([[Pay-per-view|PPV]])

==External links==
* [http://www.osn.com/en-sa/explore/channels/opr/osn-movies-hd OSN Movies HD]

==See also==
*[[OSN]]
*[[OSN Sports]]
*[[OSN News]]
*[[OSN FIRST]]

{{Asia-tv-stub}}
{{tv-station-stub}}

[[Category:Television stations in Dubai]]
[[Category:Pay television]]</text>
      <sha1>31nlflgkuobkr9ymq2hxhit1djqfvvs</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Outline of Argentina</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>16278408</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868846238</id>
      <parentid>867251740</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-14T20:44:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Wbm1058</username>
        <id>14383484</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>sp.: [[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]], per [[MOS:CONSISTENCY]], proper names use the subject's own spelling (via [[WP:JWB]])</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="20634">&lt;!--... Attention:  THIS IS AN OUTLINE

        part of the set of 740+ outlines listed at
             [[Portal:Contents/Outlines]].

                 Wikipedia outlines are
              a special type of list article.
              They make up one of Wikipedia's
                content navigation systems

                See [[Wikipedia:Outlines]]
                      for more details.
                   Further improvements
              to this outline are on the way...--&gt;
{{See also|Index of Argentina-related articles}}
{{double image|right|Flag of Argentina.svg|196|Coat_of_arms_of_Argentina.svg|89|The [[Flag of Argentina]]|The [[Coat of arms of Argentina]]}}
[[File:Argentina (orthographic projection).svg|right|188px]]
[[Image:Argentinamap3.gif|thumb|An enlargeable map of the [[Argentine Republic]]]]

The following [[Outline (list)|outline]] is provided as an overview of, and introduction to Argentina:

'''[[Argentina]]''' &amp;ndash; country in [[South America]], the continent's second largest by land area, after [[Brazil]]. It is constituted as a [[Federalism|federation]] of 23 [[Provinces of Argentina|provinces]] and an [[autonomous city]], Buenos Aires. It is the [[List of countries and outlying territories by total area|eighth]]-largest country in the world by land area and the largest among [[Hispanophone|Spanish-speaking nations]].

{{TOC limit|limit=2}}

== General reference ==
[[image:Argentina-CIA WFB Map.png|thumb|An enlargeable basic map of [[Argentina]]]]
* [[International Phonetic Alphabet|Pronunciation]]: {{IPAc-en|audio=en-us-Argentina.ogg|ˌ|ɑr|dʒ|ən|ˈ|t|iː|n|ə}}
* Common English country name: [[Argentina]]
* Official English country name: The [[Argentine Republic]]
* Common [[endonym]](s): [[List of countries and capitals in native languages|Argentina]]
* Official endonym(s): [[List of official endonyms of present-day nations and states|República Argentina]]
* [[List of adjectival and demonymic forms of place names#Countries and nations|Adjectival]](s): [[Argentine (disambiguation)|Argentine]] &lt;!-- This disambiguation page is the only page on Wikipedia that specifically explains this term and its country adjectival contexts, and it does so excellently.  Please leave this link in place. --&gt;
* [[List of adjectival and demonymic forms of place names#Countries and nations|Demonym]](s):
* [[Etymology]]: [[Name of Argentina]]
* [[International rankings of Argentina]]
* [[ISO country codes]]: AR, ARG, 032
* [[ISO region codes]]: See [[ISO 3166-2:AR]]
* [[Internet]] [[country code top-level domain]]: [[.ar]]

== Geography of Argentina ==
[[Image:Argentina topo blank.jpg|thumb|An enlargeable topographic map of [[Argentina]].]]

[[Geography of Argentina]]
* Argentina is a: [[Country]]
* Location:
** [[Southern Hemisphere]]
** [[Western Hemisphere]]
*** [[Latin America]]
**** [[South America]]
***** [[Southern Cone]]
** [[Time zone]]:
*** [[Argentina Time]] - ([[UTC-03]]) - No DST
** [[Extreme points of Argentina]]
*** High:  [[Aconcagua]] {{convert|6960|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} – highest point outside of [[Asia]]
*** Low:  [[Laguna del Carbón]] {{convert|-105|m|ft|0|abbr=on}} – lowest point in the [[Western Hemisphere]] and the [[Southern Hemisphere]]
** Land boundaries:  9,861&amp;nbsp;km
::{{Flag|Chile}} 5,308 km
::{{Flag|Paraguay}} 1,880 km
::{{Flag|Brazil}} 1,261 km
::{{Flag|Bolivia}} 832 km
::{{Flag|Uruguay}} 580 km
:* Coastline:  4,989 km
* [[Population of Argentina]]: 40,677,348 people (2008 [[Approximation|estimate]]) - [[List of countries by population|30th most populous country]]
* [[Area of Argentina]]:  {{convert|2766890|km2|abbr=on}} - [[List of countries and outlying territories by total area|8th largest country]]
* [[:commons:Atlas of Argentina|Atlas of Argentina]]

=== Environment of Argentina ===
[[Image:Argentina Blue Marble.png|thumb|An enlargeable satellite image of the [[Argentina]]]]

[[Environment of Argentina]]
* [[Climate of Argentina]]
* [[Renewable energy in Argentina]]
* Geology of Argentina
** [[List of earthquakes in Argentina|Earthquakes in Argentina]]
* [[Protected areas of Argentina]]
** [[List of biosphere reserves in Argentina|Biosphere reserves in Argentina]]
** [[List of national parks of Argentina|National parks of Argentina]]
* [[Wildlife of Argentina]]
** [[Environment of Argentina#Flora|Flora of Argentina]]
** [[Environment of Argentina#Fauna|Fauna of Argentina]]
*** [[List of birds of Argentina|Birds of Argentina]]
*** [[List of mammals of Argentina|Mammals of Argentina]]

==== Natural geographic features of Argentina ====
* [[Glaciers of Argentina]]
* [[List of islands of Argentina|Islands of Argentina]]
* [[List of lakes in Argentina|Lakes of Argentina]]
* [[List of mountains of Argentina|Mountains of Argentina]]
** [[List of volcanoes in Argentina|Volcanoes in Argentina]]
* [[List of rivers of Argentina|Rivers of Argentina]]
* [[List of World Heritage Sites in the Americas#Argentina|World Heritage Sites in Argentina]]

=== Regions of Argentina ===

[[Regions of Argentina]]
The [[provinces of Argentina]] are often grouped into six geographical regions. From North to South and West to East, these are:
*'''[[Argentine Northwest]]''': [[Jujuy Province|Jujuy]], [[Salta Province|Salta]], [[Tucumán Province|Tucumán]], [[Catamarca Province|Catamarca]], [[La Rioja Province, Argentina|La Rioja]]
*'''[[Gran Chaco]]''': [[Formosa Province|Formosa]], [[Chaco Province|Chaco]], [[Santiago del Estero Province|Santiago del Estero]]
*'''[[Mesopotamia, Argentina|Mesopotamia]]''' (or '''Littoral'''): [[Misiones Province|Misiones]], [[Entre Ríos Province|Entre Ríos]], [[Corrientes Province|Corrientes]]
*'''[[Cuyo, Argentina|Cuyo]]''': [[San Juan Province, Argentina|San Juan]], [[Mendoza Province|Mendoza]], [[San Luis Province|San Luis]]
*'''[[Pampa]]s''': [[Córdoba Province, Argentina|Córdoba]], [[Santa Fe Province|Santa Fe]], [[La Pampa Province|La Pampa]], [[Buenos Aires Province|Buenos Aires]]
*'''[[Patagonia]]''': [[Río Negro Province|Rio Negro]], [[Neuquén Province|Neuquén]], [[Chubut Province|Chubut]], [[Santa Cruz Province, Argentina|Santa Cruz]], [[Tierra del Fuego Province, Argentina|Tierra del Fuego]]
* '''[[Argentine Antarctica]]'''

==== Administrative divisions of Argentina ====

=====Provinces=====

[[Provinces of Argentina]]
{| style="background:transparent;" cellspacing="0" cellpadding="0"
|- valign="top"
|style="width:370px; font-size:95%;"|
*'''{{flag|Buenos Aires|name=Autonomous City of Buenos Aires}}'''{{smallsup|a}}
*'''{{flag|Buenos Aires Province}}'''
*'''{{flag|Catamarca}}''' 
*'''{{flag|Chaco}}'''
*'''{{flag|Chubut}}'''
*'''{{flag|Córdoba}}'''
*'''{{flag|Corrientes}}'''
*'''{{flag|Entre Ríos}}'''
*'''{{flag|Formosa}}'''
*'''{{flag|Jujuy}}'''
*'''{{flag|La Pampa}}'''
*'''{{flagcountry|La Rioja (Argentina)}}'''
*'''{{flag|Mendoza}}'''
*'''{{flag|Misiones}}'''
*'''{{flag|Neuquén}}'''
*'''{{flagcountry|Río Negro (Argentina)}}'''{{smallsup|b}}
*'''{{flag|Salta}}'''
*'''{{flag|San Juan}}'''
*'''{{flag|San Luis}}'''
*'''{{flag|Santa Cruz}}'''
*'''{{flag|Santa Fe}}'''
*'''{{flag|Santiago del Estero}}'''
*'''{{flag|Tierra del Fuego|name=Tierra del Fuego, Antártida e Islas del Atlántico Sur}}'''{{smallsup|c}}
*'''{{flag|Tucumán}}'''

&lt;br&gt;
{{smaller|&lt;sup&gt;'''a'''&lt;/sup&gt; Not a Province. '''''Autonomous City''''' and seat of [[Argentine Government|National Government]].&lt;br&gt;(Also known as [[Buenos Aires|Buenos Aires City]]).&lt;br/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;'''b'''&lt;/sup&gt; or [[Río Negro Province|Provincia del Río Negro]].&lt;br/&gt;&lt;sup&gt;'''c'''&lt;/sup&gt; Tierra del Fuego Province includes claims over [[Argentine Antarctica]], [[Falkland Islands sovereignty dispute|Falkland Islands]], and [[South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands sovereignty dispute|South Georgia and South Sandwich Islands]].}}
|
{{Argentina imagemap with province names|400}}
|}

===== Municipalities of Argentina =====
[[Image:Buenos Aires - Vista aérea - Puerto-Retiro-Av9Julio-2006.JPG|thumb|300px|[[Buenos Aires]], Argentina]]

[[Municipalities of Argentina]]
* [[List of cities in Argentina|Cities of Argentina]]
** [[Capital (political)|Capital]] of Argentina: [[Capital of Argentina|Buenos Aires]]

=== Demography of Argentina ===
{{main article|Demographics of Argentina|Ethnography of Argentina}}

== Government and politics of Argentina ==

[[Politics of Argentina]]
* [[Form of government]]: [[federation|federal]] [[presidential system|presidential]] [[representative democracy|representative democratic]] [[republic]]
* [[Capital (political)|Capital]] of Argentina: [[Capital of Argentina|Buenos Aires]]
* [[Elections in Argentina]]
** [[Primary elections in Argentina]]
* [[List of political parties in Argentina|Political parties in Argentina]]
* [[Taxation in Argentina]]

=== Branches of the government of Argentina ===

[[Government of Argentina]]
==== Executive branch of the government of Argentina ====
[[File:Casa rosada 2.JPG|thumb|210px|The [[Casa Rosada]], seat of the Argentine Executive Branch of Government]]
* [[Head of state]] and [[Head of government|government]]: [[President of Argentina]], [[Mauricio Macri]]
* [[Ministries of the Argentine Republic|Cabinet of Argentina]]
* [[Chief of the Cabinet of Ministers]]
* Minister of the Interior
* [[Ministry of Foreign Affairs, International Trade and Worship|Minister of Foreign Relations]] (mostly known as the [[Chancellor#Foreign minister|''Chancellor'']])
* [[Ministry of Defense (Argentina)|Minister of Defense]]
* [[Minister of Economy of Argentina|Minister of Economy]]
* Minister of Justice and Human Rights
* Minister of Security
* Minister of Labor, Employment and Social Security
* Minister of Education
* Minister of Science, Technology and Product Innovation
* Minister of Health
* Minister of Social Development
* Minister of Federal Planning, Public Infrastructure and Services
* Minister of Industry
* Minister of Agriculture
* Minister of Tourism

==== Legislative branch of the government of Argentina ====
[[File:Buenos Aires-Plaza Congreso-Pensador de Rodin.jpg|thumb|210px|The [[Argentine Congress]] and one of the few surviving original casts of [[Auguste Rodin]]'s ''[[The Thinker]]''.]][[Image:Palacio de justicia.JPG|thumb|210px|The Argentine Supreme Court]]

* [[Argentine National Congress]] (''Congreso Nacional'') ([[bicameral]])
** [[Upper house]]: [[Argentine Senate]] (72 seats), presided by the Vice-President
** [[Argentine Chamber of Deputies]] (257 seats), currently presided by Emilio Monzó of [[Buenos Aires Province]]).

==== Judicial branch of the government of Argentina ====


Court system of Argentina
* [[Supreme Court of Argentina]]
** President of the Supreme Court: Dr. [[Ricardo Lorenzetti|Ricardo L. Lorenzetti]]
** Vice-President of the Supreme Court: Dra. [[Elena Highton|Elena I. Highton de Nolasco]]
** Minister of the Court: Dr. [[Carlos Fernando Rosenkrantz]]
** Minister of the Court: Dr. [[Juan Carlos Maqueda]]
** Minister of the Court: Dr. Horacio Rosatti

=== Foreign relations of Argentina ===

[[Foreign relations of Argentina]]
* Diplomatic missions
** [[List of diplomatic missions in Argentina|Diplomatic missions in Argentina]]
** [[Diplomatic missions of Argentina]]

==== International organization membership ====
The Argentine Republic is a member of:&lt;ref name=CIA_World_Factbook&gt;{{cite web|date=July 9, 2009|url=https://www.cia.gov/library/publications/the-world-factbook/geos/ar.html|title=Argentina|work=[[The World Factbook]]|publisher=[[United States]] [[Central Intelligence Agency]]|accessdate=July 23, 2009}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{Col-begin}}
{{Col-2}}
*[[African Development Bank Group]] (AfDB) (nonregional member)
*[[Agency for the Prohibition of Nuclear Weapons in Latin America and the Caribbean]] (OPANAL)
*[[Andean Community of Nations]] (CAN) (associate)
*[[Australia Group]]
*[[Bank for International Settlements]] (BIS)
*[[Central American Bank for Economic Integration]] (BCIE)
*[[Central American Integration System]] (SICA) (observer)
*[[Food and Agriculture Organization]] (FAO)
*[[Group of 15]] (G15)
*[[Group of Twenty Finance Ministers and Central Bank Governors]] (G20)
*[[Group of 24]] (G24)
*[[Group of 77]] (G77)
*[[Inter-American Development Bank]] (IADB)
*[[International Atomic Energy Agency]] (IAEA)
*[[International Bank for Reconstruction and Development]] (IBRD)
*[[International Chamber of Commerce]] (ICC)
*[[International Civil Aviation Organization]] (ICAO)
*[[International Criminal Court]] (ICCt)
*[[International Criminal Police Organization]] (Interpol)
*[[International Development Association]] (IDA)
*[[International Federation of Red Cross and Red Crescent Societies]] (IFRCS)
*[[International Finance Corporation]] (IFC)
*[[International Fund for Agricultural Development]] (IFAD)
*[[International Hydrographic Organization]] (IHO)
*[[International Labour Organization]] (ILO)
*[[International Maritime Organization]] (IMO)
*[[International Mobile Satellite Organization]] (IMSO)
*[[International Monetary Fund]] (IMF)
*[[International Olympic Committee]] (IOC)
*[[International Organization for Migration]] (IOM)
*[[International Organization for Standardization]] (ISO)
*[[International Red Cross and Red Crescent Movement]] (ICRM)
*[[International Telecommunication Union]] (ITU)
{{Col-2}}
*[[International Telecommunications Satellite Organization]] (ITSO)
*[[International Trade Union Confederation]] (ITUC)
*[[Inter-Parliamentary Union]] (IPU)
*[[Latin American Economic System]] (LAES)
*[[Latin American Integration Association]] (LAIA)
*[[Multilateral Investment Guarantee Agency]] (MIGA)
*[[Nuclear Suppliers Group]] (NSG)
*[[Organisation for the Prohibition of Chemical Weapons]] (OPCW)
*[[Organization of American States]] (OAS)
*[[Permanent Court of Arbitration]] (PCA)
*[[Rio Group]] (RG)
*[[Southern Cone Common Market]] (Mercosur)
*''[[Unión Latina]]'' (observer)
*[[United Nations]] (UN)
*[[Union of South American Nations]] (UNASUR)
*[[United Nations Conference on Trade and Development]] (UNCTAD)
*[[United Nations Educational, Scientific, and Cultural Organization]] (UNESCO)
*[[United Nations High Commissioner for Refugees]] (UNHCR)
*[[United Nations Industrial Development Organization]] (UNIDO)
*[[United Nations Mission for the Referendum in Western Sahara]] (MINURSO)
*[[United Nations Peacekeeping Force in Cyprus]] (UNFICYP)
*[[United Nations Stabilization Mission in Haiti]] (MINUSTAH)
*[[United Nations Truce Supervision Organization]] (UNTSO)
*[[Universal Postal Union]] (UPU)
*[[World Confederation of Labour]] (WCL)
*[[World Customs Organization]] (WCO)
*[[World Federation of Trade Unions]] (WFTU)
*[[World Health Organization]] (WHO)
*[[World Intellectual Property Organization]] (WIPO)
*[[World Meteorological Organization]] (WMO)
*[[World Tourism Organization]] (UNWTO)
*[[World Trade Organization]] (WTO)
*[[Zangger Committee]] (ZC)
{{Col-end}}

=== Law and order in Argentina ===

[[Law of Argentina]]
* [[Constitution of Argentina]]
* [[Crime in Argentina]]
* [[Human rights in Argentina]]
** [[LGBT rights in Argentina]]
* [[Law enforcement in Argentina]]
** National law enforcement agencies
***[[Policía Federal Argentina|Argentine Federal Police]]
***[[Gendarmería Nacional Argentina|Argentine National Gendarmerie]]
***[[Prefectura Naval Argentina|Argentine Naval Prefecture]]
***[[Policía de Seguridad Aeroportuaria|Airport Security Police]]
***[[Servicio Penitenciario Federal|Federal Penitentiary Service]]
** Regional law enforcement agencies
***[[Policía Bonaerense|Buenos Aires Provincial Police]]
***[[Policía de la Provincia de Santa Fe|Santa Fe Province Police]]
***[[Policía de la Provincia de Córdoba|Córdoba Province Police]]
***[[Policía de la Provincia de Tucumán|Tucumán Province Police]]

=== Military of Argentina ===
[[File:Vista de Puerto Madero - Aduana de Buenos Aires.jpg|thumb|210px|The Libertador Building, seat of the Argentine Defense Ministry]]

[[Armed Forces of the Argentine Republic]]
* Command
** [[Commander-in-chief]]: [[President of Argentina]], [[Cristina Fernández de Kirchner]]
*** [[Ministry of Defense (Argentina)]]
* Forces
** [[Argentine Army]]
*** [[Argentine Army Aviation]]
** [[Argentine Air Force]]
*** [[Agrupación Aérea Presidencial]]
*** [[Argentine Air Force Mobile Field Hospital]]
** [[Navy of the Argentine Republic|Argentine Navy]]
*** [[Argentine Naval Aviation]]
*** [[Argentine Marines]]
* [[Military history of Argentina]]
* [[Military ranks of Argentina]]
* [[White Helmets Commission]]

== History of Argentina ==

[[History of Argentina]]
=== History of Argentina, by period ===
* [[May Revolution]]

=== History of Argentina, by region ===

* [[History of Buenos Aires]]
** [[Timeline of Buenos Aires history]]

=== History of Argentina, by subject ===
* [[Economic history of Argentina]]
* [[Military history of Argentina]]

== Culture of Argentina ==

[[Culture of Argentina]]
* [[Architecture of Argentina]]
* [[Cuisine of Argentina]]
* [[Humor in Argentina]]
* [[Languages of Argentina]]
* [[Media in Argentina]]
* [[National symbols of Argentina]]
** [[Coat of arms of Argentina]]
** [[Flag of Argentina]]
** [[National anthem of Argentina]]
* [[People of Argentina]]
* [[Public holidays in Argentina]]
* [[Religion in Argentina]]
** [[Buddhism in Argentina]]
** [[Christianity in Argentina]]
** [[Hinduism in Argentina]]
** [[Islam in Argentina]]
** [[Judaism in Argentina]]
* [[List of World Heritage Sites in the Americas#Argentina|World Heritage Sites in Argentina]]

=== Art in Argentina ===
* [[Cinema of Argentina]]
* [[Literature of Argentina]]
* [[Music of Argentina]]
** [[List of music artists and bands from Argentina]]
* [[Television in Argentina]]
* [[Theatre in Argentina]]

=== Sports in Argentina ===

[[Sports in Argentina]]
* [[Argentina at the Olympics]]
* [[Football in Argentina]]

== Economy and infrastructure of Argentina ==

[[Economy of Argentina]]
* [[List of countries by GDP (nominal)|Economic rank, by nominal GDP (2007)]]:  31st (thirty-first)
* [[Agriculture in Argentina]]
* [[Banking in Argentina]]
* [[Communications in Argentina]]
** [[Internet in Argentina]]
***[[.ar]] [[Internet]] [[country code top-level domain]] for Argentina
* [[List of companies of Argentina|Companies of Argentina]]
* [[Currency|Currency of Argentina]]: [[Argentine peso|Peso]]
**[[ISO 4217]]: ARS
* [[Economic history of Argentina]]
* [[Energy in Argentina]]
** [[Energy in Argentina]]
* [[Health care in Argentina]]
* [[Mining in Argentina]]
* [[Argentina Stock Exchange]]
* [[Tourism in Argentina]]
* [[Visa policy of Argentina]]
* [[Transport in Argentina]]
** [[List of airports in Argentina|Airports in Argentina]]
** [[Rail transport in Argentina]]
** [[Roads in Argentina]]
* [[Water supply and sanitation in Argentina]]

== Education in Argentina ==

[[Education in Argentina]]
* [[List of schools in Argentina]]
* [[List of Roman Catholic seminaries#Argentina|Roman Catholic seminaries in Argentina]]
* Universities in Argentina
** [[List of agricultural universities and colleges#Argentina|Agricultural universities and colleges in Argentina]]

==See also==
{{Portal|Buenos Aires|Córdoba|Rosario|Football in Argentina|Argentina|Latin America}}
{{InterWiki|Spanish language|code=es}}

[[Argentina]]
*{{PrefixAllPages|Argentina}}
*{{PrefixAllPages|Argentine}}
*{{Intitle|Argentina}}
*{{Intitle|Argentine}}
*[[Index of Argentina-related articles]]
*[[List of Argentina-related topics]]
*[[List of international rankings]]
*[[Member state of the Group of Twenty Finance Ministers and Central Bank Governors]]
*[[Member state of the United Nations]]
*[[Outline of geography]]
*[[Outline of South America]]

==References==
{{Reflist|1}}

==External links==
{{Sisterlinks|Argentina}}
* {{Wikiatlas|Argentina}}
* [http://www.argentinaoutlook.com Business News and Analysis in English]
* [http://www.argentina.gov.ar Government of Argentina] {{es icon}}
* [http://www.argentina.ar Official website]
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20080417154757/http://www.portalbue.com.ar/ Information about Buenos Aires]
* [http://www.casarosada.gov.ar/index.php?lang=en The President of Argentina]
* {{dmoz|Regional/South_America/Argentina}}

; Country Data
* {{CIA World Factbook link|ar|Argentina}}
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20080513045004/http://devdata.worldbank.org/external/CPProfile.asp?SelectedCountry=ARG&amp;CCODE=ARG&amp;CNAME=Argentina&amp;PTYPE=CP World Bank's country data profile] for Argentina.
* [http://www.wipo.int/about-ip/en/ipworldwide/pdf/ar.pdf World Intellectual Property Handbook: Argentina]
{{Clear}}

{{Outline footer}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Argentina}}
[[Category:Outlines of countries|Argentina]]
[[Category:Argentina| ]]
[[Category:Argentina-related lists| ]]</text>
      <sha1>iv2fp91876rqjkhmxx3uhvmrivk89ru</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>RDP África</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>23338743</id>
    <revision>
      <id>835117769</id>
      <parentid>815742526</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-04-06T17:27:03Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>InternetArchiveBot</username>
        <id>27015025</id>
      </contributor>
      <comment>Rescuing 1 sources and tagging 0 as dead. #IABot (v1.6.5)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2472">{{Infobox broadcasting network
|network_name = RDP África
|network_logo = [[Image:RdpAfrica_2016.png|200px]]
|branding     = RDP África
|country      = [[Portugal]] and [[Portuguese-speaking African countries|Lusophone Africa]]
|network_type = terrestrial, [[cable radio|cable]], [[Digital Audio Broadcasting|digital]], and [[satellite radio|satellite]] [[Radio]] 
|available    = [[International]]
|owner        = [[Rádio e Televisão de Portugal|RTP]]
|launch_date  = 7 January 1998
|website      = [http://www.rtp.pt/rdpafrica/]
}}

'''RDP África''' is a terrestrial radio station owned by [[Rádio e Televisão de Portugal]] broadcasting to [[Lusophone]] African countries with programming such as Lusophone [[music of Africa|African music]], as well as [[music of Portugal|Portuguese music]] and [[music of Brazil|Brazilian music]], with update reports from the Lusophone African recording world.

The station broadcasts on FM in Portugal (Lisboa 101.5&amp;nbsp;MHz, Coimbra 103.4&amp;nbsp;MHz and Faro 99.1&amp;nbsp;MHz), but also on most African Portuguese-speaking countries: [[Cape Verde]], [[Guinea-Bissau]], [[Mozambique]], and [[São Tomé and Príncipe]].

RDP África was introduced to Lusophone Africa when RDP Internacional stopped its broadcast on 6 January 1998 and launched RDP África the next day. The radio station also serves the Portuguese populations of Lusophone Africa and African populations of both black, white, and [[mulatto]] blood of Portugal.

[[File:RDP Africa.png|200px|thumb|right|RDP África logo from 2004 to 2016.]]

==External links==
*[http://www.rtp.pt/rdpafrica/ RDP África Website]
*[https://web.archive.org/web/20090930061250/http://tv1.rtp.pt/canais-radio/rdpafrica/distribuicao.php?canal=4 FM, DAB and satellite transmitting network]
*[http://www.rtp.pt/play/direto/rdpafrica RDP África Live Stream on RTP Play]

{{Rádio e Televisão de Portugal}}
{{Radio stations in Portugal}}

{{coord missing|Portugal}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:RDP Africa}}
[[Category:External services (broadcasting)]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Angola]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Cape Verde]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Guinea-Bissau]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Mozambique]]
[[Category:Radio stations in Portugal]]
[[Category:Radio stations in São Tomé and Príncipe]]
[[Category:Portuguese-language radio stations]]
[[Category:Rádio e Televisão de Portugal]]
[[Category:1998 establishments in Portugal]]
[[Category:Radio stations established in 1998]]</text>
      <sha1>gts3gr51ktr861xxva9phqnjzeuytr3</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Roman Catholic Diocese of Fort Portal</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>15344060</id>
    <revision>
      <id>792300811</id>
      <parentid>744792887</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-07-25T18:48:52Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Jeromeenriquez</username>
        <id>27291737</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="3516">{{Use dmy dates|date=March 2014}}
{{Expand Italian|Diocesi di Fort Portal|date=February 2011}}
{{Infobox diocese
|jurisdiction     = Diocese
|name             = Fort Portal
|latin            = Dioecesis Arcis Portal
|country          = {{flag|Uganda}}
|metropolitan     = [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Mbarara|Mbarara]]
|rite             = [[Latin Church|Latin Rite]]
|cathedral        = 
|cocathedral      = 
|area_km2         = 9,553
|population       = 1,486,000 
|population_as_of = 2006 
|catholics        = 696,000 
|catholics_percent= 46.8 
|pope             = {{Incumbent pope}}
|bishop           = [[Robert Muhiirwa]] 
|coadjutor        = 
|auxiliary_bishops= [[Joseph Mugenyi Sabiiti]] 
}}

The '''Roman Catholic Diocese of Fort Portal''' ({{lang-la|Arcis Portal}}) is a [[diocese]] located in the city of [[Fort Portal]] in the [[Ecclesiastical province]] of [[Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Mbarara|Mbarara]] in [[Uganda]].

The Catholic Diocese of Fort Portal formerly belonging to Rwenzori Vicariate was erected on 2 July 1961, with Vincent Joseph McCauley CSC as its first bishop. He was succeeded in 1972 by Serapio Magambo who served the Diocese until 1991, when Paul Kalanda took over as the third Bishop of the Diocese. His successor, the current bishop, Robert Muhiirwa, was ordained and installed on 15 June 2003.

==Leadership==
* [[Bishop]]s of Fort Portal (Roman rite)
** Robert Muhiirwa (since 2003.03.18)&lt;ref&gt;[http://www.catholic-hierarchy.org/bishop/bmuhi.html Robert Muhiirwa Appointed Bishop on 18 March 2003 &amp; Ordained Bishop of Fort Portal Diocese on 15 June 2003]&lt;/ref&gt; 
** [[Paul Lokiru Kalanda]] (1991.06.17 – 2003.03.18)
** Serapio Bwemi Magambo (1972.11.16 – 1991.06.17)
** [[Vincent J. McCauley]], [[Congregation of Holy Cross|C.S.C.]] (1961.02.21 – 1972.11.16)

Robert Muhiirwa Akiiki

Born at Ibonde, Virika Parish, Fort Portal Diocese on 23 Oct. 1958, ordained a priest on 11 August 1985. Appointed Bishop of Fort Portal Diocese on 18 March 2003; consecrated and installed as Bishop of Fort Portal Diocese on 15 June 2003.
Lokiru Paul Kalanda

Lokiru Paul Kalanda. Born at Buwunde, Masaka Diocese, on 24 Feb.1927, ordained priest on 21 Dec.1957. Appointed Bishop of Moroto on 29 Nov 1980. Consecrated Bishop on 22 March 1981. Appointed Bishop of Fort Portal on 28 April 1991, installed Bishop of Fort Portal on 3 Nov.1991. Retired on 15 June 2003 and appointed Apostolic Admini-strator of Lira Diocese on 2 Dec. till 9 July 2005.

Joseph Mugenyi Sabiti, Auxiliary, Bishop of Fort Portal Diocese

Joseph Sabiiti Mugenyi. Born at Nyansozi, Fort Portal Diocese on 8 May 1948. Ordained Priest on 1 June 1975. Appointed Auxiliary Bishop of Fort Portal on 30 Jan.1999, Consecrated Bishop at Virika on 24 April 1999.

== References ==
&lt;references /&gt;

==External links==
* [http://www.gcatholic.org/dioceses/diocese/fort2.htm GCatholic.org]
* [http://www.catholic-hierarchy.org/diocese/dfopo.html Catholic Hierarchy]
*[http://www.avemariapress.com/itemdetail.cfm?nItemid=931 Vincent McCauley: Bishop of the Poor, Apostle of East Africa] Ave Maria Press (2008)

{{Kabarole District}}

{{coord|0.6366|N|30.2684|E|source:wikidata|display=title}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Fort Portal}}
[[Category:Roman Catholic dioceses in Uganda]]
[[Category:Religious organizations established in 1961]]
[[Category:Roman Catholic dioceses and prelatures established in the 20th century]]
[[Category:Kabarole District]]
[[Category:1961 establishments in Uganda]]

{{Uganda-stub}}
{{Africa-RC-diocese-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>j281e3mbs9bbs6sse39nau8lry52gxe</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Sampson (horse)</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>5572696</id>
    <revision>
      <id>870897841</id>
      <parentid>870897837</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-27T17:46:49Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>ClueBot NG</username>
        <id>13286072</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Reverting possible vandalism by [[Special:Contribs/94.118.95.78|94.118.95.78]] to version by Oshwah. [[WP:CBFP|Report False Positive?]] Thanks, [[WP:CBNG|ClueBot NG]]. (3548874) (Bot)</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="916">'''Sampson''' was a [[Shire horse]] [[gelding]] [[foal]]ed in 1846 in Toddington Mills, [[Bedfordshire]], [[England]]. He was the tallest and heaviest [[horse]] ever recorded.

Sampson, owned by Thomas Cleaver, stood {{hands|21.2+1/2}} high by the time he was four years old, when he was renamed '''Mammoth'''. 

His peak weight was estimated at {{convert|3360|lb|kg|0|abbr=on|lk=on}}.&lt;ref name=Whitaker60&gt;Whitaker ''The Horse'' p. 60&lt;/ref&gt;  He was [[gelding|gelded]] at approximately one and a half years old, and [[horse testicles|his testicles]] were already the size of [[Ball (association football)|soccer ball]]s.&lt;ref&gt;''Encyclopedia of the Horse'', Norris, Carlos R., 1998, p. 174.&lt;/ref&gt;

== References ==
{{Reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Sampson (Horse)}}
[[Category:1846 animal births]]
[[Category:Draft horses]]
[[Category:Individual male horses]]
[[Category:World record holders]]
[[Category:Biological records]]</text>
      <sha1>83su802kwobh2hkio2ufrwmqakh4zc5</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Snooker world rankings 2005/2006</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>1841044</id>
    <revision>
      <id>770257631</id>
      <parentid>769767494</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-03-14T10:40:38Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>NuclearMissile</username>
        <id>29920985</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="6956">'''Snooker world rankings 2005/2006''': The professional [[snooker world rankings|world rankings]] for the top 64 [[snooker]] players in the [[Snooker season 2005/2006|2005/2006 season]] are listed below.

{{Infobox snooker player
|name         = No. 1: [[Ronnie O'Sullivan]]
|image        = Stephen Maguire, Ronnie O’Sullivan, and Michaela Tabb at German Masters Snooker Final (DerHexer) 2012-02-05 05 cropped.jpg
|birth_date         = {{birth date and age|1975|12|5}}
| Sport country = {{ENG}}
| Professional = 1992–
| High ranking = 1
}}

{{Infobox snooker player
|name         = No. 2: [[Stephen Hendry]]
|image        =  Stephen Hendry.jpg
|birth_date         = {{birth date and age|1969|1|13}}
| Sport country = {{SCO}}
| Professional = 1985–2012
| High ranking = 1
}}

{{Infobox snooker player
|name         = No. 3: [[Stephen Maguire]]
|image        = Stephen Maguire at German Masters Snooker Final (DerHexer) 2012-02-05 23.jpg
|birth_date         = {{birth date and age|1981|3|13}}
| Sport country = {{SCO}}
| Professional = 1998–
| High ranking = 2
}}

{| class="wikitable"
! No.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Turner|first=Chris|title=Historical World Rankings 2005/06 to 2009/10|url=http://www.cajt.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/HistoricRank3.html|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120313150350/http://www.cajt.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk/HistoricRank3.html|archivedate=13 March 2012|work=cajt.pwp.blueyonder.co.uk|publisher=Chris Turner's Snooker Archive|accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;
! align="left" | Name
! align="left" | Nationality
! align="left" | Points&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Embassy World Rankings 2005/2006|url=http://www.snooker.org/Rnk/0506/ranking.asp|publisher=Snooker.org|accessdate=26 February 2011}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Official ranking list for the 2005/06 season|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/offical_rankings.htm|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=24 June 2013|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20051105041327/http://www.worldsnooker.com/offical_rankings.htm|archivedate=5 November 2005}}&lt;/ref&gt;
|-
| 1
| [[Ronnie O'Sullivan]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 49812
|-
| 2
| [[Stephen Hendry]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 42137
|-
| 3
| [[Stephen Maguire]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 33750
|-
| 4
| [[Matthew Stevens]]
| {{flag|Wales}}
| 33712
|-
| 5
| [[Paul Hunter (snooker player)|Paul Hunter]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 32125
|-
| 6
| [[John Higgins (snooker player)|John Higgins]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 32024
|-
| 7
| [[Peter Ebdon]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 31175
|-
| 8
| [[Jimmy White]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 30962
|-
| 9
| [[Mark Williams (snooker player)|Mark Williams]]
| {{flag|Wales}}
| 29749
|-
| 10
| [[Stephen Lee (snooker player)|Stephen Lee]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 29650
|-
| 11
| [[Ken Doherty]]
| {{flag|Ireland}}
| 29124
|-
| 12
| [[Alan McManus]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 28800
|-
| 13
| [[Graeme Dott]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 28315
|-
| 14
| [[Joe Perry (snooker player)|Joe Perry]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 27150
|-
| 15
| [[Steve Davis]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 26987
|-
| 16
| [[Ian McCulloch (snooker player)|Ian McCulloch]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 26612
|-
| 17
| [[Anthony Hamilton (snooker player)|Anthony Hamilton]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 26549
|-
| 18
| [[Barry Pinches]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 26375
|-
| 19
| [[Allister Carter]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 25500
|-
| 20
| [[Mark King (snooker player)|Mark King]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 25400
|-
| 21
| [[Shaun Murphy (snooker player)|Shaun Murphy]]{{ref label|Murphy|a|a}}
| {{flag|England}}
| 25112
|-
| 22
| [[Quinten Hann]]{{ref label|Hann|b|b}} 
| {{flag|Australia}}
| 24950
|-
| 23
| [[David Gray (snooker player)|David Gray]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 24950
|-
| 24
| [[Michael Holt (snooker player)|Michael Holt]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 24712
|-
| 25
| [[Marco Fu]]
| {{flag|Hong Kong}}
| 22724
|-
| 26
| [[Robert Milkins]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 22687
|-
| 27
| [[Nigel Bond]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 22500
|-
| 28
| [[Neil Robertson (snooker player)|Neil Robertson]]
| {{flag|Australia}}
| 22275
|-
| 29
| [[John Parrott]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 22150
|-
| 30
| [[Barry Hawkins]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 21950
|-
| 31
| [[Andy Hicks]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 21800
|-
| 32
| [[James Wattana]]
| {{flag|Thailand}}
| 21800
|-
| 33
| [[Ryan Day]]
| {{flag|Wales}}
| 21725
|-
| 34
| [[Dominic Dale]]
| {{flag|Wales}}
| 20775
|-
| 35
| [[Drew Henry]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 19762
|-
| 36
| [[Tony Drago]]
| {{flag|Malta}}
| 19762
|-
| 37
| [[Stuart Bingham]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 19650
|-
| 38
| [[Gerard Greene]]
| {{flag|Northern Ireland}}
| 19562
|-
| 39
| [[Mark Selby]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 19537
|-
| 40
| [[Joe Swail]]
| {{flag|Northern Ireland}}
| 18874
|-
| 41
| [[Chris Small]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 18712
|-
| 42
| [[Mark Davis (snooker player)|Mark Davis]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 18700
|-
| 43
| [[Michael Judge]]
| {{flag|Ireland}}
| 18050
|-
| 44
| [[Fergal O'Brien]]
| {{flag|Ireland}}
| 16750
|-
| 45
| [[Dave Harold]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 16725
|-
| 46
| [[Adrian Gunnell]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 16575
|-
| 47
| [[Stuart Pettman]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 16100
|-
| 48
| [[Ricky Walden]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 15500
|-
| 49
| [[Rory McLeod (snooker player)|Rory McLeod]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 15500
|-
| 50
| [[Patrick Wallace]]
| {{flag|Northern Ireland}}
| 17762
|-
| 51
| [[Tom Ford (snooker player)|Tom Ford]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 15175
|-
| 52
| [[Marcus Campbell]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 15175
|-
| 53
| [[Mike Dunn (snooker player)|Mike Dunn]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 15037
|-
| 54
| [[Shokat Ali]]
| {{flag|Pakistan}}
| 14837
|-
| 55
| [[Robin Hull]]
| {{flag|Finland}}
| 14737
|-
| 56
| [[Jamie Burnett]]
| {{flag|Scotland}}
| 14550
|-
| 57
| [[Jimmy Michie]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 13912
|-
| 58
| [[Lee Walker]]
| {{flag|Wales}}
| 13487
|-
| 59
| [[Brian Morgan (snooker player)|Brian Morgan]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 13450
|-
| 60
| [[Rod Lawler]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 13412
|-
| 61
| [[David Roe]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 13324
|-
| 62
| [[Ding Junhui]]
| {{flag|China}}
| 13225
|-
| 63
| [[Simon Bedford]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 12550
|-
| 64
| [[Shailesh Jogia|Joe Jogia]]
| {{flag|England}}
| 12550
|}

{{clear|left}}

==Note==
{{refbegin}}
*{{note label|Murphy|a|a}} As the [[2005 World Snooker Championship|2005]] World Champion, [[Shaun Murphy (snooker player)|Shaun Murphy]] automatically qualified for every ranking tournament and the Masters.
*{{note label|Hann|b|b}} [[Quinten Hann]] did not play due to an unspecified illness before being banned for 8 years for a match-fixing attempt.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite news|title=Guilty Hann given eight-year ban|url=http://news.bbc.co.uk/sport2/hi/other_sports/snooker/4725612.stm|publisher=[[BBC Sport]]|accessdate=23 April 2011|date=17 February 2006}}&lt;/ref&gt;
{{refend}}

==References==
{{Reflist}}

{{Snooker world rankings}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Snooker world rankings 2005}}
[[Category:Snooker world rankings|2005]]
[[Category:2005 in snooker|Rankings 2006]]
[[Category:2006 in snooker|Rankings 2005]]</text>
      <sha1>ayvajm72iso78251niqf8slp8wnlvbl</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Snooker world rankings 2013/2014</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>39318137</id>
    <revision>
      <id>853397095</id>
      <parentid>808202214</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-08-04T13:54:21Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>BlueFire10</username>
        <id>15017332</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="29359">{{sequence|
 prev=[[Snooker world rankings 2012/2013|2012/2013]]|
 next=[[Snooker world rankings 2014/2015|2014/2015]]|
 list=2013/2014
 }}
'''Snooker world rankings 2013/2014''': The professional [[Snooker world rankings|world rankings]] for all the professional [[snooker]] players, who qualified for the [[Snooker season 2013/2014|2013/2014 season]], are listed below. The rankings worked as a two-year rolling list. The points for each tournament two years ago were removed, when the corresponding tournament during the current season finished. The following table contains the rankings, which were used to determine the seedings for certain tournaments.

{| class="wikitable sortable" style="text-align:center;"
!  style="text-align:left; text-align:left;"|Name
!  style="text-align:left; text-align:left;"|Country&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&lt;!--Leave spaces or s wrap ugly at narrow window widths.--&gt;
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 1{{ref label|rev1|a|a}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World Rankings 2012/2013 Updated after the 2013 World Championship|url=http://www.snooker.org/res/index.asp?template=11&amp;season=2012|publisher=Snooker.org|accessdate=6 May 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=The World Professional Billiards &amp; Snooker Association official World Snooker ranking list for the 2013/2014 season|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/48/bc/0,,13165~179272,00.pdf|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|work=worldsnooker.com|accessdate=8 May 2013|date=8 May 2013|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6GTFR8281|archivedate=8 May 2013|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 2{{ref label|rev2|b|b}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|last=Brownell|first=Simon|title=Issued After The Rotterdam Open (ET2) 2013|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/b8/bd/0,,13165~179640,00.pdf|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=23 July 2013|date=22 July 2013|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6IKEx1yJQ|archivedate=23 July 2013|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 3{{ref label|rev3|c|c}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World rankings after the Shanghai Masters 2013|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/b7/be/0,,13165~179895,00.pdf|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=23 September 2013|date=23 September 2013|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6Jqpbcj8g|archivedate=23 September 2013|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 4{{ref label|rev4|d|d}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World rankings after the International Championship 2013|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/49/bf/0,,13165~180041,00.pdf|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=4 November 2013|date=4 November 2013|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6KsrrOgtD|archivedate=4 November 2013|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 5{{ref label|rev5|e|e}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World rankings after the UK Championship 2013|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/b7/bf/0,,13165~180151,00.pdf|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=10 December 2013|date=9 December 2013|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6LlJZADhD|archivedate=10 December 2013|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 6{{ref label|rev6|f|f}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World rankings after the German Masters 2014|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/53/c0/0,,13165~180307,00.pdf|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=4 February 2014|date=3 February 2014|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6N7o8KGjq|archivedate=4 February 2014|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
! colspan="2"|{{nowrap|Revision 7{{ref label|rev7|g|g}}&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=World rankings after the Players Championship 2014|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/fe/c0/0,,13165~180478,00.pdf|work=worldsnooker.com|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|accessdate=1 April 2014|date=31 March 2014|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6OVifGGv4|archivedate=1 April 2014|format=PDF}}&lt;/ref&gt;}}
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Neil Robertson (snooker player)|Neil Robertson]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{AUS}}||2||79460||1||90160||1||86580||1||87680||1||89800||1||89300||1||88800
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mark Selby]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||1||79740||2||83640||2||78100||2||82220||2||87020||2||85160||2||84480
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ding Junhui]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||10||57900||11||59920||7||64700||3||77900||3||79540||3||82520||3||83660
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Barry Hawkins]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||9||58880||7||63085||6||65480||8||66620||6||69700||5||68980||4||73500
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Stuart Bingham]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||6||62940||8||61800||10||60760||9||64540||7||69500||6||68140||5||72320
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Judd Trump]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||3||76720||3||78200||3||75640||4||74760||4||69960||4||70460||6||71640
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Marco Fu]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{HKG}}||17||49790||13||57110||11||60565||6||67805||9||64645||9||63850||7||69750
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Shaun Murphy (snooker player)|Shaun Murphy]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||4||68220||4||68600||4||68680||7||67400||8||66440||8||64420||8||69260
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Stephen Maguire]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||5||66940||5||66480||5||66360||5||70200||5||69840||7||64480||9||64080
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[John Higgins (snooker player)|John Higgins]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||11||56355||6||64575||9||62415||10||64155||12||62235||10||61375||10||63395
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ricky Walden]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||8||59765||9||61710||8||63365||12||62685||11||62485||12||58985||11||60350
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mark Davis (snooker player)|Mark Davis]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||13||54280||15||56080||14||56020||13||60440||14||59440||13||58980||12||60055
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ali Carter]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||16||52895||18||54295||15||55795||16||57015||17||56815||16||56455||13||59615
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mark Allen (snooker player)|Mark Allen]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{nowrap|{{NIR}}}}||7||62460||10||61220||12||59260||11||63700||10||63700||11||61340||14||59220
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Joe Perry (snooker player)|Joe Perry]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||20||44580||19||50300||19||50375||18||55515||15||57995||15||56995||15||58580
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Robert Milkins]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||18||48580||14||57005||13||57285||14||58765||13||59925||14||58615||16||57165
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Graeme Dott]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||12||54900||16||55100||17||53100||15||57340||16||57140||17||55000||17||55480
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mark Williams (snooker player)|Mark Williams]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||15||53260||17||54520||18||50405||19||55105||18||55065||18||53045||18||55165
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Matthew Stevens]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||14||53660||12||58200||16||54560||17||56400||19||55040||19||52620||19||52260
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ryan Day]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||31||39575||28||42715||26||42615||21||46435||21||45795||21||46675||20||49655
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Liang Wenbo]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||32||37600||35||38020||36||37160||26||44460||23||45180||23||45260||21||49610
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Michael Holt (snooker player)|Michael Holt]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||26||43155||26||43425||21||45205||20||47285||20||47565||20||47740||22||47100
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Dominic Dale]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||23||43915||20||46095||23||44940||23||45760||29||42360||26||43125||23||44370
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Peter Ebdon]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||30||40135||32||41270||29||41095||25||44715||22||45795||22||45295||24||44050
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Xiao Guodong]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||37||34185||37||37680||28||41145||27||43705||26||43385||25||43865||25||43670
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mark King (snooker player)|Mark King]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||29||41665||25||44325||27||42505||28||42865||25||43585||24||44050||26||43270
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ronnie O'Sullivan]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||19||46360||21||45640||25||42900||29||42780||24||44300||31||39700||27||42640
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ben Woollaston]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||33||37590||31||41620||32||39315||33||40955||34||39715||30||39715||28||41755
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ken Doherty]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{IRL}}||27||42130||30||41790||30||40670||32||41450||33||39850||34||38790||29||40380
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Michael White (snooker player)|Michael White]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||34||36495||33||39315||34||38740||34||40280||32||40040||33||38870||30||40145
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[David Gilbert (snooker player)|David Gilbert]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||41||32055||41||34470||35||37270||35||39130||36||38890||36||38345||31||40045
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Fergal O'Brien]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{IRL}}||36||35590||34||38200||40||34425||36||37745||35||39065||35||38670||32||39825
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Andrew Higginson]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||22||44055||23||45315||24||43995||30||42355||28||42675||27||40615||33||39520
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Alan McManus]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||49||29505||43||32945||46||31860||45||33800||43||34120||42||34200||34||39040
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Marcus Campbell]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||28||42045||29||42025||31||40465||31||42005||31||42005||29||40185||35||38670
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Tom Ford (snooker player)|Tom Ford]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||24||43715||24||45235||22||44990||24||45190||27||42830||28||40330||36||38650
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mark Joyce]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||42||31620||48||31605||43||32895||37||36335||39||35535||39||35750||37||38155
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Martin Gould]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||25||43515||22||45375||20||45775||22||46335||30||42295||32||39115||38||38115
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jack Lisowski]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||35||35625||36||38005||37||36585||39||35785||37||35625||37||36140||39||36880
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Anthony Hamilton (snooker player)|Anthony Hamilton]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||43||31440||39||35810||39||34530||41||35150||42||34710||43||34180||40||36480
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Kurt Maflin]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{NOR}}||64||18690||62||21555||60||23735||60||27175||51||30135||47||32035||41||36155
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Rod Lawler]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||59||21535||59||23140||58||24715||56||28715||50||30515||44||33715||42||36135
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jamie Burnett]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||39||34005||40||34890||42||33420||44||34400||40||35360||38||35800||43||35200
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Anthony McGill (snooker player)|Anthony McGill]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||48||29580||46||32235||51||30350||43||34490||41||34730||40||34620||44||35120
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jamie Jones (snooker player)|Jamie Jones]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||40||32510||42||34375||38||34565||42||35145||38||35585||41||34275||45||34835
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Alfred Burden|Alfie Burden]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||53||27740||50||31295||45||31940||47||33420||44||34100||45||33600||46||34250
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Rory McLeod (snooker player)|Rory McLeod]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||45||30900||45||32520||44||32700||46||33780||48||32780||48||31920||47||33760
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Yu Delu]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||47||29805||47||31815||48||31225||48||32365||46||33685||49||31425||48||33605
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jamie Cope]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||38||34145||38||37165||41||33840||40||35380||45||33900||46||32605||49||31390
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Cao Yupeng]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||66||17305||60||22130||59||24090||58||27450||57||28090||55||28990||50||31150
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Liu Chuang (snooker player)|Liu Chuang]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||54||27145||53||28920||52||28560||52||30100||49||31020||50||30770||51||30875
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Tian Pengfei]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||70||15660||67||18820||65||20440||66||23200||62||25000||59||26900||52||30180
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jimmy Robertson (snooker player)|Jimmy Robertson]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||52||27895||49||31400||47||31840||49||30680||52||30120||52||29760||53||30135
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Dechawat Poomjaeng]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||67||16990||64||21110||62||22285||62||24325||60||25765||58||27165||54||29625
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Peter Lines]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||57||22620||57||25655||55||27255||54||29695||55||28335||56||28225||55||29265
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Nigel Bond]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||46||30695||44||32825||49||30600||50||30660||53||30060||53||29215||56||29025
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Dave Harold]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||50||29285||54||28835||54||28345||55||29265||54||29545||51||29760||57||28460
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Matthew Selt]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||44||30965||51||30720||53||28405||53||29845||56||28245||57||27600||58||28280
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Aditya Mehta]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{IND}}||73||13360||74||15180||73||17210||64||23210||63||24850||63||25750||59||27770
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Gerard Greene]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{NIR}}||56||23145||56||25990||56||27240||59||27300||61||25540||62||25755||60||27555
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jimmy White]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||55||25225||55||27235||57||27025||57||27585||59||26665||61||25855||61||27155
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Thepchaiya Un-Nooh]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||69||15715||70||16600||70||17870||71||21070||71||22070||69||22970||62||26530
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Pankaj Advani]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{IND}}||74||13230||73||15250||71||17630||67||22130||66||23690||64||24090||63||26450
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Steve Davis]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||51||28270||52||29890||50||30510||51||30510||58||27710||60||26590||64||26280
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Scott Donaldson]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||89||7110||81||13200||81||14830||80||17190||76||20350||76||20750||65||25670
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ian Burns (snooker player)|Ian Burns]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||68||15960||68||18480||66||20110||70||21150||69||23150||66||23550||66||25570
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Robbie Williams (snooker player)|Robbie Williams]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||79||11460||79||13890||75||16220||69||21340||67||23500||65||23900||67||25220
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Barry Pinches]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||62||20415||66||20260||67||19105||68||21365||70||22245||73||21960||68||24660
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[James Wattana]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||61||21215||61||22075||64||21215||63||23435||65||24355||68||22995||69||24175
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Sam Baird]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||81||10940||80||13345||77||15725||79||17325||78||19725||78||20125||70||23705
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Luca Brecel]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{BEL}}||72||13500||71||15770||72||17600||72||19640||72||21440||70||22340||71||23300
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mike Dunn (snooker player)|Mike Dunn]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||63||19590||63||21120||63||21730||61||25430||64||24790||67||23530||72||23290
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Paul Davison]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||75||13110||72||15430||78||15710||74||18770||74||20570||72||21970||73||23290
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Zhang Anda]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||77||11910||76||14730||80||15010||75||18570||75||20370||75||20770||74||23090
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Michael Wasley]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||80||11420||77||14660||74||17190||76||18230||77||19990||77||20390||75||22610
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Liam Highfield]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||76||13050||69||16740||69||18010||73||19550||73||20750||74||21150||76||22110
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|{{nowrap|[[Thanawat Thirapongpaiboon]]}}|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||71||14140||75||15025||76||16065||77||18105||79||19305||79||19705||77||21025
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Adam Duffy]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||60||21235||58||23195||61||22845||65||23205||68||23205||71||21985||78||20535
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Chen Zhe]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||78||11890||78||14050||79||15320||78||17780||80||18420||80||18820||79||20140
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Craig Steadman]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||83||10105||83||12265||83||13175||83||15575||82||16575||82||16975||80||19695
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Tony Drago]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{MLT}}||82||10350||82||12980||82||14250||82||16150||81||17550||81||17950||81||19270
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Joel Walker (snooker player)|Joel Walker]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||90||5890||89||9060||89||10330||88||12230||86||14630||84||16030||82||19090
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Gary Wilson (snooker player)|Gary Wilson]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||94||4110||96||5740||91||10440||89||13600||87||15000||83||18160
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Stephen Lee (snooker player)|Stephen Lee]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||21||44335||27||43200||33||38880||38||36120||47||32960||54||29200||84||18100
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Li Yan (snooker player)|Li Yan]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||84||9360||85||10570||88||11480||84||15040||83||15680||83||16080||85||17740
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[David Grace (snooker player)|David Grace]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||88||7905||88||9785||85||12105||85||13505||84||15065||86||15465||86||16785
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Daniel Wells (snooker player)|Daniel Wells]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||87||8170||84||10860||84||12330||86||13370||85||14810||85||15710||87||16670
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Martin O'Donnell (snooker player)|Martin O'Donnell]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||86||8340||87||9860||86||11680||87||13080||87||14080||88||14480||88||16000
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[David Morris (snooker player)|David Morris]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{IRL}}||129||{{sort|98|0}}||95||4060||92||6990||93||8530||90||12690||89||13590||89||15250
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Kyren Wilson]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||101||2380||93||6800||90||10700||92||12060||90||12460||90||13420
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Simon Bedford]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||85||8345||86||10415||87||11675||89||11675||91||12315||91||12315||91||12315
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Michael Leslie]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||94||3890||93||5820||94||6460||94||8300||94||10100||94||10500||92||12160
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Sean O'Sullivan (snooker player)|Sean O'Sullivan]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||91||5590||90||7360||90||8630||92||10170||93||11610||92||11610||93||12010
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jamie O'Neill (snooker player)|Jamie O'Neill]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||93||4060||91||6190||91||7100||95||8140||95||9580||95||10480||94||11440
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Li Hang (snooker player)|Li Hang]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||97||2970||98||4440||98||6200||96||8440||96||9340||95||11360
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Noppon Saengkham]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||107||1960||110||2240||109||3780||104||6020||101||6920||96||9780
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Alex Davies (snooker player)|Alex Davies]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||99||2670||101||3510||97||6410||99||7050||99||7450||97||9670
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Stuart Carrington]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||102||2330||107||2690||100||5890||97||8130||97||8530||98||9490
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Lyu Haotian]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||104||2160||109||2440||102||5580||102||6220||103||6620||99||8980
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[John Astley (snooker player)|John Astley]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||98||2830||97||4660||101||5700||98||7500||98||7900||100||8860
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Andrew Pagett]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||100||2580||102||3490||105||4890||103||6090||104||6490||101||8450
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Joe Swail]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{NIR}}||148||{{sort|98|0}}||106||1970||99||3810||99||6010||100||6650||100||7050||102||8370
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Stephen Hendry]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||58||22175||65||20275||68||18015||81||17095||88||13935||93||11520||103||7660
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ross Muir]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||112||1460||106||2730||104||4890||105||5890||105||6290||104||7610
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Chris Wakelin]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||114||1320||112||1960||112||3360||107||5800||107||6200||105||7520
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Hammad Miah]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||105||2130||105||2770||103||5170||106||5810||106||6210||106||7170
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Andrew Norman]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||131||{{sort|98|0}}||109||1770||104||2970||108||3970||108||5170||108||5570||107||6890
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Elliot Slessor]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||108||1820||111||2100||107||4000||109||5000||109||5400||108||6720
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Passakorn Suwannawat]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||92||5590||92||5950||95||6230||96||6630||101||6630||102||6630||109||6630
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Vinnie Calabrese]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{AUS}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||113||1460||108||2500||110||3540||110||4980||110||5380||110||6340
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Chris Norbury]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||119||760||115||1670||111||3470||111||4910||111||5310||111||6270
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Lee Page]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||110||1570||113||1850||113||2890||114||3530||115||3930||112||5250
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ratchayothin Yotharuck]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{THA}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||188||0||128||280||117||2320||116||3320||113||4220||113||5180
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Allan Taylor (snooker player)|Allan Taylor]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||120||760||116||1670||114||2710||115||3350||116||3750||114||5070
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Fraser Patrick]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SCO}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||116||920||119||1200||118||2240||118||3240||119||3640||115||4960
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ryan Clark (snooker player)|Ryan Clark]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||115||1210||118||1490||116||2530||113||3530||114||3930||116||4890
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[James Cahill (snooker player)|James Cahill]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||117||760||117||1600||115||2640||117||3280||117||3680||117||4640
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Cao Xinlong]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||124||360||124||360||121||2120||121||2760||118||3660||118||4620
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Mohamed Khairy]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{EGY}}||96||1410||103||2170||103||3430||106||4470||112||4470||112||4470||119||4470
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Robin Hull]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{FIN}}||119||{{sort|98|0}}||149||0||126||280||120||2120||119||3120||120||3520||120||4080
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jak Jones]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{WAL}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||118||760||120||1040||122||2080||122||2720||121||3120||121||4080
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Alex Borg]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{MLT}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||129||0||125||280||123||1680||123||2320||123||2720||122||4040
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Alexander Ursenbacher]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{SUI}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||182||0||183||0||126||1040||124||2040||124||2440||123||3400
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Patrick Einsle]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{GER}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||111||1480||114||1760||119||2160||120||2800||122||2800||124||3160
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ahmed Saif]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{QAT}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||169||0||127||280||125||1320||125||1960||125||1960||125||2360
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Jin Long (snooker player)|Jin Long]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||122||360||122||360||124||1480||126||1480||126||1480||126||2040
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Khaled Belaid Abumdas]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{LBY}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||130||0||129||400||127||1360
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Shi Hanqing]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{CHN}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||121||360||121||360||127||720||127||720||127||720||128||720
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Lee Spick]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{ENG}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||175||0||176||0||128||640||128||640||128||640||129||640
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Hossein Vafaei]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{IRI}}||97||360||123||360||123||360||129||360||129||360||130||360||130||360
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Igor Figueiredo]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{BRA}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||137||0||140||0||141||0||142||0||142||0||142||0
|-
| style="text-align:left;"|[[Ben Judge]]|| style="text-align:left;"|{{AUS}}||95||3560||96||3560||100||3560||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}||{{sort|999|}}||{{sort|99|}}
|}

==Notes==
{{refbegin}}
*{{note label|rev1|a|a}} Revision 1 was used for the seeding of the [[2013 Wuxi Classic|Wuxi Classic]], [[2013 Australian Goldfields Open|Australian Goldfields Open]], [[European Tour 2013/2014 – Event 1|Bulgarian Open]], [[Asian Tour 2013/2014 – Event 1|Yixing Open]] and [[2013 Six-red World Championship|Six-red World Championship]].&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web|title=Calendar 2013/2014|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/staticFiles/21/bc/0,,13165~179233,00.pdf|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|work=worldsnooker.com|accessdate=30 April 2013|archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/6HWIR5A59|archivedate=20 June 2013}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{note label|rev2|b|b}} Revision 2 was used for the seeding of the [[2013 Shanghai Masters|Shanghai Masters]] and [[2013 Indian Open|Indian Open]].&lt;ref name="Seeding points"&gt;{{cite web|title=2013/14 Calendar|url=http://www.worldsnooker.com/page/Tournaments/FullCalendar|publisher=[[World Professional Billiards and Snooker Association]]|work=worldsnooker.com|accessdate=21 July 2013|archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20140219095838/http://www.worldsnooker.com/page/Tournaments/FullCalendar|archivedate=19 February 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;
*{{note label|rev3|c|c}} Revision 3 was used for the seeding of the [[2013 International Championship|International Championship]].&lt;ref name="Seeding points"/&gt;
*{{note label|rev4|d|d}} Revision 4 was used for the seeding of the [[2013 UK Championship (snooker)|UK Championship]].&lt;ref name="Seeding points"/&gt;
*{{note label|rev5|e|e}} Revision 5 was used for the seeding of the [[2014 German Masters|German Masters]], the [[2014 World Open (snooker)|World Open]], the [[2014 Masters (snooker)|Masters]] and the [[2014 Snooker Shoot-Out|Snooker Shoot-Out]].&lt;ref name="Seeding points"/&gt;
*{{note label|rev6|f|f}} Revision 6 was used for the seeding of the [[2014 Welsh Open (snooker)|Welsh Open]] and the [[2014 China Open (snooker)|China Open]].&lt;ref name="Seeding points"/&gt;
*{{note label|rev7|g|g}} Revision 7 was used for the seeding of the [[2014 World Snooker Championship|World Championship]].&lt;ref name="Seeding points"/&gt;
{{refend}}

==References==
{{reflist|2}}

{{Snooker world rankings}}
{{Use dmy dates|date=June 2014}}
{{Use British English|date=June 2014}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Snooker world rankings 2013}}
[[Category:Snooker world rankings|2013]]
[[Category:2013 in snooker|Rankings 2014]]
[[Category:2014 in snooker|Rankings 2013]]</text>
      <sha1>7ildat4gy7dl8g93yts1ajz5ioq3i8h</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>St.GIGA</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>21602549</id>
    <revision>
      <id>869020237</id>
      <parentid>869018909</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-15T22:19:05Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Mvcg66b3r</username>
        <id>23889012</id>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="30763">{{Use mdy dates|date=October 2018}}
{{Infobox Radio station
|name             = St.GIGA
|image            = St.GIGA_logo.svg
|city             = [[Akasaka, Tokyo]]
|area             = Japan
|slogan           = ''I'm here. — I'm glad you're there. — We are St.GIGA.''
|frequency        = 11.80420GHz
|format           = [[Biomusic]], [[ambient music|ambient]], [[jazz]], [[classical music|classical]], [[New-age music|new-age]]
|language         = Japanese
|airdate          = [[1990 in radio|April 2, 1990]] 
|last airdate = [[2007 in radio|October 1, 2007]] &lt;br&gt;({{Age in years and months|1990|4|2|2007|10|1}})
|facility_id      = BS5
|callsign_meaning = '''[[Pulse-code modulation|PCM]]'''&lt;br/&gt;JO33-BS-TAM1→JO23-BS-TAM1&lt;br&gt;'''Data Broadcast'''&lt;br&gt;JO33-BS-TDM1→JO23-BS-TDM1&lt;ref&gt;''[https://web.archive.org/web/20000920073937/http://www.stgiga.co.jp/info_2/CO_info/corp_info.htm 会社案内]''. St.GIGA. Archived on September 20, 2000.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;!-- After they change the satellite to BS-4 from BS-3, Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications forced them to change callsign. Please see this clip at 1:26-&gt; http://youtu.be/S9P1ISfPbsA?t=1m26s --&gt;
|owner            = [[WOWOW]]
|website          = {{webarchive | url=https://web.archive.org/web/20030528034550/http://www.stgiga.co.jp | date=May 28, 2003 | title=StGIGA.co.jp}}
}}

{{nihongo|'''St.GIGA'''|セント・ギガ|Sento.GIGA|lead=yes}} was a [[satellite radio]] company that was formed as a subsidiary of [[satellite television]] company [[WOWOW]] and later became semi-independent, forming a [[keiretsu]] with its parent.&lt;ref name=kchistory&gt;Chan, Koko. ''[https://archive.is/20030529103308/http://www5d.biglobe.ne.jp/~chankoko/soundgiga.html St.GIGA Sound of the Earth]''. Via [[Internet Archive]].&lt;/ref&gt; Using the [[Broadcasting Satellite (Japanese)|BS]] network to broadcast [[digital radio]] via [[direct broadcast satellite]] as a test on November 30, 1990, St.GIGA became the world's first Satellite Digital Audio Broadcast Corporation.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://srad.jp/story/03/09/30/002224/ さよならセント・ギガ]''. SRAD.jp. September 30, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=mamoru&gt;Mamoru, Sakamoto. ''[http://www.aa.alpha-net.ne.jp/mamos/digital/pcm.html PCM音声放送デッドヒートのゆくえ（St.GIGA開局前夜] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/67LVL0OrY?url=http://www.aa.alpha-net.ne.jp/mamos/digital/pcm.html |date=May 1, 2012 }}''. Alpha-Net. October 2, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt; Regular broadcasting began March 30, 1991,&lt;ref name=mamoru/&gt; and by September 1, St.GIGA adopted the commercial-free concept proposed by producer Hiroshi Yokoi and began to charge a broadcasting subscription fee.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite web | url=http://stgiga.jp/gallery/g-2.htm | title=セント・ギガ ギャラリー ● スクリーン・ミューター | language=Japanese | archiveurl=https://www.webcitation.org/67LVLdrs2?url=http://stgiga.jp/gallery/g-2.htm | archivedate=May 1, 2012 | publisher=St.GIGA | accessdate=November 15, 2018}}&lt;/ref&gt;

Following a period of financial difficulties and as part of an agreement with [[Nintendo]], from between April 1995 and June 2000, St.GIGA broadcast digitally encoded video games to owners of [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|Super Famicoms]] with the [[Satellaview]] attachment.&lt;ref&gt;Kameb. ''[http://www.f3.dion.ne.jp/~kameb/satella/st_prg/st_prg.htm スーパーファミコンアワー番組表] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/67LVML1fI?url=http://www.f3.dion.ne.jp/~kameb/satella/st_prg/st_prg.htm |date=May 1, 2012 }}'' The Satellaview History Museum. February 12, 2008.&lt;/ref&gt; Satellaview broadcasts were limited in distribution to Japan alone,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://blogsimages.skynet.be/images_v2/002/525/891/20060417/dyn006_original_450_691_pjpeg_2525891_9beba3cbc16b52839c5403eccbfd840e.jpg Sega, Nintendo et la Télevision...] {{webarchive|url=https://archive.is/20120718074600/http://blogsimages.skynet.be/images_v2/002/525/891/20060417/dyn006_original_450_691_pjpeg_2525891_9beba3cbc16b52839c5403eccbfd840e.jpg |date=July 18, 2012 }}''. C+. p42. Retrieved March 1, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; however through St.GIGA's services Nintendo broadcast a large number of rare ''[[wikt:裏|ura]]'' and ''[[gaiden]]'' versions of some of its most popular franchises such as ''[[The Legend of Zelda (series)|The Legend of Zelda]]'', ''[[Mario]]'', and ''[[Kirby (series)|Kirby]]''.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://csd.varlew.net/satellaview.php Crash Course on the Satellaview System]''. Chrono Series Database. Retrieved March 1, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://console-news.dcemu.co.uk/30-great-gaming-world-records-184500.html 30 Great Gaming World Records]''. Console Hardware News. February 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://blogs.ign.com/Hyrule-Times/p3 Retrospective: BS Zelda]''. [[IGN]]. June 8, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://myweb.tiscali.co.uk/superfamicom/satellaview.html Super Famicom Central: Satellaview] {{webarchive|url=https://web.archive.org/web/20070114160603/http://myweb.tiscali.co.uk/superfamicom/satellaview.html |date=January 14, 2007 }}''. Super Famicom Central. Retrieved March 1, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; With the exception of ''[[BS Fire Emblem: Akaneia Senki]]'', these games have never been re-released and can only be played today via incomplete emulation.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.blamethecontrolpad.com/bsx/bsx2.htm Broadcast Satellaview - X] {{webarchive|url=https://www.webcitation.org/67LVULae4?url=http://www.blamethecontrolpad.com/bsx/bsx2.htm |date=May 1, 2012 }}''. BlameTheControlpad. Retrieved March 1, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==Satellite history==
Broadcast between March 11, 1990 and November 28, 2007, St.GIGA has undergone a number of changes of both carrier satellite and broadcast band. The following is a condensed history of these changes:&lt;ref name=stgighist&gt;''[https://web.archive.org/web/20130227122523/http://www.stgiga.jp/history.htm セント・ギガの歴史]''. StGIGA.jp. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
*April 2, 1990 - St.GIGA is founded.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://web.archive.org/web/20010726233007/http://www.nikkei.co.jp/news/sangyo/20010725CAHI052525.html BSラジオ放送のセント・ギガ、民事再生法申請]''. Nikkei New Media. July 26, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;
*St.GIGA began broadcasts on BS-3ch in 1990 via the [[BS-2a]] satellite.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://web.archive.org/web/20080905163754/http://www.transmitter-frequencies.com/sat-6989.php Satellite Frequency from BSAT 1A,2A]''. Transmitter-Frequencies.com. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
*August 1991 - St.GIGA switched to the [[BS-3b]] satellite, and in September it began broadcasting on BS-5ch&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*April 23, 1995 - Broadcasts begin to the [[Super Famicom]] add-on, [[Satellaview]].
*April 1999 - Nintendo withdraws support.&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*June 30, 2000 - Last Satellaview broadcast.&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*On December 1, 2000, St.GIGA began simultaneous broadcasts on Radio 333ch (Data broadcasting via 633 and 636ch)&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.geocities.co.jp/WallStreet/4015/bsdatalist.html 衛星データ放送]''. 文字放送・データ放送・インタラクティブ放送. Retrieved November 24, 2014.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;[https://web.archive.org/web/20010212071824/http://www.stgiga.co.jp/DATA/data.htm セント・ギガ 衛星データ放送]. St.GIGA. Archived on February 12, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;
*March 21, 2003 - St.GIGA becomes Club COSMO.&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*October 1, 2003 - Club COSMO sold to WINJ&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*2005 - Club COSMO's 5ch broadcasts became analog (March 31) and the switch to 333ch was completed (May 10)&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*2006 - WINJ begins St.GIGA rebroadcasts&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;
*On November 28, 2007 all affiliated broadcast bands are terminated and the satellite broadcast certificate is revoked.&lt;ref name=stgighist/&gt;

==Concept==
In 1990 the established Japanese [[satellite television]] company [[WOWOW]] decided to expand their services into the field of [[satellite radio]]. The core management team made the executive decision to create a subsidiary named St.GIGA. The name was selected by a popular poll of "[[Vox populi|persons on the streets]]" because the executives agreed that they knew nothing about music. In deciding whom to hire as director for the subsidiary, {{nihongo|Hiroshi Yokoi|横井宏}} (who had recently designed the successful [[J-Wave|J-Wave FM]]) was selected as an innovator in the field.&lt;ref name=kchistory/&gt;

Soon after accepting the position, Yokoi crafted a radical proposal for the station concept. The initial reaction at WOWOW was skeptical; however within a few months of traditional satellite radio broadcasts, Yokoi's concept was given probationary adoption, and Yokoi was subsequently given full discretion to shape the company's future.&lt;ref name=kchistory/&gt;

===Yokoi's "Tide of Sound"===
Under Hiroshi Yokoi's direction, the St.GIGA station motto became "I'm here. — I'm glad you're there. — We are St.GIGA."&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IxX6rClbpR4 セントギガの例の台詞]''. St.GIGA. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s0VA2_gm5CA&amp;feature=related 【BS-5ch】衛星デジタル音楽放送 St.GIGA　その１]'' St.GIGA. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; This is a reference&lt;ref&gt;Murasaki. ''[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/St-GIGA/concept.htm Proguramming Concept]''. Retrieved February 15, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; to [[Kurt Vonnegut]]'s ''[[The Sirens of Titan]]'' in which the alien life forms called [[Harmonium (fictional creature)|harmoniums]] communicate using only the phrases "Here I am." and "So glad you are."&lt;ref&gt;[[Kurt Vonnegut|Vonnegut, Kurt]]. ''[[The Sirens of Titan]]''. Random House, Inc. 1959. p 189. 1998. {{ISBN|978-0-385-33349-8}}&lt;/ref&gt; Strongly influenced by the works of Kurt Vonnegut and Kevin W. Kelley's ''The Home Planet'',&lt;ref name=tte&gt;''[http://www.thinktheearth.net/recommended/recommend.html Recommended]''. ThinkTheEarth. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; Yokoi's original concept proposal for St.GIGA would break new ground for broadcast communication methodology.

In accordance with Yokoi's conception, St.GIGA's broadcasts initially followed no externally fixed (or artificial) timetable. Rather they were based upon the cyclical motif of a 24-hour "[[tide table]]"&lt;ref name=toop&gt;Toop, David &amp; Réveillon, Arnaud. ''[https://books.google.com/books?id=s1JNNhZGZFcC&amp;pg=PA164&amp;lpg=PA164 Ocean of Sound: ambient music, mondes imaginaires et voix de l'éther]''. Editions Kargo. Pp. 164-5. 2000. {{ISBN|2-84162-048-4}}&lt;/ref&gt; where broadcast themes were approximately matched to the current tidal cycle according to the [[rule of twelfths]] throughout the 24-hour broadcasting period.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/g-3.htm セント・ギガ ギャラリー ● タイムテーブル]''. StGIGA.jp. May–December 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/image/voice8_t.JPG Colors of Seasons]''. St.GIGA. September 1, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/book-7.jpg 夢の潮流 -St.GIGA編成総論横井宏著 発行所]'' St.GIGA. Apdx 4. September 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Under this innovative schedule, the station broadcast a variety of primarily ambient music programs including {{nihongo|''Music Tide''|音楽潮流|Ongaku Chōryū}}, various jazz programs,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://stgiga.jp/mj061026-1.htm Midnight Jazz Hank De Mano Quartet 「in concert」他]''. StGIGA.jp. October 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://stgiga.jp/mj061026-2.htm Midnight Jazz - Judy Bailey Trio/Quintet 「My Favourite Things」 他]''. StGIGA.jp. October 26, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt; and {{nihongo|''Tide Table''|タイド・テーブル|Taido . Teburu}} (featuring live sound-broadcasts of the ocean shore). The beginnings and ends of programs were not clearly demarcated and instead utilized the unprecedented {{nihongo|"Tide of Sound"|音の潮流|Oto no Chōryū}} method where songs of one genre would gradually flow into and intersperse with the songs from the prior genre until the new genre became predominant.&lt;ref name=kchistory/&gt; The intent, according to Yokoi was to allow the listener to relax in a wave of sound "like a baby sleeps in the womb." &lt;ref name=toop/&gt; "Tide of Sounds" broadcasts operated under a principle of "No [[Radio advertisement|Commercials]], No [[DJ]]s, No [[News|News Broadcasts]], No [[Talk radio|Talk]]." Unlike most commercial-driven radio broadcasts, this was made possible for St.GIGA due to its reliance on a subscription [[Digital Audio Broadcasting]] (DAB) service. In order to receive this DAB service, the subscriber was required to obtain a special decoder, to pay an initiation fee, and subsequent monthly fees.&lt;ref&gt;Valenti, Gregory. ''[http://heinonline.org/HOL/Page?collection=journals&amp;handle=hein.journals/amuilr8&amp;div=22&amp;size=2&amp;rot=0&amp;type=image Digital Audio Broadcasting: An International Perspective on Compact-Disc Quality Radio]''. 8 [[Washington College of Law#Publications|Am. U. J. Int'l L. &amp; Pol'y]] 273, 289, 295-7 (1992).&lt;/ref&gt; "Tide of Sounds" broadcasts often took the form of high-quality digital recordings of [[biomusic|nature sounds]] accompanied by [[spoken word]] narration by an [[voice acting|actor]] as the "Voice."&lt;ref name=StGNews8b&gt;''[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/image/voice8_b.JPG St.GIGA NEWS]''.  St.GIGA. September 1, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; Throughout the life span of "Tide of Sounds" broadcasts, the part of the "Voice" would be played by a number of notable Japanese poets including Ryo Michiko among others.&lt;ref&gt;Michiko, Ryo. ''[http://ryomichico.net/bbs/voice.html Voice／寮美千子の詩]''. Retrieved February 19, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; "Voice" performances often consisted of all new poetry composed specifically for the show.

St.GIGA also broadcast its B-mode audio programming (a series of all [[classical music]] broadcasts) over analog broadcasting frequency bands that were shared with its parent, the [[satellite television|satellite broadcasting]] company [[WOWOW]].

Highly artistic and experimental, the St.GIGA sound became extremely popular within certain segments of the population, and the station was recognized for its innovative concept, unique vision, and nonstandard methodology.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.soundbum.org/sekai/02komazawa.html INTERVIEW ： 音のある世界で MDと風鈴を持って、山へ Vol. 2 　駒沢敏器さん]''. SoundBum. November 25, 1998.&lt;/ref&gt; Fan publications such as ''BSFan Journal'' and ''G-Mania'' sprang up to publish details of the music and to report on the ambient, mood, and electronic scene that was burgeoning in Japan.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/St-GIGA/bsfan.htm ＢＳfan誌（共同通信社）連載記事]''. June 1992 - January 1993.&lt;/ref&gt; To this day numerous fan groups, trading groups, and collectors with an emphasis on St.GIGA's musical products exist online.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.geocities.co.jp/NatureLand-Sky/7044 St.GIGA Soundstream Fan Club]''. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

The initial popularity of the music funded trips by St.GIGA [[biomusic]] recorders to travel abroad to record at such exotic locations as [[England]], [[Canary Islands]], [[Mikonos]], [[Venice]], [[Bali]], [[Tahiti]], [[Martinique]], Hanson Island ([[British Columbia|BC]]), and [[Maui]].&lt;ref&gt;[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/image/style_24.JPG St.GIGA CREW'S]. St.GIGA. p. 25-26. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Murasaki. ''[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/St-GIGA/style.htm St.GIGA Stylebook]''. February 1, 2001.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=stylebookv2&gt;''St.GIGA stylebook''. Vol. 2, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt; St.GIGA was also able to release a number of thematic books including the multi-volume ''St.GIGA Stylebook'', {{nihongo|''Current of dreams: An introduction St.GIGA programming''|Yume no choryu: St.Giga hensei soron}} (containing the full text of Yokoi's original concept proposal&lt;ref name=tte/&gt;), and {{nihongo|''Trends in Dreaming - St.GIGA's Hiroshi Yokoi's General Office''|夢の潮流 -St.GIGA編成総論横井宏著 発行所}} (also released on VHS&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/book-2.jpg 夢の潮流 -St.GIGA編成総論横井宏著 発行所]''. StGIGA.jp. October 28, 1991.&lt;/ref&gt;). Later thematic films were sold including ''Traveling with St.GIGA'' (1999)&lt;ref&gt;''[http://yutakakawasaki.hp.infoseek.co.jp/info/2001.htm SPUTNIK SPACELINES／Tokyo Designers Block 2002　LIVE EVENT@SPUTNIK DOME]''. Tokyo Designers Block 2002. Retrieved March 1, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; and ''Sound and Vision'' (2007)&lt;ref&gt;Nishimura, Yoshiaki. ''[http://www.livingworld.net/essays/nish_061225 St.GIGA]''. LivingWorld.net. December 25, 2006.&lt;/ref&gt;

{{quote box | align=right | width=25% | quote=St. Giga and other satellite radio broadcasters found it hard to attract paying subscribers as Japan's recession made consumer reluctant to invest in the expensive antennas and tuners needed to pick up satellite broadcasts.| source=''Billboard Magazine'', July 23, 1994&lt;ref name="St.Giga Billboard v106n30"/&gt;}}

St.GIGA sold a variety of products ranging from program guides&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/g-4.htm セント・ギガ ギャラリー - ● プログラムガイド]''. StGIGA.jp. Retrieved February 19, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; to "sound calendars"&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/g-7.htm セント・ギガ ギャラリー - ● サウンドカレンダー]''. StGIGA.jp. Retrieved February 19, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; to fragrances.&lt;ref&gt;{{ cite web | url=http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/g-8.htm | title=セント・ギガ ギャラリー - ● 地球の香り | deadurl=yes | archiveurl=https://web.archive.org/web/20120220121209/http://www.stgiga.jp/gallery/g-8.htm | archivedate=February 20, 2012 | publisher=St.GIGA | accessdate=May 26, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt; The company also released a number of CDs under St.GIGA's own label as well as a variety of foreign labels such as the [[Hearts of Space]],&lt;ref name=StGNews8b/&gt; and music by [[Deep Forest]].&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/image/voice12_b.JPG Quest for Saint]''. St.GIGA. 1993.&lt;/ref&gt;

The market for ambient music and its related forms was not as strong as initially anticipated, and demand was impacted by Japan's recession. By 1994, the station was beginning to face serious financial difficulties, resulting in drastic changes in programming.&lt;ref name="St.Giga Billboard v106n30"/&gt;

==Satellite Data broadcasting==
[[File:BSSuperMario.png|thumb|200px|right|Between April 23, 1995 and June 30, 2000, St.GIGA broadcast video game data for such games as ''[[BS Super Mario USA]]'' which were only playable with [[Nintendo]]'s [[Satellaview]] subsystem.]]
{{main|Satellaview}}

{{cquote |Nintendo expects to sell 2 million [Satellaview] adapter/cassette packages a year.}}

{{quote box | align=right | width=25% | quote=Unlike St. Giga's regular programming, the new data service will feature paid advertising.  Nintendo president Hiroshi Yamauchi [said] that Nintendo expects to sell 2 million adapter/cassette packages a year.| source=''Billboard Magazine'', July 23, 1994&lt;ref name="St.Giga Billboard v106n30"/&gt;}}

By 1994, St.GIGA's financial difficulties resulted in the cutting back of "Tide of Sound" broadcasts.  The company's portion of the subscription-funded audio broadcasts were to be replaced under subcontract by an all new series of advertising-funded Satellite Data broadcasts, managed under the "rescue" and executive control&lt;ref name="Nintendo drops"/&gt; of [[Nintendo]], St.GIGA's largest shareholder at 19.5%.&lt;ref name="St.Giga Billboard v106n30"&gt;{{ cite journal | last=McClure | first=Steve | title=Japan's St. Giga to broadcast Nintendo Games | work=[[Billboard (magazine)|Billboard]] | volume=106 | number=30 | pages=78, 84 | date=July 23, 1994 | url=https://books.google.com/books?id=YAgEAAAAMBAJ&amp;pg=PA78&amp;dq=billboard+magazine+july+23,+1994 | accessdate=May 26, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Vedwa, Niraj. [http://www.nasscom.in/upload/34735/NirajVedwa_GlobalcompetitiveIT.ppt "Indian I.T. – Challenges for Global Competitiveness"]. IIFT-NASSCOM Seminar. December 13, 2004&lt;/ref&gt;

Beginning on April 23, 1995, St.GIGA broadcast video-game-related data to owners of the [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|Super Famicom]]'s  [[Satellaview]]&lt;ref&gt;{{cite patent|US|6611957}}&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.freepatentsonline.com/6611957.html Start Signal for a Computer Program in a Network Environment with Start Signal of Time Information, Program ID and CM Data]''. FreePatentsOnline.com. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.google.com/patents?id=2BEPAAAAEBAJ&amp;printsec=abstract#PPA1,M1 Technique for Executing a Software Program in Response to a Received Start]''. Google Patents. October 28, 2003.&lt;/ref&gt;&lt;ref name=communications&gt;''スーパーファミコンアワーの可能性と未来''. Saterabyu Tsuushin. Vol. 5. 1995.&lt;/ref&gt; peripheral created by [[Nintendo]].  This device bolts onto the underside of the Super Famicom&lt;ref&gt;''[http://myweb.tiscali.co.uk/superfamicom/satellaview.htmlSuper Famicom Central]''. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; in a manner similar to the later [[Nintendo 64DD]]'s attachment to the [[Nintendo 64]] and the [[Game Boy Player]]'s attachment to the [[GameCube]]. Only released to the Japanese market, the Satellaview acted as a [[satellite modem]],&lt;ref name=snesperipheralindex&gt;''[http://www.gamersgraveyard.com/repository/snes/peripherals/satallaview.html Satallaview]'' The SNES Peripherals Index. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; allowing players to download broadcast data.  The resulting games were then stored on requisite specialized rewritable storage cartridges at an additional launch price of 14,000 yen ($143).&lt;ref name="St.Giga Billboard v106n30"/&gt;

The broadcast content ranged from video-game-related Satellaview news and specific interest journals such as {{nihongo|''Game Tiger's big House''|ゲーム虎の大穴|Gemu Tora no OoAna}} to expansion data for popular Super Famicom games (including, for example, ''[[Chrono Trigger#Related media|Chrono Trigger]]'') and all new video game releases including titles in such flagship series as ''[[BS Zelda|The Legend of Zelda]]'', ''[[Super Mario Bros. 2#BS Super Mario USA|Super Mario]]'', and ''[[Kirby (series)#History|Kirby]]''.&lt;ref name=snesperipheralindex/&gt; Additionally, a number of these broadcasts featured an updated version of St.GIGA's earlier "Tide of Sounds" "Voice," now called {{nihongo|"[[Satellaview#SoundLink|SoundLink]]"|サウンドリンク}}, with which St.GIGA [[voice acting|voice actors]] would provide a live vocal track to accompany games, setting plot and describing in-game goals.

Due to the rewritability of the cartridges, the fact that "SoundLink" broadcasts were not downloaded to the game cartridges but rather were streamed live during the noon-2AM&lt;ref&gt;Sinhonggyun. ''[http://www.rapa.or.kr/korean/data/kdt01b1210sh.htm 한국전파 진흥협회]'' Korean Aerospace University. Retrieved February 19, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; ''Super Famicom Hour'' broadcasting time, and because the broadcast game data have never been rereleased by Nintendo, these games have become extremely rare. The subculture of collectors and enthusiasts that has grown online have exerted much effort engaged in electronic [[archaeology]] by extracting old data from heavily rewritten data cartridges in order to faithfully reproduce the games via emulation.&lt;ref&gt;''[http://board.zsnes.com/phpBB2/viewtopic.php?p=184890&amp;sid=c97a28782289bd22e190bef4adddc12e bsnes v0.038 released]'' ZSNES Board. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;
&lt;!--Please note this reference is used to demonstrate the existence of the subculture that exists and as such only the fact of its existence is cited, not the content of the page--&gt;

Aside from St.GIGA's "SoundLink" or broadcasts accompanying the transmission of data for its {{nihongo|"Soundlink Games"|サウンドリンクゲーム}}, St.GIGA also broadcast a wealth of information on talk shows and celebrity idols, including a variety show.&lt;ref name=communications/&gt; Broadcast times were fitted to match the schedules of students, and the station's audience demographics shifted radically much to the disappointment of the station's former ambient music fans. Before long the station had ceased transmissions of all "Time &amp; Tide" programs (those featuring [[new age]] music) including the much-admired {{nihongo|''Tidal Currents''|潮の潮流|Shio no Chōryū}}, Fan publications such as ''BSFan Journal'' became replaced by more populist publications like {{nihongo|''[[Satellaview Tsūshin|Satellaview Communications Magazine]]''|サテラビュー通信|Saterabyu Tsuushin}},&lt;ref&gt;Kameb. ''[http://www.f3.dion.ne.jp/~kameb/satella/st_tushi/st_tushi.htm サテラビュー通信記事紹介]''. June 1995-May 1996.&lt;/ref&gt; and St.GIGA focused all energies on Satellaview transmissions.&lt;ref name=historyasahi&gt;''[http://www.asahi-net.or.jp/~vw6y-mk/v35/other/radio/radio.html I'm here. I'm glad you are there. - サヨナラSt.GIGA]''.&lt;/ref&gt;

Satellaview transmissions continued uninterruptedly with only a single recertification&lt;ref&gt;''[http://www.soumu.go.jp/joho_tsusin/pressrelease/english/mpt-news/vol10_8.pdf MPT’s Regular Personnel Changes]''. Biweekly Newsletter of the Ministry of Posts and Telecommunications, Japan. Vol. 10, No. 8. p.2. August 2, 1999. ISSN 0917-169X&lt;/ref&gt; between 1995 and April 1999.  Carrying a "cumulative debt of 8.8 billion yen" as of March 1998, a Reuters report on August 21, 1998 indicated St.GIGA's rejection of Nintendo's debt management proposal as well as the broadcaster's failure to apply for renewal of its governmental satellite license. This resulted in the withdrawal of Nintendo's five executive staff, and the withdrawal of all current and proposed programming plans by Nintendo, Kyocera, and "many content providers", that had been intended for launch in 2000; though Nintendo's 19.7% ownership portfolio remained intact.&lt;ref name="Nintendo drops"/&gt; St.GIGA continued Satellaview broadcasts after this point; however, the company could only broadcast reruns of games previously transmitted as Nintendo had discontinued its supply of new original content as of March 1999. Facing economic difficulties again, St.GIGA discontinued its Satellaview broadcasts on June 30, 2000 in order to return focus to music broadcasts as had been done prior to the Nintendo deal.&lt;ref name="Nintendo drops"&gt;{{ cite web | url=http://belarus.8m.com/1/cnn060001.html  | title=Nintendo drops satellite plan - Video-game company halts plan to deliver games directly to homes | publisher=Reuters | date=August 21, 1998 | accessdate=May 26, 2014}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==Later years and current status==
By 2001, St.GIGA was nearly bankrupt and entered into merger talks with {{nihongo|WireBee Inc.|株式会社ワイヤービー|Kabushikigaisha Waiyabi}} with which it became associated for the remainder of its lifespan.&lt;ref&gt;''[https://web.archive.org/web/20020619232027/http://nnm.nikkeibp.co.jp/nnm/2002/06/NNM20020610_193.html St.GIGA，民事再生手続きが終了，ディジタルBS放送専業で再出発]''. Nikkei New Media. June 10, 2002.&lt;/ref&gt; On March 21, 2003, following the death by cancer of director Yokoi,&lt;ref name=historyasahi/&gt;&lt;ref&gt;Nagano, Doranka. ''[http://www.chartdrunker.info/archives/2007-05.html 第２２６回ランキング]''. May 25, 2007.&lt;/ref&gt; St.GIGA was rechristened {{nihongo|Club COSMO|クラブコスモ|Kurabukosumo}} under the leadership of {{nihongo|Shinichi Matsuo|松尾信一}}. Broadcasts continued until October 1, when the company was forced to sell its licensing rights to World Independent Networks Japan Inc. (WINJ). WireBee immediately began bankruptcy procedures,&lt;ref&gt;Tadayuki, Mitani [http://www1.odn.ne.jp/~cjq24190/insolvent%20cases/24civil02.html 2-4(2)160 衛星デジタル音楽放送（株）]. The Mitani Tadayuki Law Office. January 18, 2010.&lt;/ref&gt; and all recording instruments and 241 tapes of nature sounds were auctioned off at open market for a total divided sale price of ¥5 million. Discussions concerning Club COSMO's involvement under WINJ's oversight in a new reality show were circulated briefly at this time, however to date no such show has been produced.

In 2006, WINJ began broadcasting reruns of St.GIGA's original "Tide of Sound" and "Time &amp; Tide" broadcasts during a 2PM-4PM time slot,&lt;ref&gt;''[http://stgiga.jp/ttable/pdf.htm WINJタイムテーブル]''. StGIGA.jp. Retrieved February 20, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt; however on November 1 of the same year these broadcasts were suspended on the pretext of broadcasting equipment maintenance. The program was scheduled to resume in the 2007 fiscal year, however on November 14, 2007, [[Hiroya Masuda]] the Minister of [[Ministry of Internal Affairs and Communications|Internal Affairs]] revoked the broadcasting certificate under Act 54 of Article 24 of the Japanese General Broadcasting Statute.&lt;ref&gt;Nihei, Shigeru. ''[http://law.e-gov.go.jp/htmldata/S25/S25HO132.html#1000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000005202400000002000000000000000000 放送法（昭和二十五年五月二日法律第百三十二号）]''. Retrieved February 18, 2009.&lt;/ref&gt;

==See also==
* [[Satellaview]] - The Nintendo peripheral that allowed player to download BS Games directly to its [[Super Nintendo Entertainment System|Super Famicoms]]
* [[WOWOW]] - Parent [[satellite television|satellite broadcasting]] [[TV Station]].
* [[Broadcasting Satellite System Corporation]] - The company that controlled the satellites from which St.GIGA broadcast, and its current fleet of Japanese broadcasting satellites.

==References==
{{Reflist|30em}}

==External links==
* [http://stgiga.jp St.GIGA Forever - St.GIGA homepage] {{ja icon}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://www.stgiga.co.jp www.stgiga.co.jp at the Internet Archive] {{ja icon}}
* [http://www.sensorium.org/sensingjapan/interview/kawasaki/profile/kawa_pro.html St.GIGA program director, Yoshihiro Kawasaki's personal website] {{ja icon}}
* [[:ja:寮美千子|ja.wikipedia article on "Voice" performer Ryo Michiko]] {{ja icon}}
* [http://ryomichico.net/bbs.html Harmonia - Ryo Michiko's personal website] {{ja icon}}
* [https://web.archive.org/web/20110715045112/http://www.partialmusic.com/live/video_popup.php/Robert_Newcomb_Music_Resume.pdf?filename=dl_file&amp;gallery=true&amp;id=3&amp;download=1&amp;start_dl=1 "Tide of Sound" performer, Robert Newcomb's page]
* [http://www2k.biglobe.ne.jp/~murasaki/St-GIGA.htm Revival of St.GIGA's "tidal sound"] {{ja icon}}

{{Nintendo developers}}

[[Category:DAB ensemble]]
[[Category:Digital radio]]
[[Category:Nintendo]]
[[Category:Radio stations established in 1990]]
[[Category:1990 establishments in Japan]]
[[Category:Radio stations disestablished in 2007]]
[[Category:2007 disestablishments in Japan]]
[[Category:Defunct radio stations in Japan]]
[[Category:Satellite radio stations]]
[[Category:Super Nintendo Entertainment System]]
[[Category:Defunct companies of Japan]]</text>
      <sha1>0boy3nlpqawjew79zilccti78nsvrnf</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The King Incorporated</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>36444109</id>
    <revision>
      <id>781879523</id>
      <parentid>754555983</parentid>
      <timestamp>2017-05-23T19:28:12Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Cydebot</username>
        <id>1215485</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot - Moving category Non-fiction books about colonialism to [[:Category:History books about colonialism]] per [[WP:CFD|CFD]] at [[Wikipedia:Categories_for_discussion/Log/2017_April_26]].</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2495">{{Infobox book
| name             = The King Incorporated:&lt;br&gt;Leopold the Second in the age of trusts
| image            = File:TheKingIncorporated.jpg
| caption          = First edition
| author           = [[Neal Ascherson]]
| title_orig       = &lt;!-- if not in English --&gt;
| translator       = 
| illustrator      = 
| cover_artist     = 
| country          = United Kingdom
| language         = English
| series           = 
| subject          = 
| genre            = 
| publisher        = [[George Allen &amp; Unwin]]
| pub_date         = 1963
| english_pub_date = 
| media_type       = Print
| pages            = 310
| isbn             = 1-86207-290-6
| oclc             = 
| dewey            = 923.1493
| congress         = 
| preceded_by      = 
| followed_by      = The Polish August : the self-limiting revolution
}}
'''''The King Incorporated''''' was the first history book published by award-winning Scottish journalist and historian [[Neal Ascherson]] exploring the course of the [[Congo Free State]] from its foundation to annexation, as well as the role of [[King Leopold II]].

''The King Incorporated'' was first published in 1963 (three years after the Congo's independence from Belgium) and has been reprinted in eight editions. The 1999 edition (published by [[Granta]]) modified the book's title to ''The King Incorporated: Leopold the Second and the Congo,'' omitting the reference to [[Trust (business)|trusts]].

==Reception==
The work was described by ''[[The Guardian]]'' as "a fascinating account of Leopold II of Belgium and his extraordinary attempt to integrate the rapacious exploitation of a personal colony with a version of 19th-century European kingship."&lt;ref&gt;{{cite journal|last=Wroe|first=Nicholas|title=Neal Ascherson: Romantic nationalist|journal=The Guardian|date=12 April 2003|url=https://www.theguardian.com/books/2003/apr/12/history.politics}}&lt;/ref&gt; The celebrated British historian [[A.J.P. Taylor]] also praised the work.&lt;ref&gt;{{cite book|last=Ascherson|first=Neal|title=The King Incorporated|year=1999|publisher=Granta Books|pages=Cover}}&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:King Incorporated, The}}
[[Category:1963 books]]
[[Category:British biographies]]
[[Category:History books about colonialism]]
[[Category:Congo Free State]]
[[Category:History books about the Belgian Congo]]
[[Category:Books about Leopold II of Belgium]]
[[Category:Works about the European colonisation in Africa]]


{{Africa-hist-book-stub}}
{{poli-bio-book-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>sfgy32koz3qxng9972pc6ht9kvmoyqc</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>The Middelburg Gazette</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>41337811</id>
    <revision>
      <id>827172163</id>
      <parentid>780498407</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-23T04:27:57Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>I dream of horses</username>
        <id>9676078</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Cleaning up a [[WP:RANPP|randomly generated list]], added [[CAT:O|orphan]] tag using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="603">{{Orphan|date=February 2018}}

{{italicstitle}}
'''''The Middelburg Gazette''''' was a newspaper that operated from Middelburg in the [[Cape Colony]], for a brief period from 1876 to 1881.&lt;ref&gt;K.Vernon: ''Penpricks: The Drawing of South Africa's Political Battlelines''. New Africa Books, 2000. p.19.&lt;/ref&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Middelburg Gazette, The}}
[[Category:Defunct newspapers of South Africa]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1876]]
[[Category:Publications disestablished in 1881]]
[[Category:1876 establishments in the Cape Colony]]


{{SouthAfrica-newspaper-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>qw2awh428ceqkh8e1bbqkcktndohtyt</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Zans</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>34854768</id>
    <revision>
      <id>868131593</id>
      <parentid>837255282</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-11-10T05:37:31Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <ip>70.51.45.46</ip>
      </contributor>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="778">{{about|the Zan speakers|the singular|Zan (disambiguation)}}
{{Georgians}}
The '''Zans''' ({{lang-ka|ზანები}}, {{lang|ka-Latn|zanebi}}) or '''Chans''' ({{lang-ka|ჭანები}}, {{lang|ka-Latn|chanebi}}) are a subethnic group of [[Georgians]] from [[Kartvelian peoples|Kartvelian family]], speaking the [[Zan languages]].

* '''[[Kartvelian peoples]]'''
**[[Georgians]]
***'''Zans''' ([[Mingrelians]] and [[Lazs]])
**[[Svans]]

==See also==
* [[Kartvelian languages]]
* [[Zan languages]]

{{Caucasus-ethno-group-stub}}
{{Kartvelian languages}}
{{Ancient Georgians}}
{{Peoples of the Caucasus}}

[[Category:Ethnic groups in Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Ancient peoples of Georgia (country)]]
[[Category:Sub-ethnic groups]]
[[Category:Peoples of the Caucasus]]</text>
      <sha1>5hfz6qaj7hjbg3p5hcy3lwva3zz0p0k</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>Äripäev</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>4443118</id>
    <revision>
      <id>827949649</id>
      <parentid>744167801</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-02-27T18:14:44Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>Tom.Reding</username>
        <id>9784415</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Fix [[:Category:Pages using deprecated image syntax]]; [[WP:GenFixes]] on, using [[Project:AWB|AWB]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="2508">{{Infobox newspaper
| name                 = Äripäev
| logo                 = Äripäev logo.svg
| logo_size            = 250px
| image                = 
| caption              = 
| type                 = [[Daily newspaper|Daily]]
| format               = [[Berliner (format)|Berliner]]
| owners               = [[Bonnier Group]]
| publisher            = [[AS Äripäev]]
| editor               = 
| chiefeditor          = Meelis Mandel
| assoceditor          = 
| maneditor            = Igor Rõtov
| newseditor           =
| managingeditordesign =
| campuseditor         =
| campuschief          =
| opeditor             = 
| sportseditor         = 
| photoeditor          = 
| staff                = 
| foundation           = {{Start date|df=yes|1989}}
| political            = 
| language             = [[Estonian language|Estonian]]
| ceased publication   = 
| headquarters         = [[Tallinn]], [[Estonia]]
| circulation          = 
| sister newspapers    = 
| ISSN                 = 1406-2585
| oclc                 = 
| website              = [http://www.ap3.ee www.ap3.ee]
}}
'''''Äripäev''''' ([[Estonian language|Estonian]] for "Business Day") is an [[Estonia]]n financial [[newspaper]] in tabloid format. It was founded in 1989&lt;ref name=eur&gt;{{cite book|title=Central and South-Eastern Europe 2004|url=https://books.google.com/books?id=5J_gAU8c9NIC&amp;pg=PA263|accessdate=4 June 2016|year=2003|publisher=Psychology Press|isbn=978-1-85743-186-5|page=263}}&lt;/ref&gt; by ''[[Dagens Industri]]'', a leading Swedish financial [[newspaper]]. The first issue of ''Äripäev'' was published on 9 October 1989. Until May 1992 ''Äripäev'' was published once a week, until February 1996 three times a week. Since 1996 ''Äripäev'' has been published five times a week.&lt;ref name="eur"/&gt;

The newspaper belongs to AS Äripäev, which is owned by the Swedish family-owned media group [[Bonnier Group|Bonnier]].

==References==
{{Reflist}}

==External links==
*{{official website|http://www.ap3.ee}} {{et icon}}
*[http://www.bbn.ee Business news from Baltic States] {{en icon}}

{{Bonnier}}

{{coord|59|25|1.15|N|24|44|29.32|E|region:EE|display=title}}

{{use dmy dates|date=February 2012}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Aripaev}}
[[Category:1989 establishments in Estonia]]
[[Category:Bonnier Group]]
[[Category:Business newspapers]]
[[Category:Estonian-language newspapers]]
[[Category:Media in Tallinn]]
[[Category:Newspapers published in Estonia]]
[[Category:Publications established in 1989]]


{{Estonia-newspaper-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>il9za8b7fm4uasmml032o0xg8bq7c57</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
  <page>
    <title>École Belge de Bujumbura</title>
    <ns>0</ns>
    <id>48363298</id>
    <revision>
      <id>862406889</id>
      <parentid>862360936</parentid>
      <timestamp>2018-10-04T05:20:00Z</timestamp>
      <contributor>
        <username>RussBot</username>
        <id>279219</id>
      </contributor>
      <minor/>
      <comment>Robot: [[WP:DPL|fix links]] to disambiguation page [[Dutch]]</comment>
      <model>wikitext</model>
      <format>text/x-wiki</format>
      <text xml:space="preserve" bytes="1799">{{Underlinked|date=April 2017}}
{{Infobox school
| name = École Belge de Bujumbura
| native_name = 
| address     = Boulevard de Yaranda, Bujumbura, Burundi
| coordinates = {{coord|-3.3938487|29.36024109999994}}
| pushpin_map = Burundi
| website = {{URL|ecolebelge.edu.bi}}
}}
'''École Belge de Bujumbura''' ('''EBB''') or the '''École Belge du Burundi''' is a Belgian international school in [[Bujumbura]], [[Burundi]]. It serves students ages 3–18, in ''maternelle'' (preschool) through ''sécondaire'' (secondary school). The school supports both Francophone and [[Dutch language|Dutch]]-speaking students.&lt;ref name=Home&gt;"[http://www.ecolebelge.edu.bi/ Accueil]" ([https://www.webcitation.org/6cYCMd2g4 Archive]). École Belge du Burundi. Retrieved on October 26, 2015.&lt;/ref&gt; It is a part of the {{Interlanguage link multi|Association des écoles à programme belge à l'étranger|fr}} (AEBE).

==History==
The school opened in September 1965 and the Burundian government recognised the school through a ministerial decree passed on 3 July 1969. The school reopened in 1996 despite an embargo put on the Burundian government.&lt;ref name=Home/&gt;

==Student body==
As of 15 October 2014 the school had 509 students. This was an increase from its October 1996 figure, 233 students.&lt;ref name=Home/&gt;

==References==
{{reflist}}

==External links==
* {{fr icon}} [http://www.ecolebelge.edu.bi/ École Belge de Bujumbura]
{{Bujumbura}}
{{Belgian international schools}}

{{DEFAULTSORT:Ecole Belge de Bujumbura}}
[[Category:Schools in Bujumbura]]
[[Category:International schools in Burundi]]
[[Category:Belgian international schools]]
[[Category:1965 establishments in Burundi]]
[[Category:Educational institutions established in 1965]]

{{Belgium-school-stub}}
{{Burundi-stub}}
{{Africa-school-stub}}</text>
      <sha1>aaukndyfc8lnne75c1k5furi0g2lj8p</sha1>
    </revision>
  </page>
</mediawiki>
